Academia Sinica's September governor's feast lecture begins
中央研究院9月份知事饗宴演讲会开始
Director Wu Chongli of the Secretariat asked us to host
秘书处吴崇李处长 问我们主持
Thank you all for coming to the governor's feast tonight
谢谢大家来参加今天晚上的知事饗宴
Originally, it was because Vice President Huang wanted to come over.
本来是因为进行黄副院长要过来
But because he has other important matters at the moment, he can't come here
但是因为他的临时有其他的要事没有办法过来
So it's just me doing the scraping here
所以就是有我在这边进行刮带
Then tonight's speech should be very exciting.
那今天晚上的演讲应该是很精彩的
The speaker is Mr. Li Zhende from our 11th school.
那演讲人呢是我们的十一所的李珍德李老师
And the theme is when history meets gender
那主题呢是当历史遇上性别
this is teacher li
这是李老师
Bouncing off the fragments of the sixth-century Bhikkhu Yuanni's tombstone in the Reread collection
從復讀所藏六世紀比丘元尼墓碑貨片彈起
Then I still think Mr. Li should be familiar to everyone in the history circle.
那我還是我想李老師在史學界大家對他應該很熟悉
But for me, I think I should introduce Teacher Li a little bit more.
那但是為了我我覺得我應該還是要稍微再介紹一下李老師
Teacher Li has a bachelor's degree in history from National Taiwan University and a master's degree in history from National Taiwan University.
李老師是台大歷史的學士 台大歷史的碩士
Went to the University of Washington in Seattle to obtain a Ph.D. in History
到了美國西雅圖華盛頓大學取得歷史學的博士
Now he is working as a researcher at our Institute of History and Research
那現在是在我們史與所擔任研究員
In fact, I interacted with Mr. Li in many meetings.
那其實在好多的會議裡頭跟李老師的互動交流
He is a very gentle lady with a good personality and very knowledgeable questions.
他是一個非常溫潤的 個性很好 詢問很淵博的一位女士
So what she does is to explore from the perspective of gender
那她本身所做的是從性別的角度來探討
About the legal system between Hantang and medical care
有關於漢堂之間的法律制度 還有醫療的照顧
She has a lot of books and the explanations are very interesting.
她的著作非常的多 而且說明也很有意思
It's called the death of the princess. What you don't know about Chinese legal history
叫做公主之死 您所不知道的中國法律史
He also has another book that is also well known
他也有另外一本著作也很知名
is a woman's history of Chinese medicine
是女人的中國醫療史
Health care and gender among Han tangs
漢堂之間的健康照護和性別
In addition, he has also read many papers
另外他也曾經看有許多的論文
and edited Gender Body and Medical
而且主編了性別 身體和醫療
Academician Liang Qizhi
還有跟梁奇之院士
co-edited women and society and more
合編了婦女與社會等等
In recent years, he is also an Asia
他近年來也是Asia
Editor-in-Chief of the Major
Major的主編
Now Editor-in-Chief of New Historiography
現在是新史學的主編
Because of his personal history
因為他個人在史學方面
So I'm often in many awards
所以我經常在很多獲獎的獎項裡頭
I have seen Mr. Li's name
都看到李老師的大名
including the Distinguished Research Award from the National Science Council
包括像是國科會的傑出研究獎
This is a very important indicator in our science and technology department
這是我們科技部裡頭一個非常重要的指標
In addition, it is also in the Distinguished Talent Lecture
另外也是傑出人才講座裡頭的
It seems like two years ago three years ago
目前好像是兩年前 三年前
Funding is currently in progress
目前正在進行資助
Apparently it is in the current Taiwan historian circle
顯然就是現在的台灣史學界裡頭
very important person
非常重要的人物
Then I won't talk nonsense anymore
那我廢話就不再多說了
Then I will give the stick to Teacher Li
那我就把棒子交給李老師
Mr. Li thank you
李老師謝謝
ladies and gentlemen
各位來賓
thank you so much everyone for tonight
非常謝謝大家今天晚上
Just after the Mid-Autumn Festival, I worked hard to come here
中秋才剛過就很用功的來這邊
Listening to the speech is really admirable
聽演講實在是令人佩服
then i'm glad to be here today
那我很高興今天能夠在這裡
Share it with everyone
跟大家分享一下
actually i think
其實我很覺得
able to receive this knowledge
能夠受到來講這個知識的
miss is to feel very honored
想念是覺得很光榮
Mainly every time I see
主要是每一次我在看到
When this poster of Knowledge Missing came out
知識想念的這個海報貼出來的時候
I feel that each of the above
我就覺得上面每一位
They are all scholars I admire
都是我佩服的學者
i was thinking
我就在想
Hey, what is the extent of this?
欸這個到底是怎麼樣的程度
Only then can we be told
才可以受到來講啊
After working here for 26 years
等了在這邊工作了26年以後
finally it's my turn
終於輪到我了
I feel very honored
我覺得很覺得非常的榮幸
So what I'm going to tell you today is
那今天我要給各位講的這個題目
is when history meets gender
是當歷史遇上性別
The subtitle says to use this
副標題是說用這個
"The Sixth Century Collected by Futu"
《復圖所藏六世紀》
Bhikkhu Yuanning Muzhi collapsed to talk about it
比丘元寧牧志塌片來談
In fact, the main thing is to use this chip
其實主要就是用這個塌片
come be a shadow
來做個影子
Hope to share with you
希望能夠跟各位分享一下
some in recent years
近幾年來的一些
Sex with Women's History
跟婦女史性別
or historical research
或者是歷史研究
on the relevant results
就有關的成果
this should be opened first
這個應該要先開
After opening
開了以後
yes not open yet
對 還沒開
So pressing it won't work
所以按就不會有用
open?
開了嗎
yes to this not to this
是對這個 不是對這個
I'm sorry, thank you
對不起 謝謝
This year is Academia Sinica
今年是中研院
90th Anniversary Celebration
90週年的院慶
It is also the celebration of the 90th anniversary of more than ten institutes
也是十餘所90週年的所慶
Actually 90 years ago
其實90年前
when the unit was established
當這個單位成立的時候
in Chinese history
在中國的歷史上面
basically
基本上來說是
Not long after the May Fourth Movement
才過五四運動沒多久
probably still receiving
大概還在受到
Impact of the May Fourth Movement
五四的風潮的衝擊
under the influence of
跟影響的狀態之下
at that moment
在那個時候
almost
差不多也就是
almost 90 years ago
差不多90年前
From one book to today
由一本到今天為止
are still influential
都還有影響力
everyone may also read
大家也可能都還讀
many teenage friends
很多少年朋友
Young friends, at least I was the same
青年朋友至少我當時也是一樣
When I first came into contact with the study of women's history
剛開始要接觸婦女的歷史研究的時候
a book that will come across
會碰到的一本書
That was around 1926 or 28
那差不多是1926年左右還是28年
It was also a book published almost 90 years ago
也是差不多90年前的時候出版的一本書
Chen Dongyuan's Life History of Chinese Women
陳東源的中國婦女生活史
In the earliest part of that book he was
他在那個書最早的時候是
In fact, it was issued by the Commerce Department
其實是商務運輸館發行的
Later in Taiwan, Taiwan Business also printed
後來在台灣 台灣商務也印了
I own these two
我自己就有這兩本
One is the first teacher of my women's envoy
一本是我的婦女使的啟蒙老師
Teacher Bao Jialing gave it to me
鮑嘉玲老師送我的
When I was a freshman in National Taiwan University
那時候我在台大一年級的時候
he is my mentor
他是我的導師
And he was just coming back from America
而且他那時候只是從美國回來
One year
課座一年
That's still assigned a tutor
那還是被分配了導生
I was lucky enough to be his tutor
我很幸運地就變成他的導生
Then he gave me a copy
那他就送了我一本
this blue leather
這個藍色皮的
I'm still on that desk
我現在還貢在那個書桌上
Later, because of reluctance
那後來因為捨不得
keep touching because it is very old
一直碰 因為很舊
So I went and bought a pink one myself
所以我自己又去買了一個粉紅色本的
Use it to browse, use it to check information
拿來翻看 拿來查資料
There is a passage in this book
這本書裡面有一段話
I was from a very young age of nineteen
我當時從很年輕的十十九歲
I was very impressed when I saw it at the age of eighteen or nineteen
十八九歲看的時候就印象很深刻
He said my book
他說 我這一本書
I'm not trying to support some Holy Mother
不是要撐送什麼聖母賢母
I don't want to push for some empress
也不想推遵什麼女皇帝
Female heroes vent their anger on women
女豪傑給女性出氣
Because most people
因為這一般人大多數的
girls don't matter
女生沒有什麼關係
i just want to point out
我只想指示出來
What kind of gaffe is the idea that men are superior to women
男尊女卑的觀念是怎麼樣的失言
What kind of Zengsheng is the destruction of women
女性的摧殘是怎樣的增勝
What kind of historical regression still weighs on the number of women now
還壓在現在女性之幾倍上的是怎樣的歷史移退
That is to say around 1926 2728
也就是說在1926 2728前後
It is the May 4th movement that wants to overthrow the old tradition
就是五四的風潮要推翻舊的傳統
Then bring new thinking
然後要帶來新的思維
In the process of new atmosphere
新的風氣的過程當中
In fact, women's identity, women's status, women's situation
其實女性的身份 女性的地位 女性的處境
scholars or intellectuals
是當時的學者或者是知識份子
An indicator of great concern
非常在乎的一個指標
So Chen Dongyuan wrote such a book
所以陳東源就寫了這樣一本書
His purpose is to tell everyone
他的目的就是要告訴大家
The lives of women in China are actually very miserable
中國的婦女生活其實是非常悲慘的
He wants to tell everyone the fact
他要告訴大家這樣的一個事實
Then we need to draw everyone's attention, hoping to reform
然後要引起大家注意 希望能夠改革
Then you can have a change of heart
然後可以有一點變心
Right around the time this book was published
就在這個 差不多這個書出版的
around this time
差不多的這個時候
Another thing was actually unearthed in Luoyang
在洛陽其實出土了另外一個東西
that's what we're going to talk about today
這就是今天我們要講的
Wei Gujiang
魏顧江
open it
打開看一下
Wei Gujiang, General Wei Gu Cheji
魏顧江 魏顧車季大將軍
Safety
平安
Wen Dingxing sends his wife the preface
文定行公寄夫人大爵士比丘元尼牧志明秉序
Anyone who can finish reading can be a historian
能夠念得完的人就可以做歷史學家
A man who can eat a mouthful of youth can speak
一口青年都完的人就可以演講
This Mu Zhiming was about 80 or 90 years ago
這個牧志明大概也差不多80、90年前
Unearthed in Luoyang, Henan
在河南洛陽出土
Then he received in
那麼後來他收在
After being unearthed by Fujinen Makishi above
由富士年牧志出土以後上面
There are collapsed pieces, that is, after falling down with this ink tile
有塌片 就是用這個墨瓦塌下來之後
Then this piece is now in the collection
那這個塌片現在收藏在
Academia Sinica Lishi Research Institute
中央研究院立時研究所
It is in the Fujinian library of my unit
就是我的單位的富士年圖書館裡面
Then his size is about
那麼他的這個大小差不多就是
57×57 cm
57×57公分
So this screen actually magnifies it a little bit.
所以這個螢幕其實稍微把它放大了
If you go to Futu to see this collapse
如果你到富圖去看這個塌片的話
It's not that big
其實沒有那麼大
That is to say, its original tombstone was not so big.
也就是它原來的墓碑沒有大到這個地步
But it's a bit big
不過算是一塊還算有一點大
Gravestone with a little weight
有一點份量的墓碑
And then the collapse
然後這個塌片塌下來
On the login of Shi Yu's office, it says
在石瑜所的登錄上面是寫
Sir Yuan Ni Mu Zhiming Bing Xu
大爵士元尼牧志明秉序
It's the front and the back
就是前面是明後面
There is this preface stating that such a person is buried in it
有這個序文說明這樣子一個埋葬在裡面
Then the hostess that Mu Zhiming talked about
然後這個牧志明所講的那個女主人
what kind of person is he
是一個什麼樣子的人
what about his age
那他的年代呢
Because in this place for the second year of Yongan
因為在這個地方為永安二年
So there is a seven-day holiday in November Monokage
所以是即有十一月物影朔七日假生造
So we know that the shepherd
所以我們知道這個牧背
This mu, Muzi was in the second year of Yong'an, and he was in the north.
這個牧 牧子是在永安二年就是北位
It was built in 529, the second year of Yong'an
永安二年529年的時候建造的
so we can know
那因此我們可以知道
This, this, Mu Zhiming, was around that time
這個 這個牧志明是在差不多那個時候
That thing is about the same
那這個東西也是差不多
It is in this turbulent May Fourth
就是在這個風起雲湧的五四
In the process of this trend
這個風潮的這個過程當中
was found trampled
被發現了 被踏了
Later, I received them from 11 libraries.
然後後來收到了十一所的圖書館裡面來
That's what we're talking about here
那這裡面講的這個
In this bhikkhu garden
這個 比丘園裡面
The woman Mu Zhiming talked about
講的這個牧志明講的這個女人
what kind of story is it
是怎麼樣的一個故事呢
Actually I was hoping
其實我本來是很希望
if today was in my class
如果今天是在我的課堂上的話
I will ask the students to read it
我就會請同學們來念一下
break this shepherd's back
斷一下這個牧背
then think
然後念一念
Everyone can be more awake
大家可以比較清醒一點
Then enter the condition
然後進入狀況
But it doesn't look like it's here
不過看起來這邊不見得
They all look old and have white hair and long hair, they are older than me
看起來都是年紀還白髮長長比我還年長
I am too embarrassed to ask everyone to read this Mu Zhiming
我不太好意思叫大家念這個牧志明
But so I figured it out
可是所以我就把它想辦法
Type this into a normal text file
這個建入成一般的文字黨
Hope to let you know more
希望可以讓大家能夠多多了解
at least understand what this is talking about
至少能夠了解這是在講什麼
Let's take a look at the nomination just now
大家看一下剛才那個提名
He said that he is the general of car technology
他說為顧車技大將軍
Ping Shu Written Actions
平書文定行功
Mrs. Ji
季夫人
Grand Jazz Monk Yuan Ning Mu Zhiming continued
大爵士比丘元寧牧志明並續
So just by looking at the title, you can probably guess
所以光看這個題目大概可以猜得出來
the first he was a bhikkhunin
第一個他是一個比丘寧
That is, he is a nun
也就是他是個尼姑
And his bhikkhu ning the monastery where he became a monk
而且他的比丘寧他出家的寺廟
or the temple he belongs to is grand lord
或他所屬的寺廟是大爵士
Great Jazz of Luoyang
是洛陽的大爵士
He died in the identity of the monk Ning Luoyang
他是在洛陽大爵士這個比丘寧的身份上去世的
But this identity is his last identity
可是這個身份呢是他最後的一個身份
not all his identities
並不是他所有的身份
can see ahead of him
可以看得到他前面
one of his identities is
他的其中一個身份是
He is Mrs. Xing Gong Ji
他是行功季夫人
That is to say, a certain line
也就是說是某一個叫行
sacrifice of man
人的人的祭祀
is the palace
就是行宮
In fact, we checked the information
其實我們查了資料
I know it's a row wheel
後知道是行輪
He is the empress of the history of Northwest University
他是北威校文地史後
a very important general
一個非常重要的武將
But it is said that he is also very personable
但是據說他也是非常的風度偏偏
dashing and handsome
瀟灑英俊
There may also be ministerial civil servants
也可以有做載相文官的
such a patient person
這種能耐的一個人
no matter what
不論如何
This round mud made his sacrifice, Mrs. Sacrifice
這個圓泥做了他的祭祀 祭夫人
After becoming the wife of the sacrifice
那當做了祭夫人之後
later he died
後來他去世了
As a bhikkhu Yuanni
他就以比丘圓泥的身份
buried after death
做為去世以後就埋葬了
that this
那這個
What is this Mu Zhiming talking about?
這個牧志明上面講的是些什麼東西呢
First
第一個
Mrs Hui Cunda
夫人會純陀
rule of law
法治至守
Grandson of Emperor Gongzong
公宗頸目皇帝之孫
Rencheng the fifth daughter of King Kang
人成康王之第五女也
So it looks like he belongs to the emperor's family
所以看起來他是屬於皇帝家裡面的人
right
對不對
his father was a certain prince
他的爸爸是某一個親王
he is the prince
他是這個親王
Recognized as Kang Wang's fifth daughter
認成康王的第五個女兒
Then Mu Zhiming, if everyone
那牧志明大家如果
Read a little bit of Mu Zhiming's words
稍微讀一些牧志明的話
Or don't be Mu Zhiming
或者其實不要當牧志明
That is, if there is always the opportunity to attend a funeral
就是如果常常有參加葬禮的機會
like me
像我一樣
then you might
那你可能就
You'll read a lot of stories like this
就會讀到很多這種事略啊
People don't call shapes anymore
現在人不叫形狀了
life story
就是事略就是生平敘述
It's usually very well written.
裡面通常都會寫得非常好的啦
Regardless of whether this child used to
不管這個小孩子以前
when this person was young
這個這個這個人年輕的時候
how to get along with this man
如何的這個男相處
No matter what this person's past
不管這個人過去是怎麼樣的
naughty missile
調皮導彈
But what about in Kinokana is usually good
但是呢在木之名通常很好
Packing fish have poor jobs and poor forests
盤根魚有拙職窮林
are very beautiful
都是非常漂亮的
It looks beautiful and the wind is good
長得又美風這個風之又好
flag from year
旗幟發自條年
rocking boat filet
搖條船魚貫魚
When he was very young and his hair was short
他很年輕的頭髮還很短的時候
smart at a young age
很小的時候就很聰明
And what about his demeanor?
而且他的風采呢
When he tied the heads of two little uncles
在他綁著兩個小舅舅頭的時候
it can already be seen
就已經可以看得出來了
is such a daughter
就是這樣一個女兒
a girl
一個女孩子
Kang Wang loves his father more
康王就他爸爸偏加深愛
It is recommended to pay attention to women
建議重女
love him very much
非常愛他
different from other daughters
跟其他的女兒都不一樣
Long live in the arms never leave the applause
長居懷抱之中不離鼓掌之上
But at the age of seven
可是呢到了七歲的時候
his father died
他爸爸去世
he is very filial
那他非常孝順
know without learning
不學習就知道
father died very loving love hurt
父親去世非常愛愛傷
Qi and blood worry
氣血如憂
cry every day like
每天哭得好像
What comes out is not tears but blood
那個流出來的不是眼淚是血
What I eat seems to be eating the curse karma
吃的好像都是在吃優醜無舍咒業
By the age of fifteen
到了十五歲的時候
Positive is when girls pull their hair up
積極就是女孩子把頭髮攀起來
when you can get married
可以出嫁的時候
Pastor Yan Gui married a man surnamed Mu
嚴規牧師嫁給一個姓牧的
who is the pastor
牧師是誰
In fact, this is from the Northern Wei Dynasty, that is Wei.
其實這個是北魏的就是衛嘛
guard
衛
Then see General Gu Cheji
那看到顧車季大將軍
So I know he too
所以也知道他也是
He is both other people's
他既是人家的既是
His husband, Xinggong, has also passed away.
他的先生行公也已經去世了
Then this Tuoba in the Northern Wei Dynasty
那這個北魏時候的拓拔
They were originally in this ancestor's
他們原來在這個先輩的
His original surname was Tuoba
原來的姓是姓拓拔
Later, because of the Sinicization of the school text
後來因為校文歷漢化的關係
Change to Yuan
改成姓圓
This Tuoba and Mu
這個拓拔跟牧
Both are ancestors, very important
兩個都是先輩非常重要的
military aristocratic group
軍事的貴族集團
Then the two families will Tuoba and Mu
那麼兩家就拓拔跟牧
Yuan Hemu
也後來的圓跟牧
are often married
彼此是常常連姻的
So when he was fifteen
所以他十五歲的時候
she married Mu
就嫁給了姓牧的
then he was very
然後他非常
This is what the shepherds must have
這個都是牧子民一定會有的
very hard
非常的用功做
Female workers are very burdened
女工非常有負擔
The results of it
結果呢
Mr. Mu
姓牧的這位先生
died shortly after
沒多久就去世了
half
良人既是半
Half of his body collapsed
他的一半身體就倒了
what half of the body fell down
什麼一半的身體就倒了
When a woman marries each other, the two become one
就女人嫁給對方以後兩個人合為一體了
after being united
合為一體之後
If the husband dies, the woman will
如果先生去世這個女的就
The other half of the body fell down.
另外那一半身體就倒了嘛
no more
就沒有了
so very sad
所以就非常的難過
he wants to be able to triple
他希望能夠三重
What is the so-called triple?
所謂三重是什麼呢
repeated marriage at home
在家重複出嫁
Repeat Resurrection Baryon
重複 複死 重子
But he had hoped so
可是他本來是希望這樣子的
But his elder brother and wife, King Wenxuan
但是他的哥哥太婦文宣王
The wife of King Wen Xuan is called Yuan Cheng
太婦文宣王叫做元成
It's Yuan Ni's brother Yuan Cheng
就是元妮的哥哥元成
The only duoqing smoke is not allowed
唯一奪情 確煙 不許
against his morals
違背他的道義
Violating Yuan Ni's morality
違背元妮的道義
robbed him of his emotions
清奪了他的情感
Just don't let him triple
就是不讓他三重
that means
那意思就是說
must remarry
一定要他再改嫁
remarry
再嫁
so who will you marry
所以呢嫁給誰
and then the next
然後接下來登場的
This is it
就是這個
Ping Shu Wen Ding Xinggong
平書文定行宮了
General Xiang
文定宮高門聖德裁監將項
I just said that
這我剛剛說了
Everyone thinks it's rich
大家覺得喔 又有文財
There are dancing money
又有舞財
Yun belongs to the relationship between Emperor Wen and Xiao Wenli
運屬文皇跟蕭文利關係
Very good, the air is like the rain Jun Cheng and the two are like the rain
非常好 氣同雨水 俊成兩個像雨水一樣
The joy of rain is not just for men and women
雨水之歡不是只有男女而已啊
It is Mu Zhimingyan who is in the north
就是在這個北位的牧志明眼
You can tell it's like rain
你可以看得出來 其實氣同雨水
Jun Sung is very compatible
就是俊成非常相得
like rain rain like water
如雨水一樣 雨跟水一樣
Mingguanshattered bone speaks good things
冥冠碎骨 講的都是好話
Then this Yuan Ni will be his spouse
然後呢 這個元妮就來做他的配偶
The two of them are as good as a harp and as harmonious as a smoker
他們兩個人 好如琴瑟 和如熏
wisdom
智
Xunzhi, right? Lehui
熏智 對不對 樂慧
He Ru Xunzhi
和如熏智
Unspoken
不言容訴 自同 冰淨
It just shows how good the relationship between the two of them is.
就是說明他們兩個感情好的程度
what does good mean
好的程度是什麼意思
He also has a very good relationship with her husband when he is at home.
他在家之後跟丈夫的關係也非常好
So good, how can the relationship be very good?
好到 怎麼樣會關係非常好呢
look what he did
你看他做了什麼事情
Of course the relationship with her husband will be very good.
當然跟丈夫的關係就會非常好的嘛
The first Fenggu salute
第一個 鳳姑敬禮
He is very hands on to his mother in law
他對他的婆婆非常的手裡
Very respectful and filial to him
非常的尊敬的 孝順他
Treat him like a gangster, Hirohito
把他當成匪洩 克匪洩裕仁
Treat him like nobody else, this girl
把他當成沒有別人了 就是這個姑
mother-in-law good
婆婆 好好的
to honor him
來尊敬他
on the other hand
另外一方面
be mediocre
處世為庸
He is the egg
就是他跟形卵
This Yuan Ni
這個元妮啊
This Mrs. Yuan and the egg
這個元夫人跟形卵
original other concubine
原來的其他的妾
get along very well
也都處得非常好
able to help evil
能夠能協邪於重烈
It's a pleasure to get along with them
就是跟他們能夠相處得很愉快
on the other hand
另外一方面
Son, a prostitute is a man
子 散妓是郎
Chang Shixun
散妓常世遜
There is a shape
有一個形遜
is one of his sons
是一個他的兒子
Is this Yuan Ni's son?
這個是元妮的兒子嗎
it doesn't look like
看起來好像不是
Son Chang Shixun, a casual prostitute
子 散妓常世遜
Yuan can be stronger or stronger
元以可強或還強
Sheng Shan Juan En Qu was home
聖善俱娟恩屈被家
Empathetic and Empress Dowager
慈遜兼後大以身人
out of the dragon
龍於己出
What's the meaning
什麼意思
this is actually
就是這個其實是
Oval
形遜其實是形卵
former wife's son
前一個太太的兒子
Then Yuan Moumou
那麼元某某
Yuan Pure
元純妥
after marriage
嫁過來之後
What about the original son?
對於這個原來的這個兒子呢
see him when he was little
看他很少的時候
no mother
就沒了母親
so love him very much
所以非常的恩愛他
what is the degree of love
愛的一個程度呢
higher than
高出於
more than one's own birth
多過於自己所生的
Just love this season
就是比愛這個季子
love their own children
愛自己生的小孩還要
more grand
隆重還要多
below the level of
的這種程度之下
he lives here
他就跟住在這個
Xinranjia
新亂家
I'm talking about this part
這一段呢就在講
Yuan Chuntuo's life after marriage
元春托在嫁之後的人生
Then what next, he began to think
那接下來呢他就開始想
how does he teach this young son
他怎麼樣來教這個小兒子
What about this season?
這個季子呢
Kim Hiran
他讀詩書金木希蘭
As long as there are poems and books in front of his eyes
只要有詩書到他眼前
also teach this child
還教這個孩子
so beautiful
那麼紅顏主
Director of Gongyan
公顏主任
Start function
入手能功
Yuan Chuntuo can not only read poetry and books
元春托不但會讀詩書
And also work as a maid
而且也做女工
well done too
也做得非常好
any type
任何一種
Sewing and knitting can't be difficult for him
縫的織的事情都難不了他
and he wears clothes
並且他穿衣服
not very weird
不會非常的詭異
to participate
去參加
What about when this idiot sweeps the closet?
這個傻掃櫃室的時候呢
I wear clothes that have been washed many times
都穿這個已經洗過很多次的衣服
Doesn't ask to be glamorous
不會要求光鮮亮麗
means a very economical one
意思就是非常節省的一個
such a woman
這樣子的一個女性
Sex can be a female high school mother for a thousand years
性可以女中一時母儀千載
Should be a very nice woman
應該是非常好的一個女人
The kind of woman who can be the mother of the world
可以做母儀天下的那種女人
can be a woman's guru
可以做女人的宗師
Such a person is like the guru of the female group
女性群體的宗師一樣的這樣的人
In the end, when it comes to the car record, who is it written in the car record?
結果到了車記寫車記是誰
It's messy
就是形亂
after death
去世之後
when died
去世的時候
He is the second widowed
他等於第二次搜寡了
After his death he privately became Fude
去世之後他私成夫德
irreplaceable
業不尋替
This is how the pastor described his richness.
這個都是牧師裡面形容他的富德的
What does that mean
什麼意思呢
when the husband died
丈夫去世的時候
don't cry at night
晚上不哭
only cry during the day
只有白天才哭
Crying at night makes people feel
晚上哭會讓人家覺得
He's just missing his love
他只是在思念他的情而已
like a widow during the day
白天就是好像寡婦
Still thinking about the bed
還在思念這個床地之事
This is obviously for the husband
這個顯然就對於丈夫
That is to say, he is not a very good rich man.
就是說自己不是很好的富人
and there is no way to show
而且也沒有辦法彰顯
husband married a
丈夫娶到一個
being a nice rich man
自己是一個很好的富人
So if it's a nice rich guy
所以如果是一個很好的富人的話
when the husband died
丈夫去世的時候
it is not allowed to cry at night
是不可以在晚上哭的
can only cry during the day
只可以在白天哭
when crying during the day
白天哭的時候
On the one hand, this can be avoided
一方面可以迴避這個
The one who thinks about the room all day long
一天到晚想房間的事情的這種
Two words or two names
二言或二名
On the other hand
另外一方面呢
When you cry during the day, you cry with the public
白天哭的時候等於是跟公眾同哭
Can demonstrate the virtue of the husband
可以彰顯出丈夫的這個德性
or his contributions to the public domain, etc.
或者他在公共領域上面的貢獻等等
but anyway
但是不論如何
privately
這私承夫德
In order to be able to demonstrate the virtue of his husband
他為了要能夠彰顯他丈夫的德性
So he is more irreplaceable
所以他越不尋替
recruit poor and humble
招苦賢卑
then he lamented
然後他感嘆
no life
無一生氣闊
I've been miserable all my life
我一輩子實在很苦啊
two more hard work
再離辛苦兩次
people leave me
都有人離開我
Altair
既才彌他之操
i didn't i'm ashamed
我沒有 我很殘愧
I didn't keep a moral
我沒有守住一個操守
what ethics
什麼操守呢
There is no second such conduct of his
就沒有第二個他的這個操守
It turned out that she was married to Mrs. Mu
就原來已經嫁給慕氏
after death
去世了以後
I was going to be alone and widowed
我本來要一個人要手寡的
As a result, my brother won't let me be widowed
結果哥哥不讓我手寡
I must be marrying
一定要我在嫁
Must be after I get married
一定要我在嫁之後呢
I become another him
我就變成有另外一個他
I am ashamed
我很殘愧
i didn't hold on
我沒有守住
No other one of his worries
沒有另外一個他的這種操心
I am ashamed
又愧不轉之心
also very ashamed
也很殘愧
my heart does not turn
我的心沒有不轉
I turned
我轉了嘛
Because I got on well with Xingchao later on.
因為我後來跟形亂也處得很好
It looks like it's good, doesn't it?
看起來好像是很好這樣子對不對
20 people are so cool, I'm really a lion
爽得20人 我實在是很獅得啊
If you have no virtue, you will serve another
沒有德性才會再去侍奉另外一個
second husband
第二個丈夫 不心塌足
But I didn't care about his family any more.
可是呢 我也沒有再替他的家族心望起來
Which means, in the end, it's just emotions anyway.
也就是說 到終反正就只有情緒
It turns out that the first mother, the child born to the first wife
原來那個第一個母親 第一個太太生的那個小孩
This kind of happiness in life comes from suffering, and the fruit comes from the cause
這種人生樂從苦生 果由因起
Think about it, it's meaningless, don't go through it again
想一想 沒有意思 不要再過了
So sacrifice one's life and get tired of getting out of the body
於是 舍身俗累 脫體法門 氣質愛驚 吸池正水
Looks like he's started reading Buddhist scriptures
脖收金帳 看起來他開始讀佛典了
Guangtong Precepts Six Degrees of Treasure Noisy Precepts Daughter
廣通戒律 珍寶六度 吵戒千金
Treat a thousand pieces of gold as a quarrel ring
把千金當成吵戒
Just think of all his practice, reading the scriptures, open it
就當他這些所有的修行 讀經啊 開開
It's starting to look like he deserves something in return
漸漸的看起來 他應該有所回報
It is he who is cultivating to this matter
就是他在修到這個事情上面
When should something be rewarded? The shadow of the twin scales wears out
應該有所回報的時候呢 雙鱗之影穿滅
Suddenly this practice is a temple
突然這個修行啦 寺廟啦
This kind of shadow of this kind of environment
這個這樣子的一個環境的這種影
It was this shadow that suddenly disappeared.
就是這個影子突然就滅掉了
What do you mean? It means he's not sick himself.
什麼意思 意思就是他自己也沒有生病了
no way to live
沒有辦法活下去了
The third person will appear next
接下去就第三個人出場
who
誰呢
Wei Qing, king of Xihe
西河王魏慶
king of the river
西河王
It's called Yuan Wei Qing
叫做原魏慶的
Priest
牧師之初
and grandson
及婦人外孫
Do you understand
看得懂嗎
understand
看得懂
third person on stage
第三個人出場
Talented Sōsei
宗世才英
Ubukata sokushin
生方即身
base
作手進基
dungeon run
地城蒙潤
Madam dead pen
夫人亡筆
Purchase Ji Miliu
購集彌流
Edom October
以東十月
Stingray Nutrition Junjie Hotel
轟於營陽俊傑別館
etc.
等等
What's the meaning
什麼意思
that is
就是說
Let's talk about him first
前面講他先
His father loved him very much when he was a child
小時候父親很愛他
then at the age of seven
然後七歲的時候
father passed away
父親去世了
he cried virtuously
他很有德性的哭了
like a girl
像個少女一樣
Married at fifteen
到了十五歲的時候嫁給了
The original Tuoba long-term alliance
原拓拔長期聯盟
A family of the military-political alliance
軍政聯盟的一個家族
Then what
然後呢
apparently had a daughter
顯然有生一個女兒
Although the front side
雖然前面那邊
No mention of having a daughter at all
完全沒有提到生女兒的事情
right
對不對
But apparently there is a daughter
可是顯然有生一個女兒
because of that daughter
因為那個女兒
Later she married Yuan
後來又嫁給了姓袁的
So that's what I just said
所以也就說明了我剛剛說的
Yuan and Mu have been married for a long time
袁跟沐之間是長期聯姻的
He married Mu
他嫁給了姓沐的
gave birth to a daughter, of course the surname is Mu
生了一個女兒 當然就姓沐
Later this daughter surnamed Mu married back to Yuan
後來這個姓沐的女兒又嫁回了姓袁的
It's from his own family
就是他自己拓拔娘家的
So another child was born named Yuan Weiqing
所以又生了一個小孩子叫做袁衛慶
Yuan Weiqing when his wife was sick
袁衛慶在夫人生病的時候
I'm working on Xihe Wang and I'm working on a mobile phone
在做西河王 而且做手進機
Dungeon Mengrun looks like it is in Luoyang
地城蒙潤 看起來是在洛陽的一個
It's a very important official, the first official
就是很重要的官員 首成的官員
Then the pastor Xihe Wang Weiqing was the wife's grandson at the beginning.
那麼西河王衛慶 牧師之初就是夫人的外孫
the son of his daughter
就是他女兒的兒子
He is a master, how good he is
是宗師英才 如何如何的好
Then the lady got sick when she went to live with him
那麼夫人去住在他那邊的時候生病了
The result is in his, in Yuan Weiqing's
結果就在他的 就在袁衛慶的
Nutritious Bacteria Sister's Annex One of his mansions
營養菌姐別館 他的一個公屬館
If you die in this villa, you will die there
這個別莊裡面去世了 就死在那裡
Dead grandson Momowa Zisu all heart
死孫毫默瓦 子素皆心
That is, no matter who is a monk
就是不管是出家的人
Ordinary people who have not left home
還是沒有出家的一般人
Everyone loves it
大家都非常的愛好
Because he should be able to be a female high school mother for a thousand years
因為他應該可以女中一時母儀千載
how did you die
怎麼去世了呢
just cry
就哭
before dying
臨終要死的之前
dying suddenly
突然臨終醒悟
Clearly lost
分明遺脫
Don't bury his sleepy heart of cultivating Taoism
另別葬他所已睡修道之心
What's the meaning
什麼意思
I've already said it
我已經臉講了
twenty minutes
二十分鐘了
What's the meaning
什麼意思
Zhu Chenyan, since you are here
朱晨諺 既然你來了
You said there's a microphone over there
你說那邊有麥克風
take a look
看一下
yes
沒錯
He woke up on his deathbed, woke up suddenly
他臨終的時候醒過 突然醒過來
Looks like he died while living at his grandson's house
看起來他應該是住在外孫的家裡的時候去世的
before dying
要去世之前
Woke up suddenly and asked to say
突然醒過來就要求說
He doesn't want to follow the one in front
他不要跟前面的這個
Don't bury what he meant, yes
別葬他所的意思 對
Just don't marry any of the previous husbands
就不要跟前面任何一個丈夫
buried together
葬在一起
Don't be buried with the expert
不要跟行家的葬在一起
because this
因為這個
don't be buried with the pastor
不要跟牧師葬在一起
Because that was her ex-husband after all.
因為那個畢竟是之前的丈夫了
Seems to make sense
好像也還說得過去
but no matter what
可是不論如何
He lived in the little child born to the priest
他是住在牧師所生的小孩子裡
home is his grandson's home
家裡 就他的外孫家
So it's a little bit unreasonable
所以也是有一點點說不過去
Then don't be buried with the expert
那不要跟行家的葬在一起
Pedestrians buried together
行人葬在一起
Of course, it was very different from the custom at that time.
當然就跟當時的習俗是很不一樣的
At that time, many couples and funeral mothers
當時其實很多夫婦和葬母
It's the couple buried together
就是夫婦葬在一起的
This means that we will always be united, etc.
這樣表示永接同心等等等等
but he doesn't want
但是他不要
He specifically stated that he would not
他特別說明他不要
Please don't bury his heart that he cultivated at the age of
令別葬他所以歲修到之心
The results of it
結果呢
Sons and daughters are respectful and dare not stop
兒女適尊不敢為止
they can't stop listening to him
他們不能不聽他的
I agreed
就答應了
It's fine after you promise
答應之後就好
I will be buried in a certain day and a certain year
某一天某一年就葬下去了
Buried next to Luoyang
葬下去葬在洛陽的旁邊的一個
Beside Maan Hill
馬安小山的旁邊
This front is the so-called narrative
這個前面就是所謂的敘
is the narrative
就是敘文
Because of Mu Zhiming
因為牧志明那個
This civilization is actually a famous text like a singing language
這文明其實是像唱歌語的名文嘛
four words four words four words
四個字四個字四個字
Then we need to explain why there is this sequence later.
那前面要說明為什麼後面會有這個序
will have this name
會有這個名
so its words about
所以其詞約
what about the word
來 這個詞呢
Of course, just sing him like this, how, how, how
當然就唱他這樣一聲 如何如何如何
the last word says
最後這個詞說
Of course, these are what we just talked about
當然前面這些就是我們剛剛講的
In fact, the sequence of the content is almost the same.
其實序跟序的那個內容也差不多啦
It means to tell him how he is doing, okay?
意思就是在講他一聲怎麼樣的好嘛
but in the end
可是最後呢
Life, birth and fortune
生命 生福命處 咒短 消長
One return to trickle, no repeated injury
一歸細流 不反復傷
human life is short
人的生命都是短的
The time after death is longer than the time in life
死掉以後的時間是比活著的那段時間長的
Twin Scales In-laws Wind Cup Baiyang
雙鱗親家 風杯白陽
even so
雖然如此
the man who wrote his name
寫目致名的這個人
still hope
還是希望
Will lie in the blue night, there is no absolute way
會臥藍晚 無絕分方
that is
就是說
his people are buried here
他的人葬在這裡
set up a cup
立了一個杯
wrote the name
寫了目致名
And it also shows that his voice
而且也說明了他的一聲
There are also flowers beside
旁邊也種了花
Although life is short
雖然呢人生很短
time gone
走了的時間
not alive time
就不活著的時間
Time is much longer than living time
時間是比活著的時間來的長很多
those these
那些這些
these creams and more
這些霜等等
is the wind
就是風
these trees
這些樹
these trees next to
旁邊的這些樹
when it comes to winter
碰到冬天的時候
Maybe it's frosting too
可能也就結霜了
it's cold
也就冷了
The whole north wind blows up
整個的這個北風吹起來
it feels like weeping
感覺很像在悲哭一樣
probably so
大概是這樣吧
There's nothing wrong with the atmosphere
這氣氛是這樣沒有錯
but at the end
可是到結尾的時候呢
He wants this guy who writes wood to say
他希望這個寫木製的這個人說
Paint Wolan Wan
繪臥藍丸
I mean these flower beds
就是說這些花床啊
paved these
鋪了這些
those who planted these flowers
種植了這些花的這些
these flowers beside the wood
在木旁邊的這些花
Hope to be forever apart
希望能夠永遠分方無絕
don't stop
不要停下來
can still last forever
還是能夠綿綿留長下去
equal to this
等於對這個
one of the dead
死去的這個人的一個
Blessings to the future world
未來世界的祝福吧
such a world
這樣子的一個世界
In fact, this wooden name
其實這個木製名
You see I was hoping to invite you over here
你看我本來是希望在這邊請
audience come
聽眾來
to share
來分享
I read this
讀的這個心得了
As a result, I did not expect that I would
結果沒想到我自己就
It took 20 minutes to finish it
花了20分鐘把它講完了
Who is the author of this wooden name
這個木製名的作者是誰
whoever wrote it
就誰寫的
honestly
老實說
we don't really know
我們其實並不很清楚
because he didn't
因為他沒有
In the end, there was no withdrawal and said who was so and so
最後沒有提款說是誰誰誰
do so so so
做誰誰誰
wait wait wait
刻等等等等
But you from this content
不過你從這個內容
You should be able to guess
各位應該可以猜
He should have been commissioned by someone from the Xingya family.
他應該是行卵家的人委託人家做的
Because he wrote only two or three sentences about the marriage with the pastor
因為他寫跟牧師的那個婚姻只有兩三句
Lian Yuan didn't even talk about having a daughter.
連元先有女兒這件事情連講都沒講
If he hadn't died in his grandson's house in the end
如果不是他最後是死在外孫家裡面的話
Maybe we'll never know that he ever
可能就我們完全不會知道他曾經
Had a child in the first marriage
在第一段婚姻裡面還生過一個小孩子
But the second marriage is a lot
但是第二段婚姻就寫很多
And dad doesn't just write about his own virtues
而且爸不只寫他自己的德性
How to serve this mother-in-law
怎麼樣侍奉這個婆婆
How to follow these eggs
怎麼樣跟行卵的這些
Other concubines get along well
其他的妾處得好
how to teach journalists
怎麼樣教導 記者
At the same time, it also discusses how the eggs will be judged and supervised.
同時也把行卵是如何的裁監將相
such an amazing person
這樣了不起的一個人
In fact, there are profits in the practice of egg guarding.
其實行卵衛術裡面是有賺的
After checking, he was indeed very handsome and silly, etc.
去查以後確實說他是非常英俊小傻等等
But this pastor is actually the pastor of Yuanquan Camel
但是這個牧師其實是源泉駝的牧師
But he also brought a sum of eggs
可是卻把行卵也帶上一筆
said some good things about him
多說了他一些好話
At the same time, the news is that this son
同時也把這個行訊就是這個兒子
also said some good things
也說了一些好話
What about the other side?
那另外一方面呢
the virtues described in
裡面所形容的這些德性
basically looks like
基本上看起來
All belong to Chinese
全部都是屬於漢話以後
It is the virtue after the Confucian dialect of the Han dialect of Beiwei Tuoba
就是北衛托巴士漢話儒家話以後的德性
For example, it should be Pomponla and it should be cut in half.
比如說應該是蓬蓬拉應該要對切好啊
Should be able to love Long even though it wasn't born by me
應該要能夠雖然不是我生的我也要愛隆於幾初
I love him more than I ever gave birth to myself
比我自己生的還要愛他啦
Or be able to work as a female worker and read teachers' books Li Yue
或者要會做女工啦會讀師書 李月啦
From these angles it would appear that
從這些角度看起來應該
This shepherd, although we do not know who the author is
這個牧之民雖然我們不知道作者是誰
Basically, it should be the home of eggs.
基本上應該還是行卵的家就行家
It is the people in his second husband's family
就是他的第二個人丈夫的家裡面的人
Please someone write a shepherd like this
拜託人來寫這樣子的一個牧之民
I don’t know how you feel about this shepherd
這個牧之民我不知道各位看了以後有什麼感覺
If you've seen this shepherd, start reading with us
如果你們看了這個牧之民跟我們一開始讀
It was about the same time that this shepherd was unearthed
差不多同就是這個牧之民出土的時候
We know the age of the shepherds 1920's 30's
我們知道有這個牧之民的這個年代1920 30年代
According to the life history of Chinese women we just read by Chen Dongyu
跟我們剛剛讀陳東語人的中國婦女生活史說
I don't want to see some queens and heroines
我不想要看到什麼女皇帝女豪傑
I think how miserable it is for a woman's male director to be inferior
我覺得女人的男主任女卑是多麼的悲慘啊如何如何如何
Read these two things at about the same time
差不多同一個時間讀這兩樣東西
Because this thing has been kept in the father and son's library
因為這個東西呢一直放在父子裡的圖書館
Not many people know about this blockbuster
就這大片沒有很多人知道
often in the library
常在圖書館裡面
In fact, until the first time I knew about this thing
其實一直到我第一次知道這個東西
Of course
當然了
Probably decades after it was unearthed
大概出土之後大概幾十年以後
Received on an untouched South American wooden tread
才收在一個未經南美朝的木製的踏片
or in these books
或者是這些籍子裡面
but no research
但是沒有研究
really have research i see
真正有研究我看
I'm probably the first
大概我就是第一個人
when I was writing my doctoral dissertation
就是我在寫博士論文的時候
After returning from the United States, I went to the Fox Union Library to check information
從美國回來到福斯聯圖書館去查資料
then i found
然後我發現
There's a wooden tread like this
有這樣子一個木製踏片
This is the life of this woman
這裡面寫著這個女人的人生
when i was in college
跟我在大學的時候
The life history of Chinese women sent to me by the teacher who read Ba Zhuo
讀八卓的老師送我的中國婦女生活史裡面
So I see that women's lives actually seem to be different
所以我看到女人生活其實好像不太一樣
so i was curious
所以我就覺得很好奇
i want to know
我想要知道
How exactly do women live their lives?
具體的女人到底是怎麼樣過日子
what happened
發生了什麼樣的事情
Does this wooden name tell us something
這個木製名是不是可以告訴我們一些
In the life history of Chinese women
在中國婦女生活史裡面
Aspects that will not be touched
比較不會觸及到的面向
Then in the 1990s I wrote my doctoral dissertation
那再來90年代我寫博士論文
The 90s were all 24 seasons
90年代就是都是24季的時候的事情
in the 90s
90年代的時候
I finished my doctoral dissertation
我把博士論文寫完了
I used a story like this
我就用了這樣子的一個故事
Recently, due to the need for more in-depth analysis
最近因為需要做比較深入的分析
because you are participating in different anthologies
因為你是參加不同的文集
project translation project etc.
計畫翻譯計畫等等
I put the wooden name very carefully
我就很仔細的把這個木製名
read it again
重新再讀一次
After reading it, you will find that
一讀以後就會發現確實
When living with Chinese women
跟中國婦女生活時
In fact, women's lives presented
其實所呈現的女性的生活
may be different
可能是有不一樣的地方
what is a different place
一個不一樣的地方是什麼
First
第一個
He married twice
他又嫁兩次啊
that's where we are
就是我們在
May Fourth
五四的時候
struggle here
在這邊奮鬥
to struggle
要拼搏的
one of them is
其中有一個就是
Needle survey
針節排訪
offhand day problem
副手節的問題
this was popular at the time
這個是當時流行
not popular
不是流行
a painful thing
當時痛苦的一件事
That is to say, the painful thing at that time
就是說當時切身覺得痛苦的事
But Chinese history has not always been
可是中國歷史並不是一直都是
What I saw on May 4th
五四所看到
their previous state
他們之前的那個狀態
in what we found
在我們所發現的
Yuanchun camel's wooden inside found
元春駝的木製裡面發現
There was a time in Chinese history
中國歷史上曾有一段時間
women's situation
女性的處境
or the form of his life
或他生活的形式
It's actually different
其實是不一樣
or the status of his marriage
或他的婚姻的狀況
In fact, it's not the hand festival at home
其實並不是手節在家
no wrist
沒有手節
Widowed
手寡
get a needle survey
拿到一個針節排訪
can be at home
可以在家
Does that mean he has a higher status?
就表示他地位比較高嗎
uncertain
不一定
because he said he
因為他說他
His brother is the only one who is passionate
他哥哥唯一多情啊
He wants wristbands
他想要手節啊
My brother won't let him hold hands
哥哥不讓他手節啊
we look again
我們又看
So it's not what he said
所以也不是他自己講的
If Won Chun asked Key to stand up today and say
如果元春托今天Key當站起來說
No, in fact, I really wanted to revalue
沒有 其實我當時確實也有要再價值
It's just that I can't help it if they just write it like this
只是他們就這樣寫我也沒辦法
I do not know
那就不知道了
This will only be known after the chicken
這就要靠起雞以後才知道
How can we get the ancients to tell us the truth?
要怎麼樣能夠叫古人來跟我們講真心話
But even if the ancients really come back
不過就算古人真的回來
They tell the truth we don't know
他們會講真心話我們不曉得
because we are now face to face
因為我們現在面對面的人
Not necessarily telling the truth, right?
也不見得都是講真心話對不對
How can you believe that the one with the chicken came back
你怎麼會相信起雞的那個回來的
just tell the truth
就是講的是真的
This is getting further and further away. Don't worry about him.
這個越講越遠了 不要去管他
but i mean
但我的意思是說
It is true that re-price is a norm in Raising and Zhimin
募治民裡面確實呈現了再價是一個常態
This is a fact
這是事實
In fact, after reading other materials, we
這其實我們在看了其他的資料以後
will also find
也會發現
The so-called widowed, widowed, needle knot, defense
所謂手寡 手寡 針節 排防
These things were indeed a sore spot when the samurai
這些東西確實是武士的時候的痛處
But not in Chinese history
但是不是中國歷史上
It's always been like this
一直都是這樣子的一個情形
The second is to say
那第二個就是說
after he was widowed twice
他兩次手寡之後
He finds his life boring
他發現他沒意思 人生
I don't want to live like this
我不想這樣過了
what can he do
他有什麼事情可以做
he became a monk
他出家
he decided to become a monk
他決定出家
Without people also head towards the pond
未經人們也朝到水塘
As far as we are concerned, women in medieval China
就我們所說的中國中古的女性
In fact, apart from getting married
其實除了出嫁之外
There is another thing you can do
還有另外一個可以做的事情
is to become a monk
就是出家
and become a monk
而且出家
like he looks like
像他看起來好像是
Life is really hard like this
人生真的是苦到這種樣子
not interesting
沒有意思
Widowed twice, I became a monk
兩次手寡我就出家了
But after leaving home it looks like
可是出家之後看起來
he can read
他可以讀書耶
Bo collection gold account
博收金帳
also read commandments
還讀戒律
what else
還什麼什麼
did you really read
是不是真的讀
Literacy and reading
認字讀
we're not really sure
我們其實不是很確定
Because people in the past called reading
因為以前的人所謂讀書
Sometimes someone else reads to him
有時候是別人讀給他聽
If he can understand, it means he has read
聽得懂的就表示他有讀
This is also a way of reading
這也是一種讀書的方式
sometimes really read by yourself
有時候是真正自己讀
Sometimes you can recognize a few words
那有時候是認得幾個字
but some don't know
但是一部分不認識
Then ask others to read it together
然後請教別人一起讀
In fact, the situation is not necessarily
其實狀況其實不一定的
but anyway
但是不論如何
after becoming a monk
出家之後
if he is not a noblewoman
如果他不是貴族婦女
He's just an ordinary girl
他只是一般的女孩子的話
he may not have a chance
他可能也沒有機會
what reading teacher book
什麼讀師書
Li Yue
李月啊
He was in this second husband's house just now
剛才他在這個第二任丈夫家當中
But after all, when he was at the home of his second husband
但他畢竟在第二任丈夫家中的時候
It seems that some texts have been touched
好像已經接觸到一些文字了
After becoming a monk
那出家之後
He started collecting money
他開始博收金
read about Buddhism
讀跟佛教有關的東西
he likes himself
他喜歡他自己
It's the interest of another world
就等於是另外一個世界的興趣了
looks like
看起來
It's also a good time
也是過得還不錯的樣子
not enough
不夠
Grand Jazz
他的掛牌是在大爵士
But he ended up going to live in his grandson's house
可是他最後去跑到他外孫家裡面去住了
In fact, there are different studies
這個其實也是有不同的研究的
What does that mean
什麼意思呢
After the Tang Dynasty
到了唐代以後
the forest
森林啊
Be it a monk or a nun
不管是和尚還是尼姑
You can't run around, bhikkhu or bhikkhu
比丘或比丘你都不能亂跑的
The government of the Tang Dynasty was stricter
唐代的政府管得比較嚴格
where do you become a monk
你如果在哪裡出家
not place an order
不在哪裡掛單
I've already said which unit I'm in
已經講好了在哪個單位
You must practice in that unit
你就一定要在那個單位修行
don't run around
不可以到處亂跑
But in the unprecedented U.S. and North Korea
可是在未經的美朝
Because Buddhism has only just emerged
因為佛教才剛剛興起來
and still preaching
而且還在宣教
still looking for someone
還在到處找人
still pulling people
還在拉人
still in the process of becoming a believer
還在信教的這個過程當中
In fact, the government does not
事實上而且政府也沒管
Also very re-entering Buddhism
也非常的重進佛教
I didn't care about so many circumstances
也沒有管這麼多的情況之下
You'll find what's called Big Jazz Round Clay
你就會發現叫做大爵士圓泥的
The place where you run around and live is not necessarily in Big Jazz
跑來跑去住的地方不見得是在大爵士
Finally, when you get sick and die, you need someone to take care of you
最後生病死的時候要人照顧
not in big jazz either
也不是在大爵士
Instead, he went to live in his grandson's house.
反而到了他的外孫家裡面去住了
And he died at his grandson's house
而且去世是在他的外孫家去世的
on the other hand
那另外一方面
His grandson's family passed away
他的外孫家去世這個
It is also related to our history of women's life in China
也跟我們在中國婦女生活史的
s got woman's
年代所得到的女人的
The impression after marriage is different
出嫁之後的印象不太一樣
That is to say
也就是說
why would he follow a
為什麼他會跟一個
Daughter from his previous first marriage
他之前第一次婚姻所生的女兒
the daughter's later son
那個女兒後來所生的兒子
live together
住在一起呢
According to what we have read about the life history of Chinese women
按照我們所讀到中國婦女生活史的
Impressions of Chinese History
對中國史的印象
Chinese women's traditional Chinese women's
中國婦女的傳統中國婦女的
impression of this life
這個生活的印象
should mean
應該是說
If he was Sir Johnny
他如果是大爵士園尼
The government is not very strict
那政府沒有管得很嚴格
if he can go home
他可以回家的話
He should go back and follow the news
他應該要回去跟行訊
and his descendants
和他的子孫就
right
對不對
Since he gets along so well with Ji Zi
既然他跟這個季子相處得這麼好
Great righteousness makes people come out of themselves
大義生人龍於己出
Ji Zi loves him too
季子也愛他愛得不得了
two like
兩個好像
good relationship
關係良好啊
The relationship with the experts is also very good.
跟行家的人關係也都非常好啊
Then if he wants to go home
那他如果要回家的時候
or when he is sick
或他生病的時候
or when he is alone
或他孤單的時候
Shouldn't he be going home?
他不是應該要回行家去嗎
Obviously not
結果顯然沒有啊
he is actually
他其實是
to his original first marriage
去他原來第一個婚姻
the daughter
生的那個女兒
the son born
所生的那個兒子
not mentioned at all
完全都沒有在提到
the gaze of his daughter
他那個女兒的目視
so it's possible in
所以有可能在
When Yuan Chuntuo was widowed for the second time
這個袁春托第二次手寡的時候
His own daughter may have died
他自己的女兒說不定已經去世了
may not know
有可能不曉得
It's also possible that his daughter lived with his son.
也有可能他的女兒是跟自己的兒子住
That is, living with Yuan Chuntuo's grandson
也就是跟袁春托的外孫一起住
So when he went to find his grandson
所以他去找他外孫的時候
In fact, to find the daughter he gave birth to
其實就是去找他自己生的那個女兒
But that is to say, although in the so-called patriarchal ethics
但也就是說雖然在所謂父系倫理裡面
A wife should always focus on her husband
妻子永遠應該以丈夫為核心
Husband's mother is my mother
丈夫的媽媽就是我的媽媽
My husband's son is my son
丈夫的兒子就是我的兒子
My husband's family is my family
丈夫的家人就是我的家人
But Yuan Chuntuo is obviously not like this
不過袁春托顯然不是這樣子
He is closer to the one he was born with
他跟他自己生的那個關係比較近
This leads us to the mother-child relationship
這個就引起我們對於母子關係
Or mother-daughter relationship or parent-child relationship
或是母女關係或親子關係
In the age we see
在我們所看的這個年代
This is the era in which Yuan Chuntuo appeared
就是袁春托所出現的這個年代
What kind of parent-child relationship is it?
是一個什麼樣的親子關係
Is it the kind mentioned in the Chinese women's living room later?
是不是後來中國婦女生活室裡面所談到的那種
A parent-child relationship that seems to be based on the patriarchal family
好像父系家族為主軸的這樣子的一個親子關係
The parent-child relationship in this era
那這個時代的親子關係
or what it means to be a mother
或做母親的意義究竟是什麼
It has also aroused the curiosity of historians
也引起了歷史學者的好奇
At the end of the interesting part, I will tell you a little more at the end
最後有趣的地方到最後我會再跟各位多提一點
Why do you say Dungeon Maker?
為什麼說地城作潤呢
Just now I said that Xihe Wang Yuanweiqing was the successor of Luoyang.
剛才講這個西河王元位慶是洛陽的成手
very important
非常的重要
In fact, this time is already the end of the year in the north.
其實這個時候已經是北位的末年了
not long
沒多久
Probably not a few years later the North will perish
大概沒過幾年以後北位就滅亡了
In fact at this time
事實上這個時候說
Zu Yong'an is the year name of Emperor Xiaoming in the north
祖永安是北位孝明帝的年號
But in fact, when Emperor Xiaoming was in power,
但是其實孝明帝在在位的時候
Basically he is not in charge
基本上管世的並不是他
it's his mother
是他的媽媽
This is the Queen Mother
就是這個靈太后
that is a heroine
也就是一個女主
a political queen
一個社政太后
So, when Yuan Cunda lived in this age
那麼所以當元純陀生活活動的這個年代
In fact, China is historically
事實上是中國在歷史上面
women can remarry
女性可以改嫁
Whether he wants to or not
不管他是願意還是不願意
Anyway, he doesn't have the obligation to keep the chastity.
反正他並沒有要守節的這個義務
At the same time, besides his marriage
那同時他除了出嫁以外
There is also the opportunity to become a monk
還有出家的這種機會
On the other hand, he may have a relationship with his parents and children.
另外一方面他可能跟自己的親子的關係
very tight
非常的緊密
what it means to be a mother
做母親的這個意義
very important
非常地重大
another one is
還有一個就是
This is actually an era ruled by a heroine
這其實是一個女主所統治的時代
not a male emperor
並不是一個男皇帝
In public opinion, he is the male emperor
民意上是男皇帝啦
But the real ruler is actually this
但是真正統治者其實是這個
emperor's mother
皇帝的媽媽
That means the role of mother
那意思也就是說母親的這個角色
In fact, it is very important in this era
其實在這個時代是非常重要的
from here
那從這裡呢
we found out
我們就發現
This is basically talking about the period from the Qin and Han Dynasties to Shishi
這個談的基本上是這個從秦漢到實在
It's what we call medieval history
就是我們說的中古史的
but i'll get to that later
但是我等一下會講到
Probably not exactly limited to this time
大概不完全限制在這個時間
Because of the different aspects of Chinese history
因為中國歷史的不同的面向
change, time, ups and downs
變化、時間、起伏
It is not necessarily possible to use the political tide to stop and stop
不見得都是用政治潮在可以斷落、斷下來的
If we look at Yuan Cuntou's life story, we will find that
如果我們從原存頭的生命故事來看的話就會發現
In fact, the so-called respect for the seven generations of the husband or respecting the husband
其實所謂的夫尊七輩或以夫為尊的這個東西
that is, by law
也就是以法律
legally
法律上
The core is the idea that the husband is the main axis
核心是以丈夫為主軸的這樣子的一個觀念
There may be something different in this day and age
在這個時代可能有一些不一樣
On the other hand, mother and son
另外一方面母子親恩
May reveal a new fertility culture
可能展現出一種新的生育文化
This is also a historian
這也是歷史學者
pondering place
琢磨的地方
Then there is
再來就是
widowed monk
手寡跟出家
Widowed women may also become ordained
就手寡的婦人也可能出家
never married girl
從來沒結過婚的女孩子
Maybe he became a monk in his teens
也可能十幾歲就出家
Said he was leaving home
就說他要出家
It is possible in this era
這個時代是有這樣子的可能性的
So scholars of the history of religion have also been inspired by this
所以宗教史的學者也從這當中得到了啟發
start doing research
開始做研究
on the other hand
另外一方面
Chen Dongyuan says
陳東源說
I don't want to talk about female emperors and heroines venting their anger on women
我不想談什麼女皇帝女豪傑給女性出氣
Because these people have nothing to do with ordinary women
因為這些人跟一般的女人根本沒關係
What is the meaning of talking about female Wu Zetian
講女武則天有什麼意義
no use at all
根本沒用
Actually still useful
其實還是有用的
see what you say
看你怎麼講
If you take Wu Zetian as saying that she is venting her anger for a woman
如果把武則天當成說是替女人出氣
Of course it's useless
那當然就沒有什麼用了
But if Wu Zetian's appearance
但是如果把武則天的出現
placed in a series of historical developments
放在一系列的歷史發展
In the context of political history
就政治史的脈絡裡面
Why is there such a female emperor?
為什麼會出這樣子一個女皇帝
The only one in Chinese history
中國歷史上唯一的
Scholars of political history may have something to say
那可能政治史的學者就有話可以說
it makes sense to talk about
就有意義可以談
It is the characteristic of national culture
就是民族文化的特色
or interracial contact
或者是不同種族的接觸
Or a change in the concept of class
或者是階級的觀念的改變
When these things are added together
這些東西加在一起的時候
In fact, it’s all because historical research didn’t want to learn from women
其實都是因為歷史研究本來沒有想從女性
or gender perspective
或性別的角度來想那些事
But if from a gender point of view
但是如果從性別角度來
rethinking legal history
重新考慮法律史
When medical history is compared with religious history or political history
醫療史跟宗教史或政治史的時候
we may see something different
我們可能會看到不同的東西
The pure wood is just right
那元純多的木質剛好
All fit. Let's look at something like this
都符合可以讓我們來看看這樣的東西
If the law makes us talk about basically
如果從法律使 我們先講基本上
Chinese law probably started after the Tang Dynasty
中國的法律大概在唐代以後
It has been established that the so-called Five Blessings are used to punish people
就確立下來是用所謂的五福來處罰人
What's the meaning
什麼意思
what is five blessings
五福是什麼
does anyone know
有人知道嗎
Does anyone know what Wufu is?
有人知道五福是什麼嗎
Can you see it here?
這邊可以看得出來嗎
If there is a self here, have you seen yourself?
假如這邊有一個自己 有沒有看到自己
own father died
自己的爸爸去世
I have to serve him for three years
要為他服斬催三年
own brother died
自己的兄弟去世
I have to serve him for a year
要為他服滋催一年
own grandfather died
自己的祖父去世
Take nourishing reminder for one year
服滋催一年
Tang Brothers Passed Away in September
唐兄弟去世 服大功九月
Don brothers' child dies
唐兄弟的小孩子去世
I mourn for him
我為他服喪
Fu Xiaogong May
服小功五月
grandson of tang brothers dies
唐兄弟的孫子去世
I served his dead horse for three months
我為他服屍馬三個月
sound like proper nouns
聽起來都是專有名詞
what the hell is this talking about
這到底在講什麼
Cut and blow the broken sound
斬吹破音字啦
It doesn't matter if you cut it inside
裡面斬衰也沒關係
cut blow means
斬吹的意思就是說
very tattered sackcloth
很破爛的麻衣
The sackcloth is torn to the bottom
那個麻衣破爛到下面
no seams
邊都不縫
like cut it
像斬開就切開一樣
rotten
爛巴巴的
very very bad sackcloth
非常非常爛的麻衣
And the edges are not sewn
而且邊都不縫起來
Wearing this sackcloth for three years
穿這樣的麻衣穿三年
Why
為什麼
because my father died
因為我父親去世了
very very painful
非常非常痛苦
father is a man's day
父親是一個人的天
This is in Yili Shangfu
這個在以禮商服裡面
This whole chart is from Yili Shangfu
這整個圖表是從以禮商服
the relationship between the traditional family
就是傳統家族之間的關係
how to define
怎麼界定
by
以
that person died
那個人去世
I wounded for him
我為他服傷
how long to take
服多久
wear rotten sackcloth
穿多爛的麻衣
to define the distance between me and him
來界定我跟他之間的
Intimacy
親疏尊卑關係
so if
所以如果
i don't know now
我不知道現在
if you go to a funeral
如果你去葬禮
get a reply
拿到一個複文
But now everything is electronic
可是現在什麼東西都電子的
I do not even know
我都不知道
Is there anything else I can get?
還有沒有這種東西可以拿
If a woman dies
如果一個女性去世的時候
Sometimes his husband comes out to do funerals for him
有時候他的丈夫會出來替他辦喪事
Husband and wife
就叫丈夫妻夫
Wife is the meaning of a year here
妻就是這邊的一年的意思
I read the word "Blowing"
我念破音字之吹
You can miss your wife if you want
你要念妻衰也可以
mean to say
意思就是說
The death of a brother is not as serious as the death of a father
兄弟去世沒有像父親去世那麼嚴重
still very sad
還是很悲傷
But what about the sackcloth with the clothes on?
但是呢 穿著衣服的那個麻衣
It can be sewed, so the wife dies
是可以縫編的 所以妻衰
And the time to serve in the warehouse is less than three years
而且服倉的時間不用到三年
just one year is enough
只要一年就夠了
That means the father is supreme
那意思就是說 父至尊
he is my most respected person
他是我最尊的人
So when he passed away, I beheaded him for three years
所以他去世我是斬催三年
brother of course
兄弟當然親
But it didn't reach the level of supreme
但是呢 沒有到至尊的那種地步
So the sackcloth is a bit better for sewing
所以麻衣還算好一點可以縫編
Not even three years
時間也不用到三年
Just one year
只要一年就可以了
just a little less
就稍微少一點
One year, also called wife
一年呢 又叫妻
that is
就是
During that period, practice making chicken
期間的那個期 演練做雞
but no matter what
但不論如何
It means taking a year of injury
意思就是服一年傷
come down the other
再下來其他的
Dagong is linen
大功是麻布
But it's thicker linen
但是呢是比較厚一點的麻布了
slightly thicker like
稍微厚一點沒有像
That rotten cloth
那個衰這麼爛的布
Then he just needs to obey
那他只要服
Nine months and a little further away
九個月再遠一點的親戚
Minor
小功的
better again
又更好了
Just take it for five months
只要服五個月
Relatives who are far away wear Sima
再遠的親戚就穿司麻
Sima is actually quite dense.
司麻其實已經算是比較密的麻了
Even without the crappy clothes
就算沒有很爛的衣服了
The sackcloth is good but it is good
麻衣不錯 但是是好
Pretty good sackcloth
還算好的麻衣
how long to wear for three months
穿多久穿三個月
Therefore, take five servings according to etiquette
所以以禮商服用五服
Just take five servings
就是拿五服
three years one year nine months
三年一年九個月
five months three months
五個月三個月
Paired with bad Zhancui
搭配很爛的展翠
slightly rotten
稍微爛一點
But not the worst Zhi Cui
但不算最爛的支翠
Then come back to the great and the small
然後再來大功小功司麻
five different clothes
五種不同的衣服
this type
這個型
different linen clothes
不同的麻布的衣服
the dead live for the dead
去世活著的要為去世的人
what to wear for mourning
服喪穿什麼衣服
Use this method to show the relationship between a family
用這個方式來顯示一個家族之間
relationship of intimacy
彼此之間的親疏尊卑關係
Well, this intimacy and inferiority are related to the Tang Dynasty
好 這個親疏尊卑關係到了唐代
It becomes placed in Tang Lv Shuyi
就變成放在唐律書義裡面
recognized by law
法律裡面來認定
If you have a murder, a murder, a fight at home
如果你在家裡面發生相殺 相傷 打架
When someone is injured or someone dies
受傷 有人死了的事情的時候
If you want to serve him for a year
假如是你要為他服 滋催一年的話
Then you hit him and hurt him
那你打了他受傷
You will be punished more than when two passers-by get into a fight
你要受的刑罰就比兩個路人打架的時候受傷
It's worse to hurt someone
讓別人受傷要來得重
if i hit him he hurts
如果我打他是他受傷
But he's for me if I die
但是他是要為我 如果我死了
He served me for three years
他是為我服滋催三年
For example, Zicui, Dagong is ready in September, just give me an example
比如滋催 大工九月好了 隨便舉個例子
It means that he serves me
意思就是說他為我服的是
Heavier than what I put on him
比我為他服的還要重
He came and beat me
結果他來打了我
then i hit him
那麼 然後我打了他
Then I shall be punished more than
那麼我要受的刑罰就比
Generally, two passers-by kill each other and hurt each other lightly.
一般兩個路人互相相殺相傷來得輕
do you understand me
這樣了解我意思嗎
That is to say, the parent-book preparation relationship in a family uses this talisman
就是說一個家族裡的親書準備關係是用這個符
So after the Tang Dynasty we saw that in fact
所以呢在唐代以後我們看到其實
China has probably always said when judging cases
中國以來大概都會在判案的時候就會說
case official system
案官符制
This case involves symbols
這個案件啊牽涉到符制
When someone in the family hurts each other
就家族裡面有人互相傷害的時候
Then I'll put it between him and him
那我就要算他跟他之間
What kind of relationship should it be in the five symbols?
原來應該是在這個五符裡面是在哪一種關係
Who is more respectful and who is more sad
誰比較尊 誰比較悲
Who's more dear who compares books
誰的比較親 誰比較書
Sentencing only after confirmation
確定之後才來判刑
The penalty for fighting with two passers-by is different
跟兩個路人互相打架的刑罰是不一樣的
meaning that
意思也就是說
This set of concepts of all traditional Chinese etiquette
把所有傳統中國的禮的這一套觀念
put it into the law to implement
放到法裡面來執行
do you know what i mean
這樣瞭解我意思嗎
but you can see
可是各位可以看得到
look here
你看這裡面
All men and no women
全部都是男的都沒有女的啊
how could this be
怎麼會這樣子呢
what's going on
是怎麼回事
because
因為
What about me if my wife dies?
自己呢如果妻子去世的話
Remind him for a year
為他符制催一年
But we didn't see that if we are female
可是我們沒有看到如果自己是女的
What if the husband dies?
那丈夫去世怎麼辦
same as son
跟兒子一樣
This wound that the wife served for her husband
妻子為丈夫服的這個傷
It's the same wound that the son took for his father
是跟兒子為爸爸服的傷一樣
it means
意思就是
when a woman marries
當一個女人出嫁的時候
if she is at home
她如果她在家裡的時候
she is a living woman
她是在世女
her father died
她的父親去世
She will take the worst injury
她要服最重的傷
for her father
就是給她的父親
once she is married
一旦她出嫁之後
her worst injury
她最重的傷
for her sir
就是給她的先生
so-called widow
所謂的遺夫作天
originally your father
本來你的爸爸
Originally your father was your god
本來你的爸爸是你的天
now once married
現在一旦結婚之後
husband is your god
丈夫就是你的天
so the wife died
所以太太去世
The husband only needs to serve his wife for one year
丈夫只需要為太太服一年
wearable sackcloth
穿還可以的麻衣
But if the husband dies
可是如果丈夫去世的話
The wife will serve her husband for three years
太太就要為丈夫服三年
and the worst
而且是最爛
sackcloth
不逢邊的那種麻衣
means to show
意思就是在展現
Husband honors his wife and mourns
夫尊妻悲
what about my son
那麼兒子怎麼辦呢
when dad died
爸爸去世的時候
serve him for three years
為他服三年
Zhancui three years
展翠三年
What about the mother's death?
那媽媽去世呢
one year
一年
mother died
媽媽去世
Take the reminder of a year's injury
服之催一年的傷
that is why
就是說為什麼
Because although my mother is a close relative
因為媽媽雖然至親
But not higher than the Supreme
但不能高過至尊
inside a home
一個家裡面
the most respected person
最尊的那個人
can't be taller than him
不可以高過他
The premise is
這個前提是
Dad is still there, right?
爸爸還在嘛對不對
So the Supreme is still there
所以至尊還在
Although the dearest relative died
至親雖然去世
You can't be right for him
你也不可以為他服對
So I can only take it for a year
所以只能服之催一年
But if my mother dies
可是如果我媽媽去世的時候
my dad has passed away
我爸爸已經去世了
I'm not here anymore
我至尊不在啦
what to do
怎麼辦
Eloquent
以理說
you can serve for three years
你可以服三年
but can't
但是不能
Can't wear sharp clothes
不能穿斬催的衣服
Only wear self-proclaimed clothes
只能穿自催的衣服
just your sackcloth
就你的麻衣
can't be chopped
不可以斬爛
Because although your Supreme is dead
因為你的至尊雖然去世
He will always be your king
他還是永遠是你的至尊
So even though your loved one died
所以雖然你的至親去世了
you are very sad
你非常悲痛
You want to serve him for three years
你想為他服三年的傷
Can
可以
but the clothes can't arrive
但是衣服不能到
worst level
最爛的那一級
must be between parents
必須在父母之間
There must be a division
有一個區隔才行
Otherwise, you can't tell the difference
否則的話就分不出
who is supreme
誰才是至尊
I can't say that it doesn't count if you're dead.
不能說死了就不算啦
He is still supreme
他還是至尊啦
so what
所以呢
you can know
各位就可以知道
such a concept
這樣子的觀念
This way of distribution
這樣子的分配方式
If you put him in the law
如果把他放到了法律裡面的時候
If you use this thing to sentence
用這個東西來判刑的話
that is to say
那也就是說
If a son hurts his father and his mother
一個兒子如果傷害了父親跟傷害了母親
Or if a father hurts a child
或者一個爸爸如果傷害了小孩
or the mother hurt the child
或媽媽傷害小孩
or
或者是
mom hurt dad
媽媽傷害了爸爸
child saw
小孩看到了
In fact, the sentence will be based on
其實判刑都會根據
who is respect and who is sorrow
誰是尊 誰是悲
to deal with it, right?
來做處理對不對
After the Tang Dynasty
到唐代以後
It's actually like this
其實就是這個樣子
Then since the wife is the husband
那麼妻子既然是丈夫
it's his god
是他的天
after the wife passed
妻子過去之後
The most important thing for him is to take this husband's family
他最重要的就是以這個丈夫的一家
for his core
為他的核心
his main task
他的主要的任務
It is said in the so-called ceremony
就是所謂的禮祭裡面說
Guangsaiji Temple
祖宗愧 廣祭寺
i can't find much
我找不到太多
The picture of Guangji Temple is difficult to draw here
廣祭寺的圖很難在這邊畫
but anyway
不過呢 不論如何
You can watch the cooking
燒飯你可以看
This is a planing plan
這是一個刨廚圖
This is a hot chicken picture
這個是一個燙雞圖
This is a Buddhist Nine Pose Mother
這個是一個佛教的九姿母
Guizi mother has many children and grandchildren
龜姿母就很多子多孫的圖
Then this is a picture of casting Buddha and praying for four horses
然後這個是投佛祈求四騎的圖
mainly just to tell you
主要只是告訴各位
wife if married
太太如果嫁過去
a woman married like this
一個女人嫁過去這樣
After the husband's house, he takes his family as the core
丈夫家之後 他就以他家為核心
The whole point of his family is to
一夫作天 在他家裡面的重點就是要
Responsible for three meals and sacrificial offerings. Roast pigs, cattle and sheep. Roast duck and fish for three meals.
負責三餐跟祭祀要燒豬牛羊 三餐要燒鴨魚
Then the other thing is to have more sons for him
那麼另外就是要替他多生兒子
so that the family can continue
使這個家族能夠綿延下去
In this case, the sacrifice of the good man
在這種情況之下 良人祭祀
If it is according to the martial arts disciples of this sect, as we just said,
如果是按照本宗武夫徒 就我們剛講的那個樣子的話
Even if a loved one dies
就算是良人去世的話
your significant other your husband died
你的另一半 你的丈夫死了
This is what Yuan Chuntuo said about the half body request
這就是袁純陀說的半體允請
Half of my body should have collapsed
我的半個身體應該就倒了
That kind of context is right
那種脈絡才對
But if we look at other documents that were actually unearthed at that time
可是呢 如果我們看一下其他當時真正出土的文獻的話
You'll find that actually in what we've seen
你就會發現 其實在我們所看到的這個
Except that Mu Ziming of Yuan Chuntuo saw him at home
除了袁純陀的這個牧子明看到他在家之外
We can see it in many other unearthed materials
我們在很多其他的出土材料裡面看得到
Once the husband dies, the wife or the case
一旦丈夫去世之後 太太或者是這個案子
The case of Zou Yanshu is
奏豔書的這個案子是
A wife when her husband is watching for her husband
一個太太在丈夫在替丈夫守齡的時候
next to that hand with another man
在那個手上的旁邊跟另外一個男人
someone fucked
有人胡搞
It was discovered by my mother-in-law
結果被婆婆發現了
This is all dug out Jane
這個都是挖出來的簡
We didn't know there was such a story before.
以前我們都不曉得還有這種故事的
I don't know if it's love or a story from Han Dynasty
不知道是情還是漢出的故事
so what
那麼呢
As for the mother-in-law, she will sue the officer
就婆婆就去告官
Then a group of officials
然後一群官
Then start judging this
然後就開始要判這個
widow's punishment
寡婦的刑
I always said how to beat him
本來都說應該怎麼樣打他
how to shut him
怎麼樣關他
What about various prison sentences?
怎麼樣各式各樣的徒刑啊
Corporal punishment, wait
肉刑啊等等的
There are various discussions
有各種各樣的討論
When it's almost time to test
差不多都要定驗的時候
Suddenly there is an official who did not attend
突然有一個原來沒有參加的官員
back from business trip
出差回來了
Tell me which case you are discussing
說你們在討論的哪一個case
I will also participate
我也來參加
after participating in the discussion
就參加討論以後
the official said
那個官員就說
When alive, two are one
活著的時候是二人是一體
when dead
死了的時候
According to our Han out
按照我們這個漢出
Is this love or a legal order from Han?
這個是情還是漢出的法律令
dead and gone
死了就沒有了
Can't handle it anymore
管不了了
So what about this lady
所以呢這個太太
she only
她只
if you want to find her check
如果你要找她的查
If you want to report her for any crime
要告發她做任何有罪的行為的話
It can only be said that she is not satisfied with closing the curtain.
只能是說她對於關幕不盡啊
No respect for this hand hurt venue
對這個手傷的場所不尊敬
you can't use adultery
你不能夠用通姦
because it's the same way as adultery
因為本來一樣通姦的方式
to judge her
要來判她
The mother-in-law is very angry. When the mother-in-law and daughter-in-law hold hands together
婆婆很生氣 婆媳兩個一起手上的時候
The mother-in-law suddenly found out that the daughter-in-law was with someone else
婆婆突然發現媳婦跟別人在
Linjiu's backside is messing around
臨久的後面在糊搞
So I took her to the police
所以就把她抓去告官了
What about the result? The result of the discussion later
那結果呢 後來討論的結果
It was the official who obeyed
是聽從了後來的這個官員
According to a legal judgment at the time when the situation was still in Han Dynasty
按照當時情還是漢出時候的一個法律判斷
I think that when a man is alive is after his wife dies
認為人活的時候是太太死了以後
just people who don't matter
就是沒有關係的人
So mother-in-law is not eligible
所以婆婆沒有資格
I don't have the capacity to sue this daughter-in-law
也沒有這個身份去告這個媳婦
This is the most recent colleague of ours is the academician of Industry Field
這個是最近我們的同仁就是行業田院士
I just did some research and found out that there is such a thing
才做的研究 才知道 原來還有這回事
Then the other one is
那麼另外一個是
In 2006, it was discovered in 2006 that the park had been built for 20 years.
2006年的時候發現的前情建園20年的急障
That's household registration
那個是戶籍的登記
it's also late
這也是很晚進
Only friends of academic level can do the research
才有學階的朋友把研究做出來
found out that the girl got married
發現其實女孩子結婚
if after death
如果去世之後
He won't stay at her husband's house either
他也不會留在夫家
He went back to his mother's house
他就回娘家了
And no longer bear the husband's surname
而且也不再冠夫姓了
restore his original natal status.
就恢復他原來的娘家的性勢
Just live with my mother's family
就跟娘家一起生活
why would you know
為什麼會知道呢
Because the urgent obstacle is the transfer registration of household registration
因為這個急障就是戶籍的這個轉移登記
we found out like this
我們發現了這樣子
a custom of
的一個習俗
so it can be seen
所以可以看得出來
In fact, if there is a so-called
其實如果有所謂的
Well
呃
what i just said
我剛剛講的
Wufu's set
五福的這套東西
In the Tang Dynasty, it was indeed
到唐代的時候確實是
in law
在法律裡面都
laid down
奠定下來了
But in this process, there are five blessings
可是在這個過程就是有五福
The Five Blessings
以理喪福這個五福
During the Tang Dynasty
到唐代這過程當中
Although I just said
雖然在我剛剛講
forgot to say this
漏了講這句
267 years
267年的時候
I already said when I got in
進到時候已經說
In the future, the Five Blessings must be approved to rule the law
以後都要準五福以治律
is to be stipulated in this way
是要這樣規定的
So in the Tang Dynasty
所以到唐代的時候
Only then can we really write the meaning of Tang Law's calligraphy
才會真正寫到唐律書意
But from 267 to the establishment of the Tang Dynasty in the seventh century
可是從267年到唐朝建立第七世紀
During these four hundred years
這四百多年當中
In fact, we have seen in many other materials
其實我們在很多其他資料裡面看到
Wufu can't help
五福並沒有辦法
really into the law
真正進到法律裡面
people's living habits
人們的生活習俗習慣
In fact, with his mother's family
其實還跟他的娘家
Girls usually
女孩子其實通常會常常
maintains a fairly close relationship with his natal family
跟他的娘家保持蠻密切的關係
and legally
而且在法律上面
won't last forever
也不會一直維持著
so-called concubine
所謂的夫尊妻妃
or the husband died
或者是丈夫死了
must be consistent
必須從一而終
this kind of attitude
這類的態度
In fact, in the data we have seen
其實在我們所看到的這些資料裡面
are very few
都很少
on the other hand
另外一方面
you can see
你可以看得到
inside the business suit
以理商服裡面
It's also very clear, didn't we just talk about it?
也很明確我們剛剛不是講了嗎
if one knows oneself
如果一個人知道自己
only know my mother
只知道自己的母親
don't know my father
不知道自己的父親
actually not
其實是不行的
Because this whole uniform
因為這整個武服
It's all about the father
都是以父親為主軸
to regulate
來規範
What about when the law decides a case?
那麼在法律判案的時候呢
In fact, the whole process
其實在這整個過程
From the business service to the Tang Dynasty
就從以理商服務到唐代
determined in the middle
確定下來的中間
There are many different cases
有很多不同的案件
have been through debates and quarrels
都曾經經過辯論跟吵架
dispute
爭執
one of them was a
其中有一次就是有一個
what i just said
我剛剛講的
when a son finds his mother
當一個兒子發現他的媽媽
killed his dad
殺了他的爸爸
if this is the case
如果這樣子的時候
Does the son need to sue the police?
兒子需不需要去告官
According to the Confucianism of the time
按照當時的儒家
influenced by Confucianism
受到儒家觀念的
the influence of these
這個影響的這些
official statement
官員的說法
must be sued
是必須要告官的
because dad is your king
因為爸爸是你的至尊
Although mother is your dearest relative
雖然媽媽是你的至親
if you sue
你如果去告了
ok
好啦
couple
夫婦
my parents domestic violence
我的父母家暴
beated
打了
fight
打架
beat to a degree
打到一個程度
mom can't stand it
媽媽受不了了
dad killed
爸爸殺了
son saw with his own eyes
兒子親眼看到
Should my son go at this time?
這個時候兒子該不該去
sue the officer
告出官
It was an issue they were debating
就是他們當時辯論的一個問題
influenced by Confucianism
受儒家影響的
Or officials who believe in military uniforms say
或是相信武服這一套的官員說
Of course you should sue the officer
當然應該要告官
Because your Supreme has been killed
因為你的至尊被殺啦
How can you keep silent
你怎麼可以莫不坑聲呢
But officials who don't believe in this set think that
可是不相信這一套的官員就認為
mother is your close relative
母親是你的至親
You saw him kill your Supreme
你看到他把你的至尊殺了
You go to report on your next of kin again
你又去告發你的至親
In the end your next of kin were killed
最後你的至親就被殺了
was seized by the government
就被官府給收拿
and then sentenced to death
然後就判出死刑
So didn't you kill your loved ones?
那麼你不是害你的至親死亡嗎
so there's no way to tell
所以這沒有辦法告
this can't be sued
這不能告的
what to do
該怎麼辦
Both sides are officials for the benefit of this law
兩邊就是官員為了利益這個法
Should I sue
該不該告
sparked debate
就引起了辯論
was debating the sixth century
當時在辯論六世紀
while still debating
還在辯論的時候
an official said
就有一個官員說
of course to sue
當然要告
Because the House of Elishang has already said
因為以理商府已經說了
know mother but not father
知母而不知父
The savages are easy to enjoy
勢彼野人易盡情受
It's the so-called resistance
就是所謂的抵堵情深
What does it mean to block
抵堵是什麼意思
Mavericks
小牛啊
Do calves and cows have a deep love?
小牛跟母牛情很深嗎
Resisting affection is the meaning of affection
抵堵情深就是情受的意思啊
Yeah
是嗎
Clam
蛤
if you only knew cows
如果你只知道母牛
you only know cows
你只知道母牛
don't know bull
不知道公牛
Then you are a beast
那你就是禽獸啊
For all the beasts know
因為所有的禽獸都曉得
love my mother
愛自己的媽媽
Only civilized animals like humans
只有人這種有文明的動物
I learned to respect my father
才曉得要尊敬自己的爸爸
So if you only know how to love your mother
所以如果你只懂得愛媽媽
I don't know how to respect my father
不知道尊敬爸爸
Shibi Savage
就是勢比野人
Exotic Beasts
異境禽獸
Your morality is at the level of animals
你的道義跟禽獸的水準
almost
就是差不多的
That another official is objecting
那另外一個官員在反對的
the official said
官員就說
this is no way to accept
這是沒有辦法接受
This way of talking is unacceptable
這種談法無法接受
Why
為什麼
only with parents
只與父母同氣異息
born of the same breath
是同一個氣息生下來的
Zhong Tian Mi repays love in the wild
中天彌報在情一野
The love for parents should be the same
對父母的情應該是一樣的
exclamation on its dignity
驚呼論其尊卑
change its pros and cons
變其優劣
Why do you suddenly say that the father respects the mother?
怎麼就突然說是父尊母卑
Parents are good and mothers are bad
父優母劣
If the mother kills the father
如果是母親殺父親
must sue
就一定要告呢
If the father kills the mother without suing
父親殺母親不告的話
Mother should not sue father for killing father
母親殺父親應該也不要告
so suddenly
所以突然這樣講
push salary
推薪為人
anti ancient fearless
防古無懼
In fact, he said that anti-ancient fearlessness is wrong.
其實他說防古無懼是錯的啦
Because Anti-Ancient is fearful
因為防古是有懼的啦
Because Yili Shangfu is clearly like this
因為以禮尚夫就明明這樣子
But don't believe this
但是不相信這樣子一套
And think mother and father
而認為母親跟父親
In fact, they are all the same breath
其實都是同氣一息
born together
一起把小孩子產出的
Such an official cannot accept
這樣子的官員就不能夠接受
So the law didn't change
所以後來法律就沒有改
That is to say, the father killed the mother
也就是說父親殺母親母親
Like discovering a domestic violence case at home
像在家裡面發現家暴案件
no son
兒子都沒有
I can't bear it
不忍都不可以搞
can't do it
都不能夠搞
So everyone can guess
所以大家也可以猜得到
Domestic violence cases at that time probably had no solution
當時的家暴案件大概是沒有辦法
appeared
出現的了
it just won't work
就是不會成案的
Because basically the law can't bear it
因為基本上法律不忍心
Tell this kid to sue
就叫這個小孩子去告
any father or mother
任何一個父親或者是母親
This is because of my mother
這樣子因為母親的關係
love and kindness between mother and child
母子之間的情跟恩
challenged
挑戰了
It turns out we were just
原來我們剛剛在
The whole set of Eli Sanford
《伊里桑福》所講的那整套
in this day and age
在這個年代
In fact, there are many, many
其實就出了非常非常多
amendments to laws
法律的修正案
for example
譬如說
tree is a person
樹子就是一個人
weak child
竊弱生的小孩
if he be his father's heir
如果他做父親的繼承人
The so-called son of the tree is the queen of the father
所謂樹子為父后
That is, if a boy
就是說如果一個男孩子
became the father's heir
做了父親的繼承人
It's just that his father didn't
就是他爸爸沒有
During the first period, no children were born
正期就第一期沒有生小孩
All that was born of him
他這個切所生的
later became
後來變成
heir
繼承人了
Then according to the regulations of business clothes with etiquette, that is to say
再按照以禮商服的規定就是說
If the number of sons is the father
如果數子為父後
The son of the concubine became the heir of the father
數子做了 妾的兒子做了父親的繼承人
to himself the mother who bore him
對他自己生他的那個母親
Because that mother is a concubine, right?
因為那個母親是妾嘛 對不對
Isn't it the real wife?
不是正妻嘛
nothing to wear
沒有什麼服的
wear very very light
服得非常非常輕
It seems that I haven't taken it or take it for three months
好像沒有服還是服三個月
but in this era
可是在這個時代
As far as we are talking about the era of Yuan Cuntuo
就我們在談原存陀的這個年代
Because many sons are reluctant to part with their mothers
因為很多的兒子舍不得自己的媽媽
Since my concubine uncle gave birth to my good son
既是妾叔生養了我這個好兒子
I managed to become my father's heir
我好不容易做了父親的繼承人
How could I not honor my own mother
我怎麼能夠不尊榮我自己的母親呢
so when my mother died
所以當我的母親去世的時候
Although he is a concubine
雖然他是一個妾
I still take a heavy wound for him
我還是為他服很重的傷
It's like he's my aunt
好像他是我家的嫡母一樣
many people like this
很多人這樣
After many sons do this
很多兒子這樣做之後
Later the law was changed
後來法律就改了
just accept
就接受
Counting sons as fathers and then mothers
數子為父後為生母
It's the mother who is the concubine
就是做妾的這個母親
can also take serious injuries
也可以服重傷
besides
還有
If according to the ethics of the patrilineal family
如果按照父系家族的倫理
son
兒子
one who gave birth to a son
生兒子的一個
even the main wife
即使是正妻
once his husband died
一旦他的先生去世了
he becomes a widow
他就變寡婦
If a widow remarries into another family
寡婦如果再嫁到別人家
people
就是人家的人
As far as my family is concerned
就我這一家來講
well done
行家好了
In terms of original depository, shepherds
原存托就牧家來講
already another
已經是另外
completely other people
完全是別家人
It has nothing to do with my family
跟我家一點關係都沒有了
so what
所以呢
The child born in the original home
在原來的家裡面所生的這個小孩
Once my widowed mother goes out
一旦我手寡的媽媽出去
marry someone else
又嫁給別人家
after she died there
她在那家死了之後
I will not mourn her
我是不會她服喪的
This is stipulated under Yishangfu
這在以禮商服之下規定
But in the age we're talking about
可是在我們所談的這個年代
These sons are reluctant
這些兒子都捨不得
It's her parent-child relationship
就是她親子關係
You'll know it after watching Yuan Cun Tuo Muzhi
你看了原存托牧之就知道
even if widowed
即使手寡在嫁
There is contact with the original child
跟原來生的小孩之間是有接觸的
if there is contact
如果有接觸
when you dress according to etiquette
你在按照以禮商服的時候
you are not allowed to mourn
你不准服喪
Knowing that the mother who gave birth to me died
明明就知道我生我的媽媽去世
died elsewhere
在別家去世了
I still can't help it
我還是忍不住
So there are a lot of people in mourning
所以就很多服喪的這樣子的
something happened
事情出現
Later the law was changed
後來法律也就跟著改
acceptable
可以接受
can mourn
可以服喪
besides
還有
stepfather
同母義父
according to etiquette
按照以禮商服
This question of the Supreme Father seems to be
父至尊的這一題系看起來
stepfather
同母義父
people who don't matter at all
根本沒關係的人
because that's sex
因為那是性別的性
It's not that I don't believe it
不是我理也不信原
I don't believe in pastoralism
也不信牧也不信
neither believe in pastor nor practice
也不信托牧也不信行
right
對不對
But
可是
It is because we look at the example of Yuan Chuntuo
就是因為我們看元純托的例子
Of course there are many other examples
當然還有很多其他例子
I just use Yuanchunto to make a shadow
我只是用元純托做一個影子而已
you will know
你就會知道
Brothers and sisters between the same mother and adoptive father at that time
當時同母義父之間的兄弟姊妹
may be related is related
可能是有聯繫的 是有關係的
not unrelated
並不是毫無關係的
then if at the time of death
那麼如果去世的時候
Originally, I was dissatisfied with the business clothes with etiquette
本來在以禮商服是不服的
But they all
但他們都監
A lot of people are supervising doctors, too.
很多人監 世大夫也好
The royal family is fine, the royal family is fine
皇室也好 王室也好
Supervisor
都監持服
result to the end
結果到最後
the law was changed
法律也就改了
so that they can mourn each other
讓他們能夠彼此服喪
There is also the so-called
還有就是所謂的
nephew mourning for mother
外甥為母舊服喪
Mujiu is mother's brother
母舊就是媽媽的哥哥
It's actually another family.
其實也是別家人啊
He's different from me
他跟我的不同性啊
the same reason
一樣的道理
in other words
換句話說
Because of this mother
因為這個媽媽這件事情
contacted a lot of original
聯繫了很多原來
Looks like it's in the patrilineal family
看起來在父系家族裡面
ok person
沒關係的人
And these people who don't matter
而這些沒關係的人
become related to each other
彼此之間變成了有關係
This is in our section
這個就是在我們這一段的
the study of legal history
法律史的研究裡面
Research done by scholars later found that
學者所做的研究以後發現
Because of the kindness of mother and son
因為母子親恩
Patriarchy
而挑戰了父系理法
and modified the then
而修改了當時的
etiquette and law
禮俗跟法律
Mother
母親
really the importance
真的這種重要性
The so-called king of Xihe did not sleep
所謂西河王未寢是
Mrs. Grandson of the Beginning of Vision
目視之初夫人外孫
sons and parents have different habits
子於父母同氣異習
so to speak
那這樣說起來
daughter is still
女兒依然就子
son to parents
兒子對父母來講
It's homosexuality
是同氣異習
no way to call him
沒有辦法叫他分
Then of course the daughter has no way to ask him to share.
那麼女兒當然也沒有辦法叫他分
what about this era
這個時代呢
In fact, when we look at it this way, we find that
事實上我們這樣看以後會發現
Fertility is the matter of giving birth to a child and being a mother
生育就是生孩子做媽媽這件事
indeed in this one
確實在這一個
In the age of the Middle Ages we are talking about
在我們所談的這個中國中古的時代
on this reproductive culture
在這個生育文化上面
There is a step forward
有一步進一步的推進
how to say
怎麼說呢
in the fifth century
五世紀的時候
It is about a hundred years earlier than this Yuanchuntuo Belt
就比這個元純陀帶早一百年左右
There is a book called Xiaopin Fang
有一本一書叫做小品方
There used to be a saying in Xiaopinfang called
小品方裡面曾經有一句話叫做
Going to the ground to make grass is as old as dead
下地作草法如舊死
What's the meaning
什麼意思
we were
我們那時候
When I read this sentence
我那時候讀到這句話的時候
I can't read it
我才讀不懂啊
Why is it called childbirth?
為什麼叫生孩子的時候
call down the ground to make grass
叫下地作草
Wonderful
精彩精彩
The spirit is born on the ground and the law is like the old dead
靈產下地作草法如舊死
when this woman is about to give birth
這個女人要生孩子的時候
to get down to the ground and sit on the grass
要下到地上坐在草上面
like waiting to die
就好像在等死一樣
Because it is actually very dangerous to produce
因為其實生產非常危險
But why is it called the grass under the ground?
可是為什麼叫下地座草呢
I for this reason
我因為這個緣故
read this thing
讀了這個東西
feel very curious
覺得非常的好奇
to check all kinds of information
就去查各式各樣的資料
it turns out
結果就發現
these are western
這些都是西方的
Here is a Japanese
這邊一個日本的
you will find
你會發現
I used to have a baby
以前人生孩子的樣子
It's not the same as what you see now
跟現在你看到的不太一樣吧
still the same
還是又一樣了
Now it's old again
現在又恢復了古風
use now
又用現在
Again in this vertical way
又用這種垂直式的方式
giving birth
在生孩子了
This is a Greek peach
這個是一個希臘的桃湧
look at the people behind
你看後面的人
prop up his cutting nest
撐住他的割枝窩
there is a child here
這邊有一個小孩
about to fall
就要掉下來了
This is a Roman relief
這個是一個羅馬的浮雕
look at
你看看
there is a person here
這邊有一個人
prop up his cutting nest
撐住他的割枝窩
Then he put his hand here
然後他把手這邊接著
ready to pick up the baby
要準備接小孩了
this roman relief
這個羅馬的浮雕
and then this is
然後再來這個是
14th century England
14世紀英國的
Right, Mr. Shen
是吧 沈爺
A Miserable Woman's Handbook in England
英國的一個慘婆手冊
You can take a look
各位可以看一下
here is a rope
這邊有一個繩子
Then someone fell
然後這邊掉了一個人
pull the rope
拉著繩子
This man is teaching him how to push hard
這個人在教他你要怎麼樣用力
If the child in your stomach
如果你的肚子裡面的小孩子
if this shape
這個形狀的話
That's natural birth, right?
那就是順產對不對
It should be born smoothly, right?
應該會順利生下來對不對
if like other olympics
如果是像其他奧林匹克
Olympic gymnasts
奧林匹克這個運動會體操選手的
Posture words
姿勢的話
that's probably
那大概就是
Difficult
難纏嘛
unlikely to survive
不太可能生得下來
But in this wave shoveling manual, he will be taught
可是在這個鏟波手冊裡面會教導他
how do you make it smooth
你怎麼樣把順利
even a child in the belly
即使是小孩子在肚子裡面
Is it the hands on top, the head on top, or where are the feet?
是手在上 頭在上 還是腳在哪裡
how to massage your belly
怎麼樣按摩你的肚子
how to go around
怎麼樣轉轉轉
There is still a way to get this kid
還是有辦法把這個小孩子
turn into this
轉成這個樣子正胎
Then let the child be born smoothly
然後讓這個小孩子順利的生下來
Then look again
然後呢 再再看
this his pose
這個他的姿勢
he's not lying in bed
他也不是躺在床上
he is standing he is sitting
他是站著 他是坐著
he is standing with standing
他是站 伴站著
Again, this is an Arabic manuscript from the 14th century
再來這個是14世紀的一個阿拉伯的稿
manuscript look
手稿 你看
Same thing, hold up his pigeon spider
也是一樣 撐住他的鴿蜘蛛
the way he sits
他就坐的方式
find a way to get the child
想辦法把小孩
Mr. that is in another room
那先生在另外一個房間
Very nervous, I can't tell
非常緊張的樣子 看不出來
but anyway
但是不論如何
He is a vertical product
他是一個垂直式的生產品
this is safe
這個是平安的
Shin'an Dynasty's Japan
新安朝的日本
Inside of a demonic ultra near the twelfth century
差不多十二世紀的一個惡鬼超之裡面
you can see
你可以看得到
This man is having a baby
這個人要生孩子了
The devil is waiting here
惡鬼在這邊等
If someone dies hard to hide
如果有人難藏死掉的話
This evil spirit can come to the mad ghost
這個惡鬼就可以來找氣死鬼
then something to eat
然後有東西可以吃了
the point is not it
重點不是它
Although this is a Buddhist saying
雖然這個是一個佛教的話
but what am I interested in when I see
但是我看到的時候有興趣的是什麼
it's time for this person to give birth
是這個人要生的時候
he didn't lie flat
他沒有躺平
Someone behind him is supporting his den
後面有人撐住他的割之窩
Someone in front is going to give birth to the next child
前面有人準備要把小孩接著生下來
This is the so-called grass
這就是所謂的下地作草
When people used to give birth
以前的人在生孩子的時候
The era that we originally lived in
我們所原存陀的這個年代
I found out that it was written in the art
就發現就在藝術裡面有寫道
You don't lie flat when you're about to have a baby
要生孩子的時候不是躺平的
It is a vertical production experience
是一個垂直式式的生產體味
Then we continue to find all kinds of information
然後我們繼續去找各式各樣的資料以後
vertical production experience
就會發現垂直式的生產體味
Indeed many civilizations
確實是很多的文明
ancient and modern
就古今中外
Except by
除了經以外
It is the ancient Chinese and foreign
就是古代的中外
You can find such a vertical production experience
都可以找到這樣垂直式的生產體味
This one is from the fourteenth century
這個是十四世紀的一個
Vienna Herbs Inside
維也納的草本裡面
you can see
你可以看到
Someone behind him is supporting his den
後面有人撐住他的割之窩
to squat vertically
要垂直半蹲
half done pose
半做的姿勢
There's another woman here
另外這邊還有一個女性
Holding the medicine is like making medicine and stuffing it in
拿著藥好像是做藥要塞進去
Let her skid smoothly
讓她能夠順利滑胎
give birth quickly
把胎趕快的生下來
so what
所以呢
we can discover the whole process of being a mother
我們就可以發現一個做母親的整個過程
It turned out that no one actually studied it.
原來其實是沒有什麼人研究的
Because children have been born by women until now
因為生孩子到現在為止都是女人生嘛
right
對不對
Has a man ever given birth?
有男的生過嗎
Except Arnold Schwarzenegger
除了阿諾史瓦辛格
people about my age
年紀跟我差不多大的人
Should have seen Arnold Schwarzenegger have a baby
應該看過阿諾史瓦辛格生孩子
I am now in class if I say
我現在在課堂上如果講
arnold schwarzenegger
阿諾史瓦辛格
they say the governor of california
他們說加州的州長
child retired who
孩子已經退休了誰嗎
actually not
其實不是
women are giving birth
都是女人在生孩子
Because women give birth
因為都是女人生孩子
so no history
所以沒有歷史可言
historical research is
歷史研究是變
Confucianism is the study of normal and unchanging things
經學才是研究正常不變的事情
normal stuff
常態的東西
often
經常嘛
History is interested in change
歷史學有興趣的是變
something changed
有變的東西
we have
我們才有
Only historians are interested
歷史學家才有興趣
This is from Sima Qian
這是從司馬遷
That's what our Master Master said at the beginning
我們的主師爺開始就是這麼說的
What did Sima Qian say?
司馬遷的說法是什麼
Through the ancient scriptures
通古經
On the occasion of salvation
救天人之際
some are gods
有些是天的事情
some are
有些是
the boundary between man and sky
人和天之間的那個界線那個分際
Historians need to find it out
歷史學者要去把它找出來
If it is a matter of God, for example
如果是天的事情譬如說
It's God's business for a woman to have a baby
女人生孩子是天的事情
No man has children
沒有男人生孩子啊
So this is not a human thing
所以這個不是人的事情
women give birth
都是女人生孩子
But what is the human part?
可是人的部分是什麼呢
how do women give birth
是女人怎麼生孩子
there may be changes, right?
可能會有變化對不對
It's a day for a woman to give birth
女人生孩子是天
It may still be days until now
到現在為止可能都還是天
Although in the 1970s
雖然在1970年代
even earlier in the 60s
甚至更早60年代
when women exercise
婦女運動的時候
There was hope to use that artificial sub-worker
曾經有希望用那個人工子工
put it over there
把它放在那邊
Then after conceiving in it,
然後在裡面孕育好了以後
let him take the child
自己讓他把小孩子
It can come out like this
產出這樣啪就可以出來
But so far no success
但是到現在為止還沒有成功過
Even as a surrogate mother
即使是代理孕母
or women give birth
還是女人生孩子
Alright, between heaven and man
好啦天人之際
There is a divide between heaven and man
天和人之間有一個分際
Historians must first understand
歷史學者要先搞清楚
what are the gods
哪些是天的事
we don't have to touch
我們就不用碰了
because it doesn't change
因為它不會變的
are certain
都是一定的
common sense
經常的道理
what are human things
哪些是人的事情
It's how a woman lives
就是女人怎麼個生法
This matter may be subject to change
這件事情可能是有變化的
Tai Shigong said
太史公說
When historians are looking for heaven and man
歷史學家找天人之際
What about the human part?
之後人的部分呢
Changes through the ancient scriptures
通古經之變
you look early
你早早看
How to give birth in ancient times
古代是怎麼樣生孩子的
How to give birth in modern times
現代是怎麼樣生孩子
You compare ancient childbirth with modern childbirth
你把古代生孩子跟現代生孩子的事情
make him this change, figure it out
把他搞這種變化 把它搞清楚
then write it out
然後把它寫出來
It's called the words of a family
叫做成一家之言
what historians do is
歷史學家做的就是
On the occasion of salvation
救天人之際
Changes through the ancient scriptures
通古經之變
Then after writing out
然後寫出來之後
into a family
成一家之言
Maybe someone ignores you and doesn't believe what you say
可能有人不理你 不相信你講的
It's okay, this is my family
沒關係 這是我一家之言
what about family talk
一家之言要怎麼樣
Descendents of Changzhu Minshan
長珠民山傳之後世
someone will find out later
後面總會有人發現的
These people are waiting for me
這些人呢 就是在等我啊
That is to say
也就是說
They have put this information
他們已經把這下資料
I don't know it's been two thousand years
不知道放了兩千年了
no one ever noticed
從來沒有人注意過
Going down to the ground to practice grass is like saving lives
下地做草法 如救死
I watched Yuan Chuntuo
我因為看了袁純陀
Such a close relationship with his parents and children
跟他的親子的關係這麼密切
The role of this mother is so important
這個母親的角色這麼重要
But no one has studied
但是竟然沒有人研究過
When I was interviewing at Dr. Luo
當我在博士羅人口試的時候
I was doing legal history at that time
我那個時候做的是法律史
Just said the first paragraph
就剛剛講的那個第一段
All are fragrant and fragrant
全部都是香沙香香
hit a ball
打了一團
The oral examination committee said
口試委員就說
every time a woman wants to live
每次要婦女生活時
why is it bloody
為什麼都是血淋淋
They're all murderers?
都是殺人啊什麼
Women are not the most important vocation
女人不是最重要的天職
Is it just to have a baby?
就是生孩子嗎
why nothing good
為什麼都沒有好的事
Whatever the relationship between husband and wife
就夫妻關係怎麼都是
These things are in your thesis
你的論文裡面都這些東西
At that time, of course I had to graduate in order to get a Ph.D.
那時候我當然為了要博士要畢業
I say because of art
我就說因為藝術的東西
Because there is no data to study
因為這個沒有什麼資料可以研究
So we didn't study it
所以呢我們也就沒有研究它
That's because there is a new Zhangjiashan Han sister
那因為有新的張家山漢姐
the master check out
那主檢出來
So let's look at it from a legal point of view
所以我們就從法律的角度來研究它
then they all listen to me
那他們都聽我的
Just let me get my doctorate and come back
就讓我拿到博士學就回來
is working with
是與所工作了
But when I came back, I found out
可是我回來之後就發現
In fact, there is no information
其實不是沒有資料
because we have no gender awareness
是因為我們沒有性別意識
That is, when we are doing medical history research,
也就是說當我們在做醫療史的研究的時候
Didn't think of thinking about medical history from a woman's perspective
沒有想到從女性的角度來想醫療史
Our previous medical history research was basically
我們以前的醫療史研究基本上就是
civilian medical research
民醫研究啦
Emperor or Democracy Studies
皇帝或是民主研究
Emperor Neijing Shennong Materia Medica
皇帝內京神農本草京
all the way down
一路這樣子下來
Then go to Li Shizhen Materia Medica Gangmu
然後到李氏珍本草剛母
who is modern now
現在現代又有誰
Otherwise, it's not civilian medicine, it's democracy
要不然不是民醫就是民主
Otherwise, it is the legend of the great man
要不然就是偉人傳
Otherwise it is the history of progress
要不然就是進步史
It's just been making great progress
就是一直都非常的進步
More and more progress, and finally today
越來越進步 終於到了今天
How our medicine prospers
我們的醫學昌明如何如何
Without the perspective of the recipient being the user
沒有從那個接受者就使用者的這個角度
especially not writing medical books
尤其是不是寫醫書
but was taken care of by medical books
而是被醫書所照顧的
or being taken care of by others
或者是被別人照顧的
or someone else who acts as a caregiver
或者是擔任去照顧人的其他的
The kind that does not enter medical books
不進入醫書的那種
pure woman
pure女人
Women participate in birth, aging, sickness and death health care
女人參與生老病死健康照顧
really everywhere
真的是無所不在
But because of our medical history
但是因為我們的醫療史
no such consciousness
沒有這樣子的意識
So don't do this kind of research
所以不會去做這樣的研究
Going to the ground to make grass is as old as dead
下地作草法如舊死
such a sentence
這樣一句話
has been around since the fifth century
從第五世紀就出現了
No one studied it in 1500
1500年也沒有人去研究它
I found it very strange when I saw it
我看到以後覺得非常的奇怪
I want to know what it means
我想要知道下地作草法如舊死是什麼意思
found out
結果就發現了
In fact, there are all kinds of ancient and modern Chinese and foreign
其實古今中外有各式各樣
Images of this type tell us
這一類的圖像告訴我們
previous production pose
以前的生產的姿勢
is a vertical production position
是垂直式的生產體位
besides the person born because of this
因此生的那個人之外
other people supporting him
其他旁邊撐住他的人
is very very important
是非常非常重要的
I am due to time today
我今天因為時間關係
show you pictures
給大家圖片看
In fact, there are such explanations in medical books.
其實醫書裡面也有這樣子的說明
It's the so-called refusal of female parents
就是所謂的拒居女父輩
When you are about to give birth, there are many
要生的時候旁邊有非常多的
One wants to help him hold a pig
一個要幫他撐住個豬
one to help him tie his hair
一個要幫他綁頭髮
one to help him
一個要幫他
if passed out
要是昏過去了
I still have to struggle with him
還要拿掙扎他一下
Spray him with water
還要拿水噴他
splash him wake him up
潑他讓他醒過來
There are various
有各式各樣
there will be many different women
就會有很多不同的女性
while helping a woman
同時幫一個女人
give birth to a child
把小孩子生下來
And this woman who is about to give birth
而這個要生的女人
won't lie on a boat
不會躺在船上
Let the doctor see him and give him a finger
讓醫生來看他開一指
or open two fingers
還是開二指
or open three fingers
還是開三指
he will walk around
他會要走來走去
because he figured out
因為他想辦法
Make it easier for the child to get down
讓小孩比較容易下來
So I will keep walking in the room
所以會在房間一直走
Then he keeps walking through the room
那他房間一直走
The people next to him have been following him around like this.
旁邊的人就一直跟著他這樣繞
So the health care provider
所以這個健康照顧者
or maternity caregiver
或產育照顧者
or married woman
或是婚婆
or live-in
或者是住產者
In fact, the person born with
其實跟生的這個人
is one
是合為一體
Physical labor
肆體勞動
find a way to give birth to a child
想辦法把孩子生下來
stay with us
跟我們在
late twentieth century
二十世紀末
Later in France
後來在法國
this scene
看到的這個景象
It's actually a bit like
其實是有點像的
but we
但是我們這些
not in our impression
都不是我們印象中
if you ask me today
如果你今天問我
impression of having a baby
生孩子的印象
you wouldn't think
你不會想到
A photo like this, right?
這樣子的照片對不對
because we have entered into
因為我們已經進入到
after modern
現代以後
all lying in the hospital
全部都躺在醫院裡面
let the doctor
讓醫生
the height of that bed
那那個床的高度
almost
就差不多
The height of the doctor's convenience
醫生操作方便的高度
You won't come down casually
你也不會隨便再下來了
If it hurts and you can't give birth
很痛又生不出來的話
That might be the mother-in-law
那可能就婆父了
mother-in-law to a degree
婆父到一個程度
In fact, people have
其實人已經
born this person
就生的這個人
no longer conscious
已經沒有意識了
Actually I have a lot
其實我有很
some friends were born by in-laws
一些朋友是婆父生的
after birth
生出來之後
He said he didn't remember at all
他說他完全不記得
The moment he suddenly became a mother
他突然做媽媽的那個瞬間
he has no impression
他都沒有印象
feel very sad
覺得非常的難過
of course of course
當然是當然啦
want this myself
想要這個自己
consciously say
有意識的說
I suddenly become a mother
我突然做媽媽
the pain is severe
那個痛的程度是很嚴重的
when i was in class
那我上課的時候
will tell the students
會跟同學們講
go back and ask mom
你們回去問媽媽
How painful was that time
那個時候多痛
squatting or squatting
是蹲著身還是蹲著身
still sitting
還是坐著身
how much pain
痛到什麼程度
But my students come back
不過我的學生回來
Most of the answers are
大部分的答案都是
Mom said it hurts to give birth to you
媽媽說生你的痛
not as good as later
比不上以後
come to hurt my heart
來傷我心的痛
Then there's no way
那就沒辦法了
this totally leaves
這個完全離開
my original topic
我原來的題目
but anyway
但是不論如何
you can know
各位可以曉得
This form of production
這樣子的生產形式
In fact, it was like this in ancient times
其實在古代是這樣子
in the middle of the twentieth century
那二十世紀中葉的時候
Because the whole world is the same
因為全世界都一樣啦
the relationship of scientism
就是科學主義的關係
Make the mother-in-law's birth rate too high, too high
使得婆父產率太高太高了
So the French obstetrician
所以法國的富產科醫生
This is a French obstetrician
這是個法國的富產科醫生
decided to
決定要
nostalgia
思古之憂情啊
Get inspired by historical plot databases
從歷史的劇情資料庫當中得到靈感
How to help women who come to his clinic to give birth
怎麼樣來幫助來他的診所裡面生產的女性
It is possible to have an experience of the process of being a mother
可以有一個做母親的那個歷程的經驗
if they want
如果她們願意
If you are not in good health, of course you can't try it casually
如果身體不好當然不可以隨便試
sometimes it's dangerous
有時候是很危險的
It's really dangerous
確實是會危險啊
not without danger
不是沒有危險啊
But if you still can
但是如果還可以的時候願意的話
she will have a husband by her side
她會有一個丈夫在旁邊
licensed nurse
有住產式執照的護士
plus this obstetrician
加上這個產科醫生
help this maternity
幫助這個產婦
Use the Vertical Production Position
用垂直式的生產體位
Bone Fang left the little ones
骨方把小孩子給剩下來
What about her way of life?
那她這樣的生法呢
After I came out, I was actually challenging the time
出來以後其實在挑戰當時
France or Europe
法國或是歐洲啦
In fact, or around the world in the 1970s
其實或全世界1970年代的時候
This kind of mother-in-law birth rate is very, very high
婆婦產率非常非常高的這種
The custom of letting Qi intervene in the female body
氣泄介入女體的這種習俗
So some obstetricians were very upset about her
所以呢有一些產科醫生就非常不高興她
I think she's blocking people's money.
覺得她擋了人家的財路了
because if you give birth
因為你如果婆婦產的話
In the early stage, there were indeed more
前期確實是比較多的
What's more, she said that when you give birth there, it's a normal delivery.
而且呢就說她你到那邊生產都是順產
That's why we can use the vertical production position you just mentioned
所以才能夠用你剛說那種垂直式的生產體位
It is even more impossible if the childbirth is reversed
如果逆產更不可能
Then this doctor Michel Auden said
那這個醫生Michel Auden就說
No I also have a buttock on my side
No 在我這邊也有臀產的
If you look at it today, of course it's counterproductive.
這個如果在今天看當然是逆產嘛
It's not normal. The butt comes out first.
不是正產啊 這個屁股先出來
But if you're willing to massage it slowly
但是如果你願意慢慢的按摩它的話
In fact, this child is still born naturally or stretched out
其實這個小孩子還是順產還是伸出來
As far as the buttocks are still stretched out like this
就臀產還是這樣伸得出來
So you know that in this context
所以你就曉得在這樣子的脈絡之下
A resident is actually very, very important
一個住產者其實是非常非常重要的
Not only those doctors who write medical books are important
不是只有寫醫書的那些醫生重要
The whole process of getting a woman to be a mother
要一個女人做媽媽的這整個過程裡面
In addition to the fact that this person is very important
除了生的這個人非常重要之外
The person next to you is very important
旁邊幫助的人非常重要
This is the picture on the poster and the cover of my book
這個就是海報上那張圖也是我書的封面
It is because after I read these books
就是因為我看了這些書以後
I did research and I found
我做了研究我發現
This is really a big family from Sichuan
這個實在是這個是大族四川大族的
A moment for parents to pay attention to men's repayment
父母恩重男報經的一個時刻
you can see
各位可以看得到
Here is a woman in a vertical birth position
這裡就是一個女人垂直式的生產體位
Someone behind him supports his height
後面有人撐住他的個子位
Someone up front donated their sleeves
前面有人捐起袖子
give birth to him
要幫他生了
Who is this next to you?
旁邊這個是誰呢
Since the Buddha said that parents should pay attention to men
既然佛說父母恩重男報
Of course, if this is the mother, then this is the father.
當然這個是母的話 這個就是父了嘛
This is definitely not an obstetrician
這個絕對不會是產科醫生啦
not an obstetrician
不是產科醫生
this is father
這是父親
But this father is very interesting
可是這個父親很有趣的
He's holding something like a test, like a book
他手上拿了像檢測 像書一樣的東西
In fact, this is a very good explanation
其實這個非常好的說明了
Framing of our later study in the medical room
我們後來醫療室的研究的取景
from the perspective of your culture of birth
就是從你從生育的文化的角度
Let's see how to have a baby
來看怎麼樣生孩子
Then give birth to a female tetrasomy
然後生育是女性四體
is to help each other
就是互相互助
Born and cared for Helping people take care of each other
生得跟照顧的 幫助的人互相照顧
give birth to the child
把小孩生下來
Rather, these things are actually in medical books.
而是呢 這些東西其實在醫書裡面
There is a different way of saying
有別套的說法
Just this man next to him is a father figure
就這個人在旁邊是一個父親的角色
If he is in courteous clothing
他如果在以禮商服
It's a very important role, right?
是非常重要的一個角色對不對
But here he is taking a book and saying
可是他在這裡是拿一本書說
Listen to me, he's still anxious
聽聽我的 他還是很焦慮的啦
Because he's going to be a father
因為他要做爸爸了嘛
But what about these three people?
可是這三個人呢
I don't have time for him
其實沒有時間管他
They worked so hard to get this baby born
他們很努力的要把這個小孩生下來
And where does his authority come from?
而他的權威從哪裡來
not from his hands
不是從他用手操作而來
but in his hand
而是在他的手上拿的
something like a book comes
像書一樣的東西而來
What does that mean
什麼意思呢
In fact, in medical books
就是其實醫書裡面
very much recorded
記載的非常多
How do you feel about having a baby?
如何看待生孩子這件事
in what i do we just talk
在我所做 就我們只講
Yuan Cuntuo is the age of Yuan Cuntuo
原存陀 就是原存陀的這個年代
The matter of childbirth is gradually being treated by doctors
生育這件事情 漸漸被醫者
full involvement
全面介入
before Yuan Cuntuo
就是在原存陀之前
It's the Han Dynasty or earlier
就是漢代啦 或更早的時候
we see occasionally
我們看到 偶爾會出現
Medical books will appear related to childbirth
醫書裡面會出現跟生孩子有關的
Mostly after pregnancy
大部分都是在懷了以後
or after birth
或者是生完以後
Afraid of dystocia or poor health after giving birth
怕難產 或是生完以後身體不好
how to take care of
要怎麼調養
But in the fifth to seventh centuries
可是在五到七世紀
This is the era of Yuan Cuntuo
就是原存陀的這個年代
It’s the era I’m working on, and the problem hasn’t been explained yet.
就是我做的這個時代 問題還沒解釋
The doctor gradually began to write from the time of seeking a child
醫生漸漸的開始從求子就開始寫
That is, we want to be able to know
就是說 我們希望能夠知道
how can i get pregnant
怎麼樣能夠懷得上
So there are all kinds of suitors
所以有各式各樣的求子的一方
And earlier, the begging party
而更早的時候求子一方
They are basically in the middle of the room
基本上都是在房中方裡面
Just use the book in the room
就用房中書
That is, a man who wants to have a child
也就是男人想要生孩子
have son temple
要有兒子寺
Then you know the room
那你叫懂房中啊
The truth of the time period is happy at the same time
世期道理 同期快樂
There is a son who thinks he is good and old, Shou Ye
有子嫌良而老 壽也
Memorize the secrets of childbearing
背的是育房秘訣
words in the book in the room
房中書裡面的話
When you have sex you want to make your partner wife happy
行房的時候你要讓你的伴侶 太太快樂
You are only happy when she is happy, you don’t want to live your own happiness
她快樂你才快樂 你不要自己過著自己快樂
If you only want to be happy, you will not be able to have a good son
你若只過自己快樂就生不出好兒子來
The principle of the time period is happy at the same time, follow her principle
世期道理 同期快樂 順著她的道理
She thinks the reason is up, the time is up, then follow her reason
她覺得道理到了 時間到了 那就順著她的道理
Happy at the same time, she is happy, so are you
同期快樂 她快樂 那你也快樂
What will happen in the end?
結果會怎麼樣 有子嫌良而老受也
Having a son will be capable, kind, and live a long life
生兒子會又嫌能 又善良 又活得老 長命百歲
This is in the book in the room
這是房中書裡面
Who are the default readers of the book in the room? They are basically men
房中書的預設讀者是誰 基本上都是男的
Because he is the truth of the world, she told you to do this
因為他就是世期道理 她就叫你要這樣子做
Only your partner can give birth to a good son for you
你的伴才能夠替你生出好兒子
The ball pointers we saw before the fifth century were basically of this type
五世紀以前我們看到的球指方 基本上都是這一類的
But after the seventh century we discovered
不過七世紀以後我們就發現
between the fifth and seventh centuries
就五到七世紀之間
There are a lot of ball pointers that are late for wives
就有很多的球指方是給太太遲的
late for women
給女人遲的
Qianjin Fang Sun Simiao is a great doctor
千金方孫思妙 就是大醫生
Inside the Thousand Gold Prescription of Sun Simiao, a great doctor in the Tang Dynasty
唐代大醫生孫思妙的千金方裡面
The first volume in the front is about accumulating energy, which is about the basic principles
前面第一卷是蓄力 就是講基本道理的
From the beginning of the second volume, all ball fingers
後面第二卷開始就全部都是球指
What should I eat? In fact, there are some medicines in it.
應該吃什麼 其實裡面有些吃的藥
It used to be medicine for sheep in Fangzhong
是以前在房中方裡面是撞羊藥的
But now I put it in the woman's ball medicine to eat
可是現在也放到婦人的球子藥裡面去吃了
That is to say, a woman can be a mother
也就是說女性做媽媽能夠做一個
Concubine or a legitimate wife
嫡妻或者是一個正妻生
The role of the aunt
嫡母的這個角色
It is very, very important in this society of aristocratic families
在這個世家大族的社會裡面是非常非常重要的
you can see
你可以看得到
These sides of the ball
球子的這些方
Doctors also started to enter
醫生也開始進入
The woman in the medical book gradually became complete
醫書裡面的這個婦人方漸漸的完整
Not only after having a baby or getting pregnant
不是只有在生孩子或是懷孕以後才有什麼
itch
痒
tickle or
癢癢啊或者是
Itchy babies, these
痒寶胎啊這些
but from the beginning
而是從一開始
Ask for a pregnancy and a child and ask for a man
要求孕求子而且要求男子
Asking for pregnancy is a son's business
求懷孕是兒子這件事情
It also appeared in medical books this year
在醫書裡面也今年出現
So the woman party becomes an independent party
所以婦人方變成一個獨立的方出來
and born from conception
而且是從懷胎生育
How to fine tune after giving birth
生完以後要怎麼樣調精
Make his menstruation normal
讓他的月經能夠正常順
Then the whole body can be born again
接著整個人的體又可以重新生孩子
this set of ideas
這一套的觀念
It began to develop from the fifth century to the first book in China in the thirteenth century
從五世紀就開始發展到十三世紀中國的第一本
The so-called rehabilitation
所謂的復科全方
Re-examination book
復科書
It's the book about independent subjects
就是獨立科別復科的這個書
The two sides of Furen University appeared
復仁大學兩方就出現了
The way Furen University compares the two parties is
復仁大學兩方的排比的方式就是
Golden generation
金代胎產
payment in advance
先調金
set the gold
把金調好了
can
就可以
Then the red and white bag is solved so that there is no bad discharge
然後赤白袋解決不要有不好的排出物
then you can conceive
然後就可以懷胎
How to give birth to a baby after the pregnancy is over
胎完了以後怎麼樣來生小孩
Continue to transfer gold after giving birth
生完以後繼續調金
back again and again
又回來又是一個重新
A living dragon is wrong because it's about women
一條活龍不對因為是講女的
Another female body that can reproduce
又是一個可以重新生育的女體了
So the whole set actually starts with
所以這整套其實是從
The fifth century is what we're doing
五世紀就是我們在做的這個年代
gradually began to develop
漸漸開始發展
life begins to enter
一生就開始進入
Come to understand the whole female body
來了解女性的整個身體
Then what
然後呢
There are a lot of details in these processes
在這些過程當中有非常多的細節
I won't talk much because of time constraints
因為時間關係我就不多講
including birth
包括生的時候
how to which direction
要怎麼樣朝哪一個方位
Coating the placenta of the child after delivery
生完以後小孩子的胎盤包衣
Where should it be buried?
應該要埋在什麼方位
This child's life will not be
這小孩子的命才不會受
so it won't break
才不會壞掉
Because it was said before that if the placenta is bitten by a dog
因為以前就說胎盤如果被狗咬了
children may seek death
小孩子可能會找死
I don't know if you guys have heard this kind of story
我不知道你們有沒有聽過這種故事
like this
像這種
folk customs
傳說民間的習俗
There are still many
到現在都還有很多
But what about these things?
可是這些東西呢
In the past, they all had their own pictures.
以前都是分別有各自各樣的圖的
we are in the age of authors
我們在作者年代
between the fifth and seventh centuries
就五到七世紀之間
Gradually these pictures
漸漸的這些圖呢
Including the orientation of raw and the orientation of embedding
包括生的方位 埋包的方位
And the location of the delivery room, etc.
還有設這個產房的方位等等等等
all together
都全部同整起來
become dependent
變成依者在乎
and needs tidying up
而且需要整理
need to know knowledge
需要知道的知識
there is
還有就是
Where is the blood
血位哪些地方
how many months pregnant
懷胎幾月的時候
Which blood can't be dregs
哪個血不能渣
If it is scum, it may be aborted
如果渣的話就可能落胎
Actually in other words
其實換句話說
if he wants an abortion
如果他想要打胎的話
Just fuck that tire, right?
就去渣那個胎 對不對
So there is actually a whole set of knowledge that exists
所以其實是有一整套知識是在的
just to see who is using
只是看誰在用
But mastering the art
但是掌握藝術知識
basically male
基本上還是男性
what we see now
我們現在看到的
The knowledge of art is probably like this
藝術的知識大概是這樣
So around this time
所以都是在差不多這個時候
developed
發展出來的
those tires
那這些胎
Where are these blood levels?
這些血位的位置呢
with today's
跟今天的
some may be different
有一些可能是不一樣的
this of course leave
這個當然就離開
what we say
我們所講的
this part of the birth
產育的這個部分了
But just go into medical history
但是就進入到醫療史
After being challenged by the influence of gender
受到性別的影響挑戰之後
actually
其實
That is to say, the so-called twelve catties of wheat internal organs
也就是說所謂的十二斤麥五臟六腑
In fact, there is a historical evolution
其實是有歷史演變的
not fine
也不是精
not forever
也不是永遠不變的
It originally changed from eleven catties to twelve catties
它本來從十一斤後來變十二斤
how to match
怎麼樣搭配
Then a smell of blood on top
然後一個精上面的血味
In fact, there are different changes in different eras
其實在不同的時代也有不同的變化
After using these later found data, we
我們用了這些後來找到的資料之後
Combine it with today's and you'll find
再搭配今天的就發現
In fact, these have evolved
其實這些都是有演變的
Then we just said
那我們剛剛也說了
These require a vertical production
這些要一個垂直式的生產
walking around that room
那房間走來走去
impossible for him to be alone
不可能他自己一個人
There must be someone nearby to help
一定要有旁邊的人幫忙
So the caregiver becomes a very important person
所以照顧者變成是非常重要的一個人
The study of previous medical history
那以前醫療史的研究
Basically because it's all great people research
基本上因為都是偉人研究
Progress History Research
進步史研究
So it is not very good to help those who do not write medical books
所以不太會去助於那些不寫醫書的
medical participant
醫療參與者
But if we have a sense of gender
可是如果我們有了性別的意識之後
In fact, participate in medical activities
其實參與醫療活動
health care activities
健康照顧活動
but no chance to write a medical book
但沒有機會寫醫書
or leave your own gesture phrase
或留下自己姿勢片語的
Basically mostly women
基本上大部分都是女的
For many women involved in health care
就很多女性參與健康照顧
But they have the opportunity to write something
可是他們有機會寫下東西來
we're going to use other data
我們就要用別的資料
For example, time data
譬如說時刻的資料
or sculpture data
或者是雕塑的資料
This is what Buddha said just now in Parents N
這是剛剛佛說父母N中的
Another one is
另外的一個就是
The so-called push photo residence time
所謂的推照居時
mother taking care of baby
媽媽在照顧小孩子的時候
If a child is in the middle of the night
如果小孩子寶寶半夜的時候
kill the piss
殺了尿的話
mom puts herself
媽媽就把自己
push the baby to a dry place
把寶寶推到乾的地方
sleep in the wet
自己去睡在濕的地方
so as not to put the child
免得把小孩子
if you are
你如果在
when killing urine
殺尿的時候
slap you
打著你一把掌
call out
叫起來
this is not maternal love
這個就不是母愛
because of maternal love
因為是母愛的關係
so gently
所以就輕輕的把
Piss-killing son pushes aside
殺泡尿的兒子推在旁邊
let him sleep dry
讓他睡乾的地方
I will continue by myself
我自己去繼續
sleep in wet places
睡在濕的地方
is the expression of maternal love
才是母愛的表現
So
那麼
Babies are caregivers too
寶寶也是照顧者
very important role
非常重要的一個角色
then we are in
那麼我們在
other materials
其他的材料裡面
also see
也看到
Actually nanny
其實奶媽
is a very important role
是很重要的一個角色
No one has studied before
在以前也沒有什麼人研究
then with this
那有了這個
After the study of parent-child concept
親子觀念的研究之後
or caregiver
或者是說照顧者
as a mother figure
作為母親形象的
After this research
這種研究之後
image of mother
如母的形象
Mother's subject
如母的這個課題
also become negotiable
也變成可以談
The so-called milk becomes a mother
所謂的有奶變成是娘
who is called mother
誰稱作母
Although they are all called mom
雖然都叫作媽
Some are Zheng's wives
有的是鄭妻
is the aunt
是嫡母
some tree mothers
有的是樹母
some are loving mothers
有的是慈母
some thick mothers
有的是厚母
Some are foster mothers
有的是寄母
There is another kind called mother
還有一種叫如母
If a mother counts as a mother
如母算不算母
This is actually in Wei Jin's Mei Dynasty
這個其實在魏金的美朝
that's what i did
就是我做的這個
This era of Yuan Cunda
元純陀這個年代
Doctor Shi debated very fiercely
世大夫辯論得非常的厲害
Some world doctors think
有些世大夫認為
Mom has milk like a mother has milk.
媽媽有 如母有奶你啊
You grow up by eating his milk
你吃他的奶才長大
Of course when he died
當然他死的時候
Are you going to kill him for three months?
你要為他服殺三個月嘛
least least
最少最少
Are you going to serve him privately for three months?
你要替他服私嘛三個月
But some world doctors say
可是有的世大夫就說
Rumu is basically born of compassion and Bodhisattva
如母基本上都是悲菩出生的
Born as a sad daughter in the family
就家裡面的悲女出生
He just so happens to have tits for wild kids
他剛好野生小孩有奶
That's why I came
所以才來
how can that be
那怎麼可以
I am the precious son of the family
我是家裡面的這個寶貴之子
how can i come for a slave woman
我怎麼可以為一個奴婦來
He's dead and I'll take his wounds
他死了我還要替他服傷
what is this like
這像什麼
Who is the mother of the word mother?
到底媽媽這個字誰是母
If you have milk, you are a mother
有奶就是母
The one who gave birth to you is the mother
還是生你的才是母
Or dad's wife is your mother
還是爸爸的太太才是你的母
This is actually what we do
這個其實就在我們所做
The era of Yuan Cunda
元純陀這個時代
there's a lot of debate
有非常非常多的辯論
Then Fujinian library except
那麼富士年圖書館除了
and ours
還有我們的
Cultural Heritage Exhibition Hall of Shiyusho
食譽所的文物陳列館
Except what I just said
除了剛才講的
That Yuan Cunda wooden outside
那個元純陀木製之外
There is also a very famous wooden
還有一個木製非常有名
It is Su Dongpo's nurse's wooden
就是蘇東坡的奶媽的木製
Seki Na
如母人世木製名
this was me
這個我本來呢
I also like to find Chinese reading
也很喜歡找聽中念的
but today is not enough time
但是今天時間不夠
I'm also embarrassed to teach you how to read
我也不好意思再教大家起來念
you can see
你們可以看得到
Zhao Jun Su Shizi's sister is like a mother
趙俊蘇世子姊姊如母
Ren Shiming Cailian, have you seen it?
仁世名彩蓮 有沒有看到
Su Shi Su Dongpo's nanny is called Ren Cailian
就蘇世蘇東坡的奶媽叫做仁彩蓮
This Ren Cailian is following Su Dongpo's mother
這個仁彩蓮是跟著蘇東坡的媽媽
married into Su Dongpo's father's house
嫁到蘇東坡的爸爸家來的
Come to their house for 35 years
來他們家 35年
Miyahashi is diligent and thrifty, he treats the elderly, it is very good if he does not dump him
宮橋勤儉 治老 不甩 就非常好
Not only did he feed Su Dongpo's milk
不但有餵過蘇東坡奶
Also fed the milk of Su Dongpo's sister Ba Niang
也餵過蘇東坡的姊姊 八娘的奶
And also helped Su Dongpo take care of her own son
而且還幫忙蘇東坡照顧她自己的兒子
sushi's son
蘇世的兒子
Sell ​​on behalf
賣代過
It is equal to the three generations that nurse Ren Cailian helped to take care of
等於三代都是仁彩蓮奶媽幫忙照顧的
As a result, Su Dongpo, because of party disputes,
結果 蘇東坡因為黨爭的關係
When he was demoted to Huang Gang
被貶官到黃剛去的時候
He followed him and folded in yellow
他跟著他 折於黃
in the process of being demoted
就在貶官的過程當中
When the nanny went with Su Dongpo
奶媽跟著蘇東坡去的時候
Yuanfeng three years
元風三年
This is 1080
這個是1080年的時候
Died at Su Dongpo
就死在蘇東坡貶
Some people have children and sometimes they have children that are not their own
有些人會生小孩有時候養的不是自己的孩子
It is not necessary to benefit from death
死有以葬之不必其利也
dead must be buried
人死了必須葬
But not necessarily buried in his own box
但是不見得會葬在自己的箱裡
I follow it from thinking about it
我既其從於想之
Its spirit is everything
其魂氣無不之也
I come to worship you
我來祭祀你
I hope you come to eat
希望你來吃啊
in the future if i leave here
以後如果我離開這邊
i will send you to you
我會把你送給你
I worship you in different places
我在不同的地方祭祀你
I hope your soul follows me too
希望你的魂也跟著我
come and eat forever
一起來永遠來吃
Su Dongpo is a great writer
蘇東坡一個大文豪
The nanny is a member of his mother's family
奶媽是他媽媽家裡面的一個
The sad girl followed and married
悲女跟著嫁過來的
The great writer not only helped him write his name
大文豪不但幫他寫目致名
And this is Su Dongpo's words
而且這是蘇東坡的字
Just make money by writing
就字賺字書啊
earn your own money write your own
自己賺文自己寫字
Then ask someone to engrave such a famous name
然後請人刻了這樣一個目致名
A woman born from grief
一個悲菩出生的女人
Get the name of a great writer
得到大文豪的目致名
and write by yourself
而且還自己寫字
Why
為什麼
because of the mother's name
就是因為有母之名
There are mothers and milk TV mothers
有娘 有奶電視娘
This Shepherd's name is in our library
這個牧之名擺在我們圖書館
It's been a long time
也很久了
also in the 21st century
也是到了二十一世紀
Our scholars are only beginning to notice this
我們的學者才開始注意到這個
because realized
因為意識到了
and also see
而且同時看到
from the name of shepherd
從牧之名裡面
Su Dongpo
看出了蘇東坡
This feeling when being flattened
被扁觀的時候這種心情
right
對不對
It is not necessary to be born because of nourishment
生由於養之不必其之也
It is not necessary to stand after death
死又一丈之不必其立也
Who knew Su Dongpo
誰曉得蘇東坡
maybe you feel like
說不定你覺得自己
Maybe he died in Huanggang
也可能就死在黃岡
not impossible
也不是不可能
if i go back
如果我回去的話
I hope your soul will follow me
希望你的魂魄要跟著我一起
I will continue to worship you again
我還會繼續再祭祀你
Fengyang
鳳陽
so
所以
from different angles
從不同的角度
When I look at the medical room again
重新再來看醫療室的時候
what we saw
原來我們所看到的
medical classic famous doctor story
醫學經典名醫故事的
this kind of medical room
這類的醫療室
from the point of view of health care
就可以漸漸從健康照顧的角度
come in
來進入
different stories
就會發現不同的故事
on the other hand
另外一方面
we also found
我們也發現
Women in the role of health care
女性擔任醫療照顧的角色
Actually very diverse
其實非常的多元
and frequently
而頻繁
Not only female doctors
並不是只有做女醫生
Women's medical room is hard to do
女性醫療室很難做
Find a female doctor
找女醫生啊
In fact, just like this history of women's literature
其實就跟這個女性文學史
Hu Xiaozhen, Director of the Institute of Culture and Philosophy
文哲所的所長胡曉珍老師
he just
他剛剛
He returned to Taiwan almost at the same time as me
他跟我差不多同時回台灣
and then work together in the Institute
然後一起在研究院工作
When he was doing history of women's literature
那時候他做婦女文學史的時候
I also find it very interesting
我也覺得太有意思了
Because he was a talker for women in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
因為他做明清女性的談詞嘛
women's articles
女性的文章
but you know we used to do
可是你曉得我們以前做
in the history of Chinese literature
中國文學史的時候
I also find it difficult to do.
也是覺得很難做啊
It's hard for women
女性的很難做啊
Because Tang Poetry Sends Lyrics to Ming and Qing Dynasties
因為唐詩送詞明清小說
There are not many female poets of Tang poetry
那唐詩女詩人都沒幾個
talk about that
講來講去那個
That's the priestess
就是那個女道士
Nv Ji Nv language selection machine or Xuetao
女紀女 語選機 或學滔
There are not many people who send words and talk about them.
送詞講來講去那沒幾個
It's the truth of accommodation, Qing Zhao
就是住宿真理 清兆啊
Ming and Qing novels
明清小說
Little Writers Without Women in Ming and Qing Dynasties
明清沒有女的小作家
so there is nothing to write
所以就沒有什麼好寫的啦
That is, if you use the original
也就是說如果你用原來
Existing classification
既有的分類
Tang Poetry Sending Lyrics Ming and Qing Novels
唐詩送詞明清小說
Then you say I want to be a woman
然後你說我要做婦女
Then you come to see the little female writers of the Ming and Qing Dynasties
然後你來找明清小女小作家
you'll find it hard to do
你就會發現很難做
But Teacher Hu Xiaozhen
可是胡曉珍老師
just use another way
就用另外一套方式
what does he use
他用什麼
this difference
這個上差
He seems to be the same as last year
他好像是去年還前年的
Knowledge testing is here to talk about this
知識想驗就在這邊講這個嘛
right
對不對
what he wrote from women writers
他從女作家寫了什麼
to reschedule
來重新分期
You don't have to be limited by Tang poetry, Song Ci, Ming and Qing novels
你就不用受限於唐詩宋慈明清小說
women in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
就發現明清的女性
She still writes poetry
她還照樣寫詩啊
So although it is Tang poetry, Song Ci, Ming and Qing novels
所以雖然是唐詩宋慈明清小說
But the female writers of the Ming and Qing Dynasties
但是明清的女作家
with poetry long poetry
用詩歌 長詩歌的方式
to express the so-called talk of her story
來表現她的故事所謂的談詞
So there is no need to be limited by the original
所以就不需要在受限於原來
We can't find this predicament that women can do
我們找不到女人可以做的這種困境
when we have this awareness
當我們有了這樣的意識
When you look at the medical history, you will also find that
來看醫療史的時候也會發現
The role of female single medical care is very large
女性單人醫療照顧的角色非常的多
We used to be called Sangu and Liupo
我們以前叫做三姑六婆
It's a curse word
是來罵人的話
As a result, you look carefully
結果你仔細去看
actually what is it talking about
其實裡面講的是什麼
nun taoist hanging aunt pharmacist
尼姑道姑掛姑藥婆
Mei Po, Steady Po, Tooth Pot, Shiva, Ex-Woman
梅婆 穩婆 牙婆 濕婆 前婆
medicine woman
藥婆 賣藥的
A stable woman is a miserable woman
穩婆 就是慘婆
In fact, women's medical caregivers
其實就是女性的醫療照顧者
health caregiver
健康照顧者
what about others
其他的呢
Nun, Taoist, hanging aunt, Shiva, ex-wife
尼姑道姑 掛姑 濕婆 前婆
It's all about religion
其實都跟宗教有關
and sometimes involved in so-called religious medicine
而且有時候也參與所謂的宗教醫療
In fact, because of the relationship between single medical care, women
事實上女性因為單人醫療照顧的關係
health care
健康照顧
If she often participates in birth, old age, sickness and death
她如果常常參與生老病死
He really can't survive taking care of
他其實對於照顧活不過來
just can't give birth
就生不下來
mother and son king
母子君王
Or the baby in care dies
或者照顧的小孩死掉了
Or the serving mother-in-law died
或者服侍的婆婆去世了
The story of healing youth
隔骨療青的故事
The Tang Dynasty also started with a girl's story
唐代也是一個女生的故事開始的
It's the mother-in-law he took care of
就是他照顧的這個婆婆
nothing can cure
怎麼樣都治不好
He has no money for medical treatment
他又沒有錢在治病
He just takes the meat of his own thigh
他只要把自己的大腿的肉
Cut it off and feed it to my mother-in-law
割下來給婆婆吃
A story that also became very famous
也變得非常有名的一個故事
So when women who are health caregivers
所以當擔任健康照顧者的女性
his story didn't make it into the medical room
他的故事沒有進入醫療室
In fact, there are many medical faces of death
其實有很多醫療的死的面相
is invisible
是看不到的
when you see women in
當你看到了有女性參與的
after the medical room
醫療室之後
You will find that women often
就會發現女性很多時候
There is no rush to take care of
照顧不急也是有的
When he has to take care of many people at the same time
他同時要照顧很多人的時候
there is no way to take care of
是沒有辦法照顧的
I once read in the new Tang book "Legend of the Huntress"
我曾經讀在新唐書《獵女傳》裡面
A story called Li Miaofa is
一個叫李妙法的故事就是
he has married
他結婚了
marry somewhere else
嫁到另外一個地方去
I heard that my mother's father was sick
結果聽說娘家的父親生病了
dying
要死了
He can't go back and take care of his father
他沒有辦法回去照顧他的父親
he is a filial daughter
他是一個孝女
so he is sad
所以他很難過
I really want to go home
後來很想要回家
when you can't go back
又不能回去的時候
I heard that my father
就聽說父親
has passed away
已經去世了
Then he gave birth to another baby, can't go away
那他又生了一個baby 走不開
He really wanted to go back to the funeral
他非常想要回去奔喪
Because I heard that my mother is tired of taking care of my father
因為聽說媽媽照顧父親已經很累
sick too
也生病了
if he doesn't go back
如果他再不回去的話
maybe the mother died too
可能母親也死了
he won't be able to go back
他也就來不及回去
but when he left
可是他走的時候
his one year old child
他的一歲的小孩子
just keep crying keep crying keep crying keep crying
就一直哭一直哭一直哭一直哭
Ouyang Xiu is very powerful
歐陽修是很厲害的
author of new tang book
新唐書的作者
You must never believe what he wrote
你絕對不要相信他寫的
But what he wrote clearly shows
但他寫的可以很清楚的展現出
The Dilemma of Women as Health Caregivers
女性作為健康照顧者的困境
What
什麼
Li Miaofa saw his son crying
李妙法看到兒子在哭
I want to go back and take care of my mother
又想要回去照顧媽媽
So he bleeds
於是他鴿一乳流以行
What's the meaning
什麼意思
Cut off one breast and give it to my son
把一邊的乳房割下來給兒子
then stay later
然後留下來以後
and then he left
然後他人就走了
It means that he wishes to be able to
意思就是說他希望能夠
take care of both sides
兩邊都照顧到
The ones here still need milk
這邊的還要吃奶
Those over there need his care
那邊的要需要他照顧
How to do it
怎麼辦呢
cut off one breast
把一邊的乳房切下來
leave it to his son
留給他的兒子
Then he went back to take care of his mother
然後他就回去照顧他的媽媽
This is the Legend of the Huntress in the New Book of Tang Dynasty
這個是新唐書獵女傳
Biography of Li Miaofa
李妙法傳
Look at these frankincense
你看這些乳香啊
The history written makes people put a big question mark
寫的歷史都讓人打一個很大問號
But what?
可是呢
he clearly showed
他很清楚的展現出
so-called candle
所謂蠟燭
burn both ends
兩頭燒
On Women's Participation in Birth, Aging, Sickness and Death Health Care
就女性參與生老病死健康照顧
Often catching golden arrows and walking away both sides will not please
常常捉金箭走兩邊都不討好
no way to succeed
都沒辦法成功
In this case someone must die
在這種情況之下一定會有人死
But in fact, some have left their own children to take care of
但事實上也有把自己的小孩丟了去照顧
his brother's child
他的兄弟的小孩的
Because otherwise he is afraid that people will talk about him
因為不然他怕人家講他
Or his love can't bear it
或者他的愛心沒有辦法忍受
Seeing that my younger brother has become extinct
看著自己的弟弟已經絕後了
If you die again, there will be no more
如果再死的話就沒有了
So he had to put only one milk
所以他只好把只有一份奶汁
Just don't feed your own baby
就自己的小孩就不餵了
Just feed my brother's child
就餵自己弟弟的小孩
As a result, his son died
結果自己的兒子就死了
This is all written in the benefit biography
這種都寫進效益傳
if you don't
如果不這樣做
we don't know he does this kind of thing
我們也不會知道他做這種事情
Then write in the benefit biography
然後寫進效益傳
If he did it, we'd be sad to see it.
那他做了我們看了就很難過
Because he is a candle that burns at both ends
因為他就是蠟燭兩頭燒
So someone is bound to die
所以一定會有人死的這種情況下
Women have religious expectations
女性會有宗教的期待
is normal
是很正常的
He will seek the intervention of another world
他會尋求另外一個世界的介入
hope to have another chance
希望能夠有其他的機會
so what
所以呢
history of religion
宗教史
look at
你看看
Primordials are also a good example
原存徒也是一個很好的例子
He's widowed twice and he can't take it
他兩次手寡他受不了了
where is he going
他要去哪裡
become a monk
出家
I don't want to be a mother in this city
我不想在這個城市上做母親的角色
role of wife
做妻子的角色
I don't even want to be buried like before
我連埋葬都不要跟以前的
any one buried together
任何一個埋在一起
I want to get the heart of cultivation that he needs
我要領別障他所需修道之心
So the subject of religion actually has a gender awareness
所以宗教的課題其實有了性別的意識之後
In fact, there are also very interesting phenomena
其實也會發現有很有趣的現象
For example, the one on the far left, these three are all Avalokitesvara statues
譬如說最左邊的那個 這三個都是觀音像
The one on the far left is north
最左邊那個是北位的
The one in the middle is from the Song Dynasty
中間那個是宋朝的
The one on the right is from the Ming Dynasty
右邊那個是明朝的
you will feel special
你會覺得很特別吧
Yes or no
是不是
more and more like a girl
越來越像女生啦
We now see the statue of Avalokitesvara
我們現在看到觀音像
Seems like it's a female image
好像都覺得它是女性形象
In fact, Guanyin should have no male and female
事實上觀音應該無男無女嘛
is it a bodhisattva
它是菩薩嘛
But when people come close to it
可是就人來親近它的時候
In fact, there is a historical evolution
事實上是有歷史演變的
Early Avalokitesvara was like a male statue
早期的觀音像是像男像一樣
Avalokitesvara can be seen in the era of Songzi Guanyin in Ming Dynasty
可到明代宋子觀音的時代的觀音像
Already like a girl
已經跟女生一樣了
female admirers have a saying
女性崇拜者有一種說法
this is not my research
這不是我的研究
But some scholars have studied
但是有的學者就研究
During the process from Beiwei to Song and Ming Dynasties
在北位到宋明這過程當中
Female worshipers to Guanyin
女性崇拜者對觀音
It is the increase in the amount of worshiping Guanyin
就是崇拜觀音的量的增加
Make the image of Avalokitesvara gradually
使得觀音的形象漸漸的
From male to female
從男的轉成女的
That is to say
也就是說
and proximity make the person taking the photo
和親近感 使得照相的人
Doesn't it mean that Bodhisattva has changed into a human being?
不是說菩薩變人了啦
No, still the same Bodhisattva
不是 還是同個菩薩
but to create this image
但是要去塑造這個形象
A craftsman or entertainer of the image of a Bodhisattva
菩薩形象的工匠 或者是藝人
decided to make him appear as a woman
決定要讓他呈現女性的形象
Make this person who comes to worship him easier to get close to
讓這個來拜他的人 比較容易親近
So a change like this
所以像這一類的變化
The study of the history of religion
其實宗教史的研究
I'm doing it gradually
也是漸漸的都在做了
So, the relationship between women and religion
那麼 女性跟宗教之間的關係
really very close
真的非常的密切
You can see the example of Yuanchun Camel, which is a good example.
你看冤春駝的例子 就是一個很好的例子
But he's not the only one
可是他並不是唯一的
we were at about the same time
我們在差不多同個時代
Until the Tang Dynasty, some herdsmen
一直到唐代 一些牧民裡面
will see when the widowed mother dies
都會看到 寡母要去世的時候
Sudden dying said I don't want to be buried with your father
突然臨終說 我不要跟你爸爸葬在一起
Then this son will be very difficult
然後這個兒子就很難啊
Because it's customary
因為按照習俗也好
Whether Confucian norms or expectations
儒家的規範也好 期待也好
Parents' burial together is actually very important to this filial son.
父母合葬 其實對這個孝子的
reputation is important
名聲是很重要的
But this mother has been widowed for so long
那但是這個媽媽手寡了這麼久
and then fix until
然後一直修到
Then either go out or not go out
然後或者出家 或者不出家
Practice at home or practice as a monk
在家修行 或者是出家修行
Anyway, when he finally died, he told his son.
反正他最後要死的時候 交代兒子
That means I don't want to talk to my dad
就是說 我不要跟我爸爸
I don't want to grow up with your father
我不要跟你爸爸長在一起
At this time, this son's Mu Zhiming
這個時候 這個兒子的牧志明
if you see
如果大家看
The Tang Dynasty is the period from the Northern Wei Dynasty to the Tang Dynasty when this kind of Mu Zhiming
唐代 就是北魏到唐代的這一類的牧志明的時候
You'll see the hardships of that son
你就會看到那個兒子的艱辛困難
Because he wants to be a dutiful son
因為他要做一個孝子
But he can't let his mother be buried with his father
可是他用不能讓他媽媽跟父親合葬
So he will be in this Mu Zhiming
所以他就要在這個牧志明裡面
in this preface
這個序文裡面
A lot of thinking and emphasizing the hardships of being a widowed mother
多多琢磨強調母親手寡的艱辛
How to pull him up
怎麼樣把他拉拔長大
So in the end, his sons and daughters are respected and dare not stop
所以他到最後 兒女適尊 不敢為止
The relationship between women and religion
女性跟宗教之間的關係
The way he died actually showed a lot
他的死的方式其實非常多的展現出
to another world
他對於另外一個世界
or his attitude towards religion
或者他對於宗教信仰的態度
This is also about the age we are doing
這也是在我們做的差不多這個年代
In fact, burning life is included in the main case of bhikkhunis.
其實燒生 這個在比丘尼主案裡面就有
Women burn raw offerings to Buddha
女性燒生 供養佛
Hope to be reincarnated and reincarnated as a man
希望能夠轉世 投胎變成男人
Only in the next life can I become a Buddha again
下一輩子再也能夠才變成佛
Because of course it involves the issue of big students and small victories
因為當然牽扯到大生小勝的問題
It's just that some people think that
就是有的觀念裡面認為
There is no way for women to get directly from this life
女性沒有辦法直接從這一生
Because it is born of misunderstanding, it will directly become a Buddha
因為是誤會之生 直接就成佛
Must be transformed into a man in the next life
必須下一輩子先轉成男人
Only by cultivating as a boy can you become a Buddha
再從男生修行才有辦法成佛
because there is such a relationship
因為有這樣的關係
So some female practitioners feel
所以有的女性修行者覺得
Then I'll get out of this life
那我趕快脫離這一生好了
because this is disgusting
因為這個太討厭了
I can't even become a Buddha directly
我都不能直接成佛
So there is burning body to make offerings to the Buddha
所以有燒身 供養佛
There is also a Mr. Lu
另外還有一位路師長
This is also our colleague
這也是我們同事
My predecessor, Mr. Liu Shuheng made it
我的前輩 六叔恆老師做的
It is women who want to make offerings to the Buddha
就是女性要供養佛
Is to give myself to my children
就是把自己交代兒女
he wants to be in the forest
他要在森林裡面
put the body in the forest
把遺體就放在森林裡
or in a cave
或者是放在洞窟裡
Just don't bury it anyway.
反正就不要埋就對了
Let the birds and beasts eat
讓鳥獸來吃
Because this is to provide for all living beings
因為這就是供養眾生
In fact, it is making offerings to the Buddha
其實也就是在供養佛
is the same reason
是一樣的道理
So with this idea
所以有這樣子的觀念之下
In fact, in the same era
其實在同一個時代
There is a so-called concept of doomsday
有所謂的末法觀念
that is
就是說
Law will disappear one day
法總有一天會沒有的
will cause this dharma
會造成這個佛法
no way to go on
沒有辦法繼續下去的
Three groups are the most dangerous
三個群體是最危險
most annoying
最討厭的
most in need of correction
最需要糾正
be well supervised
要好好監督的
one is the monarch
一個就是君主
the king may be
君王可能是會
Because at that time the law of destruction
因為那個時候滅法
There was also the Northern Dynasty, and there was also the Tang Dynasty
北朝也有 唐朝也有
There are so-called kings who exterminate Buddha
都有所謂的滅佛的這種君王
don't believe in buddha
不相信佛
or believe
或者是相信道
or because buddhism absorbs too much of their taxes
或者是因為佛教吸收了太多他們的稅收
Or because saints are all monks
或者是因為聖人都出家
Don't join the army, don't pay taxes, etc.
也不去當兵也不繳稅等等等等
So there are monarchs who exterminate Buddhas
所以就有君主滅佛
So there is a saying in this life group
所以在這個生團裡面就有一種說法
These are the Buddhist intellectuals
就是這些佛教的知識分子
will talk about the so-called destruction
會談論所謂的造成罰滅
Three very serious effects
很嚴重的三個影響
one of them is the monarch
其中一個就是君主
bad monarch may
不好的君主就有可能
So it is very important to correct and supervise the monarch.
所以要糾正要監督君主這個很重要
The other is the corruption within the Shengtuan itself.
另外一個就是生團自己內部的腐敗
It may also result in a penalty
也有可能會造成罰滅
The last one is the blackening of a woman's body
最後一個就是女人身體的會烏
So if a woman becomes a monk
所以如果女人出家的話
It will reduce Buddhism and politics by 500 years
會使佛法政法減少500年
500 years or 800 years 500 years
500年吧還是800年500年
so at first
所以一開始的時候
Shakya's aunt
釋迦的這個姨母
When Da Yi is going to leave home
大一道要出家的時候
Sakyamuni didn't want it
釋迦本來也不要的
But then there was an economic
但是後來有經濟過
various discussions
種種種不同的討論
Finally let him leave the house
最後還是讓他出家
But when you leave home, you must pay special attention.
但是出家呢就要特別的注意
female practice
女性的修行
don't let him misunderstand the body
不要讓他誤會的身體
to influence other monks
去影響到其他的僧侶
In fact among our colleagues
事實上在我們的同事
It is in the research done by Teacher Liu Shufen
就是劉淑芬老師所做的研究裡面
You will find that there are some monks in this item
會發現有一些僧侶的這個目字裡面
Will write that it's a good thing he's not a monk woman
會寫說還好他不是僧侶女人
or next to his lament
或者是在他的這個悲鳴的旁邊
inside famous saying
裡面著名說
this is my lock
這個我的藏鎖
is where the burial
就是埋藏的地方
how far away from women
要離開女眾多遠多遠
How far away from Bhikkhuni
離開比丘尼多遠多遠
Yuan Chuntuo is very hopeful
那袁純陀是很希望
Don't hide his sleepy heart
別藏他所已睡修到之心
Of course he wants to be with other students
他當然是希望跟其他的生
you hide together
你藏在一起
Do you want to hide with your husband layman?
要不要跟丈夫俗人藏在一起
But what?
可是呢
Sheng didn't want to hide with him
生也沒有要跟他藏在一起
Because after all, the female body
因為畢竟女性的身體
under this context
在這一個脈絡底下
not good enough
其實不夠好
So there are women like this
所以也有這樣子的女性
The Body Becomes a Religious Study
身體變成一個宗教研究
or a subject for discussion in the history of religion
或宗教史討論的一個課題
Well, in order for women to get out of this
那麼女性為了要脫離這樣子
a voice of misunderstanding
一個誤會之聲
Or get out of this pain
或者是脫離這個苦吧
He may have had various activities during his lifetime
他在生前可能有各式各樣的活動
For example he might visit a temple
譬如說他可能參觀寺廟
he may visit holy key
他可能拜訪聖基
In addition, he may form the so-called women's society
另外他可能組成所謂的女人社
This is also the age we are doing
這也是我們這個做的這個年代
from China until about modern times
就是中國一直到大概近世
fifth to twelfth centuries
五到十二世紀
There are probably such data showing
大概都有這樣的資料顯示
women in the name of religion
女性以宗教為名
form a group
結成團體
Pay each other money
互相納錢
It's the same as dating, but it's not economical
搭會一樣 但是不是存經濟的
For example, sometimes it is led by nuns
譬如說有時候是比丘尼帶領的
The women of this village in this village
這個鄉裡的這個村的女人
How much to invest together
一起投資多少多少錢
then put it together
然後放在一起
if someone dies
如果有人去世的時候
Let's help her with the funeral together
我們就一起幫她辦喪事
If someone in the family is married
如果家裡面有人有婚上
when you need help
需要幫忙的時候
Let's use this money to help her together
我們就拿這筆錢一起去幫助她
or someone to help her
或人也一起去幫忙她
People give people money
人出人出錢
a religious woman
也就是一個宗教女性
All-female religious groups
純女性的宗教團體
to serve women special
來服務女性特殊的
needs of birth, old age, sickness and death
生老病死的需求的
This has also been unearthed.
這個也有史料已經挖掘出來
This is relatively recent
這都是比較最近
some are from the past
有一些是過去的
Some are recently discovered historical materials
有一些是最近發現的史料
if it is
那如果是
What you just said is that you are married
那剛剛講的都是已經出嫁
then widowed
然後手寡
Then there are these social life
然後有社會生活的這些
if not
如果不是呢
if she was young
如果她年紀輕輕的時候
just want to get married
就想要出嫁呢
In fact, we are in the Bhikkhuni Biography
其實我們在比丘尼傳裡面
will see
就會看到
not easy
不太容易
even parents would still want
就是父母還是會希望
he can marry
他能夠出嫁
so what
所以呢
The first forbidden solution in the Biography of Bhikkhuni
比丘尼傳裡面第一個禁解
The First Biography of a Bhikkhuni
比丘尼傳的第一個傳記
It is a forbidden solution in modern times
是近代的一個禁解
he is already widowed
他是已經手寡了
he married
他出嫁
then widowed
然後手寡
On his own, he should have read the book
就靠著他自己 他應該是讀過書的
fearless overcooked daughter
無畏太熟的女兒
He relied on his own poetic talent
他靠著他自己的詩文 才華
can play the piano
還會彈琴
I went to different aristocrats' homes to work as tutors.
就到不同的貴族家裡面去做家庭教師
Feed themselves
養活自己
This is the story of the fourth century
這是四世紀的時候的故事
The Second Story A Second Example of a Bhikkhuni Biography
第二個故事 比丘尼傳的第二個例子
not a widow
就不是手寡的婦人了
The second example is a living female
第二個例子就是一個在世女
unmarried girl
就是沒有出嫁過的女孩子
she wants to become a monk
她要出家
Her father said tradition says
她的父親說 傳統都說
Triple, repeat again
三重啊 再家重複
get married repeat repeat son repeat son
出嫁 重複 複子 重子
why do you want to become a monk
你怎麼要出家
What is the weight of getting married? I have never heard of it.
出嫁是哪一重 沒聽過
No such thing, don't let her become a monk
沒有這種事情 不讓她出家
The daughter told her
這個女兒就跟她說
Why bother triple then reason
何必三重 然後為理
why
為什麼呢
Because what she wants to do is walk the walk
因為她要做的是入身行道
jealous of everything
妒脫一切
I don't care about my parents
我不會不在乎父母兩親的
don't care about parents
不會不在乎父母親的
Because the purpose of my leaving home is to
因為我要出家的目的就是
Hope to save all sentient beings
希望能夠普度眾生
help everyone
幫助所有的人
let alone parents
何況是父母親呢
So you don't have to get married
所以不需要一定要出嫁
triple
才能夠有三重
doesn't have to be triple
不一定要三重
is a reasonable approach
才是一種合理的做法
But her father still didn't want to
但是她的父親還是不願意
So then
所以呢 後來
Father, of course, has many stories.
父親這個當然很多故事啦
no more
就不多講了
My father went to ask the Fotu City
父親就去問了這個佛圖城
a big monk
一個大和尚
The great monk will give him one
大和尚就給他一個
the story is too complicated
故事太複雜了
talk too much can't talk
講太多不能講
Anyway, it's right to convince his father.
反正就說服了他父親就對了
He put sesame oil on his hands
他在他的手上塗了芝麻油
tell him to go back
叫他回去
After my father went back, he took a look on the sesame oil
父親回去以後在芝麻油上面看一看
In the end, my father applied sesame oil to his palms.
結果父親就是手掌塗了芝麻油
Because I saw a big monk in the bonus
因為看到一個大和尚在獎金
then this
然後這個
Fotucheng told his father
佛圖城就跟他父親講
You see, what you see is a bit like clairvoyance
你看你看的這個有點像透視眼一樣
hand becomes a screen
手變成一個螢幕
Then I saw a big monk inside the bonus
然後看到一個大和尚在裡面獎金
Then this Fotu City told his father
然後這個佛圖城就跟他父親說
The big monk here is your daughter's previous life
這裡面這個大和尚就是你女兒的前輩子
He was already a great monk in his previous life.
他前輩子就已經是大和尚了
In this life, I should have left home
這輩子本來就是應該要出家的
so you still have to leave home
所以你還是要出家
it will do you no harm
會對你只有好處沒有壞處
After my father heard it, because of a magic trick
父親一聽以後因為出了神機了
The hand has become a screen
就已經手已經變成螢幕了
so believe it
所以就相信了
Just let my daughter leave the house
就讓女兒出家了
As a result, after her daughter became a monk,
結果對女兒一出家以後
Because this father is in
因為這個父親是在
Shila's men
時辣的手下
It is actually very heavy when it is tiger and hot
時虎時辣其實也是非常重
the king of happiness
幸佛的這個君主
After his daughter became a monk, this father actually
他女兒出家之後呢這個爸爸其實
The monarch is happy that of course his daughter is ordained
君主很高興他當然他的女兒出家
So dad gave him a promotion too
所以爸爸也給他升官了
so this
所以這個
The final meaning of this biography of the bhikkhuni is that
比丘尼傳這一個傳的最後意思是說
Why bother to triple and then be a gift
何必三重然後為禮
In fact, to help parents, it is not necessary to get married
其實要幫助父母親啊不見得要出嫁
If you become a monk, you can help your father get promoted
出家的話還可以幫爸爸升官
Because marriage was very important at that time
因為那個時候的聯姻很重要就是正親
Marriage exchange?
婚換嘛
Those who are married can help each other and become officials so that they can climb up
結婚的對象就幫互相幫忙做官可以往上爬
But this daughter relied on the way of becoming a monk
可是這個女兒是靠出家的方式
Make my father promoted to the top
使得自己的父親升官往上爬
There are actually many more stories.
那這些故事呢其實還有很多啦
for example
譬如說
And the daughter wants to become a monk
再是女兒想要出家
But mom has already set him up for a kiss
可是媽媽已經幫他訂了親了
So after the engagement, the fiancée over there has already made an engagement
所以訂了親以後那邊未婚婦已經下過聘
The dowry has come
已經聘禮都來了
We just talked about the Taishi Law
我們剛剛講那個太史律
This is the Tai Shilu in 267
就是這個267年那個太史律
That is, if the offer has been accepted,
就是說如果已經接受聘金的話
Even if you are already married, you cannot remarry
就是算已經成婚不可以回婚
what to do at this time
那這個時候怎麼辦
if you want to get married
如果要回婚的話
We must return their employment to others
就要把人家的聘還給人家
So in biography of bhikkhuni
所以在比丘尼傳裡面
There will also be great monks
也會有大和尚
just take
就拿
The window head is washed with water. What is the window head?
窗頭為水洗 什麼叫窗頭
In fact, it is the slave stele wrapped in this black cloth scarf
其實就是包著這個黑布巾的奴碑
It means that the monk is actually very rich.
意思就是和尚其實是很有錢的
He has slaves to run his treasures and human resources
他有奴隸 經營財寶 也有人利資源
When he thinks that the debtor is going to become a monk, the debtor lady will follow
當他覺得這個債司要出家的債司女士有會跟的
when he is willing to accept him as an apprentice
他願意接受他為徒弟的時候
He can give one of his own servants to the betrothed husband's family
他可以把他自己的一個奴婢就送給這個定親的夫家
As a companion to the original bride price
當作是陪原來的這個聘禮用的
You will know why the monarch will destroy the Buddha at that time
你就曉得那個時候為什麼君主會滅佛
Do you think that the money in this temple is actually very, very rich in manpower and material resources
你以為這個寺廟裡面的錢其實是非常非常的人力物力的資源豐富
There will also be sayings in the bhikkhuni village
比丘尼寨裡面也會有說
Hey, the girl is engaged again
欸 再是女訂婚了
He wanted to become a monk but his mother got him engaged
想要出家可是媽媽幫他訂了婚
After getting engaged, the son-in-law
訂了婚之後呢 這個女婿
Even the engaged son-in-law refuses to let go
就是訂婚的女婿怎麼都不肯放手
Be sure to chase after, the girls have already gone to live in the temple
一定要追 等下女孩子都已經到寺廟去住了
He's going to run to him and harass him for trouble
他還要跑去找他 騷擾他找麻煩
As a result, again
結果欸 又一次
This son-in-law was killed by a cow when he was about to go out to harass him
這個女婿要出門要去騷擾他的時候就被牛給撞死了
like this type
像這類型
There are actually a lot of stories in this episode
本集故事其實非常多
That is to say, widowed women become monks
就是說手寡的女性出家是
she has her way and her problems
她有她的途徑跟問題
Besides, if you want to become a monk, she has her own way and problems.
再是你要出家有她自己的途徑跟問題
What will happen after leaving home?
那如果出家之後又有什麼呢
In the north, there are mud drills in the south
北位其實南朝有泥鑽
There were so-called herdsmen in the Northern Dynasties
北朝有所謂的牧之民
As we just talked about, people like Yuan Cun Tuo Zuo
就我們剛剛講的像原村拓奏牧之民
In fact, there are also many monks and herdsmen
其實也有很多比丘泥的牧之民
For example, this bhikkhu mud
譬如生隻這個比丘泥
A shepherd was unearthed
就有一個牧之民出土
can see
可以看得出來
Not only can he
他不但可以到
The Demon of the Empress Dowager of Civilization
受文明太后之妖
Go inside the palace to get the bonus
到宮裡面去獎金
The so-called insider bonus
就所謂的內道長獎金
Everyone recognizes the Empress Dowager Civilization
文明太后大家都認得吧
Emperor Xiaowen's
孝文帝的
dark backup is grandma
暗備份是祖母
But my mother when I was in the north
不過北位的時候的母親
Later, grandma's concept seems to be a little confused
後來祖母的觀念好像還有一點混淆
but anyway
但是不論如何
He is raising the empress dowager of civilization and raising Xiaowen emperor
他是養文明太后是養孝文帝
Raising Emperor Xiaowen like this
把孝文帝養大的這樣子
This one was later sinicized
後來就漢化的這一個
Empress Dowager Civilization herself is surnamed Buddha
文明太后自己姓佛
he asked for this
他就請了這個
This girl goes to the palace bonus
這個女生之去宮裡面獎金
this life
這個生之
he has many mentors
他有很多的師徒
this disciple
這個徒子徒
We don’t have time to talk about Tusun Network
圖孫網絡 這個我們也沒有時間多講
But the names are lined up with well-known intellectuals and officials at that time
但是名字排開都是當時有名的知識分子跟做官的人
What about a person like this?
那麼這樣子的一個人呢
We're not really sure where he came from.
其實他從哪裡出來的我們不是很確定
But after he entered the palace
但是他入宮了以後
After he got a bonus in the palace and got acquainted with these concubines
他在宮裡面獎金跟這些後妃熟了以後
He suddenly said
他突然就冒出一句說
Actually, I have a pretty nice niece.
其實我有個侄女還蠻不錯的
You are talented, you have good virtues and surnames
才華呀 德姓都不錯
Later, the Empress Dowager Wenming was an emperor in the north.
後來呢 文明太后就是北位的一個皇帝
When the prince accepted his niece
在太子的時候就納了他的侄女
Later Queen Mother Lin
就是後來的林太后
So you can know that after the relationship between the entry bonus and the stinky concubine is established,
所以你就可以曉得這個入宮獎金跟臭妃關係搞好之後
He can also send his niece to the palace
他就可以把他的侄女也送進宮
who is empress dowager lin
林太后是誰
Empress Dowager Lin is what we just talked about
林太后就是我們剛才講的
The heroine when Yuan Chuntuo was alive
元純陀活的時候的那個女主
That is, when his son was emperor
就是說當他的兒子在做皇帝的時候
he is the de facto ruler
他是實質上的統治者
In other words, Sunny because of faith, religion
換句話說 森尼因為信仰 宗教信仰的關係
Especially the concubine who is like a female mud
尤其是女泥 一般的後妃
when he has no way to touch the outside
當他沒有辦法接觸外面的時候
What the girl said when she went in
女泥進去講的話
In fact, it will be influential
其實是會有影響力的
It's not that there is no such thing in the Southern Dynasties
那南朝不是沒有這種事情
Southern Dynasties also have
南朝也有
There is a subtle influence in the Bhikkhuni Biography
比丘尼傳裡面有個知妙影響了
Appointment of envoy Kim Thu
後來金週四使的任命
In fact, it later affected the political situation of the Six Dynasties
其實後來影響了六朝的政局
We don't have time to talk about this anymore
這個我們也沒時間再多說了
but anyway
但是不論如何
if you are a talented girl
如果你是有才華的女孩子
or you were born fine
或者你出生還不錯
or you like to read
或者是你喜歡讀書
or you don't want to get married
或者是你沒有想要出嫁
If you do things like the Zhuzonghui and Guangji
做主宗會跟廣濟式的事情的話
During the Northern Dynasties of the Wei and Jin people
在魏金人北朝的時候
have a very good baked
有一個非常好的出爐
is to become a monk
就是出家
If you don't take you after you become a monk, you may go everywhere for bonuses
出家之後不帶你有可能去到處獎金
Because they have to live in a temple
因為他們有一定要住在一個寺廟
Just like the Tang Dynasty, didn't we just talk about it?
就像唐朝我們剛剛不是講了嗎
he can go anywhere
他可以到處走
So the Empress Dowager Civilization invited him
所以文明太后請他
I might ask him to give a speech in Pingcheng
在平城的時候可能就請他演講
Came to Luoyang after bonus
到了獎金後來到洛陽
Maybe ask him for a bonus
說不定也請他獎金
So in this case
所以在這種情況之下
This bhikkhuni also travels everywhere
生之這個比丘尼也是到處旅行
And you can also recommend your niece
並且還可以推薦自己的侄女
After entering the palace, it became another
到宮裡面後來變成了另外一個
The heroine is a social and political queen mother
女主一個社政的太后
The relationship between these people is basically like this
這些人的關係基本上是這樣的
Yuan Chunta is here
園淳陀在這裡
He first married Mu Shi
他先嫁給慕氏
later married new lou
後來嫁給新婁
news
有情訊
Mu Shi gave birth to a daughter
慕氏生了一個女兒
married to yuan
嫁給姓元的
In fact, the surname Yuan
其實這個姓元的
Yuan Chuntuo
跟元春托
you look
你看上去
still the same family
還是同一家親
Yuan Weiqing was born
生了這個元未慶
It was later that he died in
就是後來他死在
this place in this villa
這個別墅的這個地方
where is the empress dowager of civilization
文明太后在哪裡
it's here
在這裡
where is empress dowager lin
林太后在哪裡
where is the branch
生枝在哪裡
his aunt is here
他的姑媽在這裡
After Empress Dowager Wenming married Brother Xuanwu
文明太后跟宣武弟結婚之後
gave birth to younger brother Xiaomin
生了孝敏弟
Empress Dowager Civilization
文明太后其實
The Empress Dowager of Civilization is also good
文明太后也好
Empress Dowager Lin is also good
林太后也好
we can say
可以說是我們講
Empress and heroine are
女皇帝女豪傑就是
The people Chen Dongyuan doesn't want to talk about
陳東元不想講的那些人
Wu Zetian's predecessor
武則天的前身
they are actually very important
他們其實很重要的
It's all because of the role of mother
都是因為母親的這個角色
gave birth to a good son
生了一個好兒子
son made emperor
兒子做了皇帝
then he can come
然後他就可以來
social affairs queen
社政做太后了
So the role of mother
所以母親這個角色
Actually there are many
其實有很
as a family
作為一個家庭
The Transitional Role of the Ruler
統治者的過渡角色
In the past, Chen Dongyuan felt that
以前陳東元覺得
they are like normal people
他們跟一般人
women don't matter
女人沒有什麼關係
But if we take the heroine
可是如果我們把女主
It's the empress dowager
就是特色政太后
When we put it in the family relationship we just talked about in the whole speech
放在我們剛剛整個演講所講的這種家庭關係裡面的時候
You will find that the heroine is actually a family role
你會發現女主其實是一種家庭角色
She's actually one because if it's my father it's the same father's family
她其實是一個 因為如果是家父是同一個父親家
As far as family and country are concerned, a country is actually governed by one family.
就家國 一個國其實是一個家在管
That's what the Emperor's House is in charge of.
就是帝王之家在管的話
When there is a loophole in the succession order of the emperor
當帝王的繼承順序 繼承出現漏洞的時候
There are not enough people to inherit. No heir or the inheritance is too small
就不夠人來繼承上 沒有繼承人或者繼承太小
when you need help
需要人幫忙的時候
This mother believes that she is the most trustworthy and will not usurp the throne
這個媽媽就以她最值得信賴 又不會篡位
Of course, before Wu Ze, I never thought about it
當然在武則之前 從來沒有想過
Somebody's going to literally throw their own son away and usurp her son's tail
有人會真的把自己的兒子撒掉 然後篡她兒子的尾了
But at least not before
但是至少在這之前沒有
Therefore, since the Han Dynasty, my mother
所以母親從漢代以來
It's always been a time of succession crisis
一直都是繼承危機的時候
very important a substitute a transition
非常重要的一個替代者 一個過渡者
The heroine is also in the context of such a family inheritance
那女主也就是在這樣一個家庭傳承的脈絡當中
become a politician
變成政治人物的
Plus what we are reading now includes Yuan Chuntou
再加上我們現在所讀的包括袁純頭
I just said that his original surname is Tuo
我剛剛說他本來姓拓吧
There are so-called women's schemes to use Furen
本來就有所謂的女性計謀從用復仁
Just listen to women's schemes, it's rare to fight a war
就是聽女人的計謀 打仗難得去打
But how to strategize is to listen to this tradition of women
但是如何謀略策劃是聽女性的這種傳統
So before the old men came in to rule
所以在先輩人進來統治之前
When they were in the grassland, there was already a so-called women's country
他們在草原的時候就已經有所謂女國
It is the history and experience of women as rulers
就是女性做統治者的這種歷史跟經驗
under this context
這個脈絡之下
When the Empress Dowager Civilization came in, she became a very important
當文明太后進來之後成為一個非常重要的
This is the research of other scholars
這都是其他學者的研究
Put it in this context and share with you
放在這個脈絡中跟各位分享
If we know that the Sinicization of Emperor Xiao Wen is the Northern Wei Dynasty of China
我們如果知道肖文帝漢化是中國北魏
very important word for a development
非常重要的一個發展的話
In fact, there is a very important prerequisite to be able to Sinicize
其實要能夠漢化有一個非常重要的前提
It was the reign of the Empress Dowager Civilization before him
是文明太后在他之前的統治
has laid the foundations of the so-called domination of farming nations
已經奠定了所謂統治農耕民族的基礎
a foundation of farming culture
農耕文化的一個基礎
In the age of the Empress Dowager of Civilization
在文明太后的時代
He established the Fenglu of the ancestors of the Northern Wei Dynasty.
他確立了北魏先輩人的這個奉祿
That is to say he is no longer feudal
就是說他不再是封建的
Not that I'm a monarch or that I'm a noble leader
不是說我一個君主或是我一個貴族領袖
The following are my men
下面都是我的人馬
Then I will eat this piece of grass
然後我就吃這一塊草地
Instead, it becomes a centralized ruling monarch.
而是變成一個中央集權的統治君主
Let's manage my bureaucrats by paying salaries
下面用發薪水的方式來管理我的這些官僚
This was established during the time of the Empress Dowager Civilization
這個是在文明太后的時候建立的
Sanchangzhi
另外還有三長治
The so-called administrative bureaucrats at different levels at the local level
就是所謂的地方層級不同層級的行政官僚
It was also established during the time of the Empress Dowager Civilization
也是在文明太后的時候建立的
The other one is the so-called Kimita Osamu
另外一個就是所謂的君田治
everyone knows this
這個大家都知道
make everyone sweeter
讓每個人都有更甜
Then the sweet tax is paid to the central government
然後收的甜的這個稅收都繳到中央來
After all is paid to the central
全部繳到中央來之後
Then I pay the officers
然後我再發薪水給官員
Under this monarch-subject relationship
在這種君臣關係之下
It turns out that feudal lords had their own soldiers and horses
原來封建的領主有自己的兵馬人馬
Then do not listen to the phenomenon of central government
然後不聽中央統治這種現象
will gradually become less
就漸漸會變得比較少一點
So the Empress Dowager Civilization passed through his
所以文明太后透過了他的
in his social age
在他社政的時代
these political reforms
所做的這些政治的改革
institutional reform
制度性的改革
Emperor Xiaowen
使得後來的校文帝
Have the opportunity to do so-called Chinese
才有機會做所謂的漢話
That is to say, wearing Han Chinese clothes
就是說穿漢人的衣服
Learn the language of Chinese Han people
學中國人漢人的語言啊
Or change it from Tuoba to Yuan, etc.
或者是改成拓拔改成姓圓啊等等等等
Empress Dowager of Civilization
文明太后之後
Another heroine is the so-called
再一個女主就是所謂的
Queen Mother Lin is actually a typical
林太后她其实是一个典型
Use the role of mother to set up witness
用母亲的角色来设证
or a person who takes power
或是取得政权的一个人
Because in the Northern Wei Dynasty
因为在北魏的时候
I'm afraid that the Queen Mother will set up a witness and rob power.
就是怕太后会设证 会抢权利
So once a certain prince is established
所以一旦立了某一个皇子
will kill this mother
就会把这个妈妈给杀掉
lest in the future this mother will take this child
免得将来这个妈妈将这个小孩子
After the son becomes the emperor, he will take charge of the affairs
儿子做了皇帝之后会来管事
Early Northern Wei Dynasty
北魏在早期的时候
There has always been such a tradition
一直有这样的一个传统
Then Empress Dowager Lin's husband Xuanwu Emperor
那么林太后的丈夫宣武帝
never had an heir
就一直没有子嗣
Because the harem is very afraid of children
因为后宫都很怕怀的小孩
In case I have a son
万一我生了一个儿子的话
i might be killed
我可能就被杀了
so the harem prays to each other
所以后宫彼此祈祷
or ask
或者是询问都说
when were you pregnant
你是什么时候怀的
when did i conceive
那我是什么时候怀
if i found out i was pregnant a little earlier than you
如果我发现我比你早一点怀
then watch this
然后看这个
This is related to the medical book I just talked about
这个又牵扯到刚讲医书
Because traditional medical texts believe that
因为传统医书认为
If you are three months pregnant
如果从怀孕三个月的话
calling you from behind
从后面喊你
real
真的
if you turn to the right
如果往右边回头的话
it will be a girl
就会是女孩子
if you turn your head to the left
如果往左边回头的话
it will be a boy
就会是男孩子
Why male left female right
为什么 男左女右
there are various
就有各式各样的
So I discussed with you again that you got pregnant last month
所以我又跟你討論說你是上個月懷孕的
I just got pregnant this month
我是這個月才懷孕的
As a result, when I call you, turn around
結果我一叫你一回頭
he will be male
他會是生男的
then i can continue to conceive
那我就可以繼續懷下去
So if I say I'm pregnant this month
那如果說我這個月懷孕的
I got pregnant earlier than him
我比他早懷孕
Then I call me back
然後我一叫我一回頭
i will have a boy
我是會生男孩子的
I will open
我就打開
i want to be later than you
我要比你晚
or if i turn around
或者如果我一回頭
i will give birth to girls
我是會生女孩子
It does not matter
那沒關係
I will continue to conceive
我就繼續懷下去
Because my child will not experience the crown prince
因為我的小孩不會歷程太子
i won't be killed
我就不會被殺掉
So the harem of the Northern Wei Dynasty
所以北魏當時後宮
When such stories are spread like this
有這樣子的流傳這些故事的時候
Queen Mother Lin said that in the middle of the night
林太后據說半夜的時候
pray that i would rather die
祈禱說我寧可死
I also hope to help my husband pass on the family line and receive
也希望能夠幫丈夫傳宗接待
you see how important it is
你看這多重要
understand
懂不懂
a solid woman
堅真的一個女人
She prayed silently alone in the middle of the night
她半夜一個人默默的祈禱
I don't know why this word comes out
也不知道為什麼這話會流出來
Of course she came out by herself
當然也是她自己流出來
let everyone know she prays in the middle of the night
讓大家都知道她半夜祈禱
I don't want to be like other concubines
我不要像其他的後妃
I am not afraid of death
我不怕死
I would rather have a son
我寧可生兒子
so that my husband can pass on
讓我的丈夫能夠傳後代
I also want to be able
我也要能夠
I would also like
我也願意
she looks like this
她一方面這樣子
that aspect
那一方面
According to the biography of Empress Dowager Lin
林太后的傳裡面說
She is full of talents
她性充物多才藝
Why does he have a little understanding of the Buddhist scriptures?
他略得佛經大義為什麼
Because his aunt is a nun
因為他姑姑就是一個比丘尼嘛
bonus nun
獎金的比丘尼
And his martial arts are also very powerful
而且他的武功也非常厲害
He once called a group of ministers to shoot arrows together
他曾經召集群臣一起來射箭
everyone shoots well
每個人都射得不錯
Then he shoots a real hole
然後他就射了一個真孔
set over there
定在那邊
One shot hits the real hole
一射就射到真孔
So all the ministers assisted him
所以群臣都輔他
So the heroine is not just relying on
所以女主並不是只是靠
Affiliation with groups or politics
群帶關係或者是側近政治而已
In Beihui, these heroines all had their own talents
北惠時候這些女主都有自己的才華
We just talked about the political strategy of the Empress Dowager Civilization
我們剛剛講文明太后的政治謀略
You can see his establishment of this system
你可以看到他的這種制度的建立
Later Sinicization of Facts
事實的後來的漢化
Very important foundation for success
可以成功非常重要的基礎
Empress Dowager Lin has such martial arts
林太后有這樣子的武功
Then we can engage in mother-child kindness politics
然後又能夠有搞母子親恩政治學
So then on the other hand
所以然後另外一方面
The history books say that he personally writes the handwriting of Wanji
史書說他親欄萬機手筆之段
He's actually the one who judges.
他其實是會判案的一個人
I won't talk about the details today
那今天我就不講這個細節
Another little book called The Words of the Princess
另外一本小書叫公主之詞
Just the one introduced by Mr. Wu Xianwu
就剛剛武先吳老師介紹的那個
It's just talking about how he judged the case
就是在講他怎麼樣判案
Of course, at the end of the sentence, he was partial to girls.
當然判到最後他是偏談女生
this is nonsense
這個是沒話講的
Well, he's not alone anyway.
那不論如何他不是孤家寡人
What's the meaning
什麼意思
don't rule alone
不是自己一個人在統治
There are supporters next to him
他旁邊是有支持者的
These supporters, apart from the ministers who admire him,
這些支持者除了群臣佩服他的
or afraid of him
或者怕他的之外
In fact he has female staff
事實上他有女性的幕僚
Our subsequent research found
我們後來的研究發現
Actually he has some princesses
其實他有用一些公主
He has a good relationship with the princess
他跟公主的關係不錯
This is appeasement
這也是姑息
what is this called
這個叫什麼
Good relationship between walk away
走離之間關係很好
He has a good relationship with the princess
他跟公主的關係好
He used the princess as a lady in a letter
他用公主來做女士中女上書
to help him with the paperwork
來幫他辦理文書
help him pass the message
幫他傳遞消息
Discuss things with him
跟他謀異討論事情
Do you guys think this is weird?
各位覺得這樣很奇怪嗎
It's not surprising at all
其實一點都不奇怪
if you go back and see
你們如果回去看
Ban Zhao who wrote this female world
寫這個女界的班昭
In fact, when he was in Donghan
其實他在冬翰的時候
It's the staff of Empress Dowager He Xideng
就是和喜鄧太后的幕僚
the same
一樣的
He Xi but Empress Dowager Deng is in power
和喜但鄧太后在執政
while in power
在掌權的時候
when being a hostess
做女主的時候
have all kinds of problems
有各式各樣的困擾
He will discuss it with Ban Zhao
他會跟班昭討論的
Ban Zhao suggested to him
班昭就建議他
Because Ban Zhao came from
因為班昭出自
big family
大家族班家嘛
who wrote this Hanshu
寫這個漢書的
he knows many things
他知道很多事情
just discuss with him
就跟他討論
So the heroine is never alone
所以女主從來都不是一個人
But of course he depends on
只是他當然要靠
he's the mother thing
他是媽媽這件事情
climb up step by step
一步一步的爬上來
get this
取得這個
dominant position
統治的地位
But he needs to be able to rule
但是他要能夠進行統治
It's definitely not just cruel and easy to kill
絕對不是只是殘忍好殺
or wait wait
或者是等等等等
None of that kind came later
都不是那一類在後來的
The so-called fox girl can be the culprit
所謂狐妹偏能禍主
in this slanderous language
這種詆毀的語言裡面
so you can get the truth
所以可以得到真相的
In fact, these heroines have staff beside them
事實上這些女主旁邊都有幕僚
There are people who help her
也有幫忙她的人
It's hard not to say
難得不說了
Female staff actually have
女性的幕僚其實也有
And the staff of Queen Mother Lin
而林太后的這個幕僚
Many of them came from the princess
就很多都是從公主出來的
then this is an interesting place
那這就是一個有趣的地方了
In fact, this research of the princess
其實就是公主的這個研究
We used to study women's political history
我們以前研究女性政治史
They are all research heroines
都是研究女主
They are all studying the female emperor, social and political empress dowager
都是研究女皇帝 社政太后
Few people study the princess
很少人去研究公主
i have a student
我有一個學生
He thinks I wrote Death of a Princess
他覺得我寫了公主之死
he is not convinced
他不服氣
he thought he was going to write about the living princess
他覺得他要寫活著的公主
what good things did you do
都幹了什麼好事
He wrote a book called
他就寫了一本書叫
Princess politics without the Southern and Northern Dynasties
未經南北朝的公主政治
The result is well written
結果寫得不錯
In fact, these princesses who have not lived in the Northern and Southern Dynasties
其實這些未經南北朝的公主
It's not that you can't get involved in politics at all.
並不是完全不能參與政治的
And when they get involved in politics
而且他們參與政治的時候
all successful
都還滿成功的
The reason is that they use the so-called
原因是他們用的就是所謂的
Physical Discourse on Liquid and Air
液體同氣的身體論述
It is absolutely impossible for a princess to become an emperor
公主絕對不可能變成皇帝
Except that the 50% daughter wants to become the emperor
除了五折天的女兒想要變皇帝以外
No other princess has the courage to become emperor
其他從來沒有公主有勇氣想要變皇帝
no idea
也沒有這個念頭
But what about them and their emperor brothers
可是呢 他們跟他們的皇帝兄弟
between us
彼此之間
It can be said with this body discourse of so-called liquid with air
可以用所謂的液體同氣的這個身體論述來說
The princess also cares about the country
公主也是在乎家國的
so the princess has her own
所以公主有他自己
untouched beauty princess
未經的美套公主
has his own house, has his own residence
有他自己的房子 有他自己的居地
Of course, father horses are miserable.
當然啦 父馬都很慘啦
In some books of that time
那個時候的一些書裡面
In that file it will be written
那個文件裡面會寫到
Father and horse are afraid to go home
父馬都不敢回家
Because the princess, that's his princess' home
因為公主 那是他公主的家
The father horse seems to have been married instead
父馬好像反而是嫁過去的一樣
The princess sometimes calls him
那公主有時候叫他來
tell him to come tell him to go tell him to go
叫他來 叫他走 就叫他走
He doesn't seem to be his family
他好像不是他家
So, the princess is the head of the family.
所以呢 公主才是一家之主
that from a negative point of view
那從負面的來看
father horse is in pain
父馬很痛苦
But because the princess has her own home
不過因為公主有自己的家
And the housework, the student
而且那個家務這個學生
I made this location map of the residence of this princess
做了這個公主的居地的這個位置圖
In fact, it's just a little bit outside the imperial city.
其實就在皇城出來一點點的地方
Therefore, the residence of the princess is often the so-called
所以公主的居地常常是所謂
soft politics
軟性政治
To kill a dragon is to kill a dragon, not to kill a dragon politically to kill a dragon
殺龍就殺龍不是殺龍政治殺龍
where soft politics are enforced
軟性政治執行的地方
That is to say, when the monarch and his kings or ministers
就是說當君主和他的諸王或群臣
Fry and tear face in the palace
在宮廷上炒翻撕破臉
There's no way to pull down my face anymore, there's no way to deal with it
沒辦法再拉下臉沒辦法處理了
a case can't be solved
一個案子不能解決了
or someone is going to be killed
或者有人要被殺了
At this time, the princess will have a waist inkstone
這個時候公主就會腰硯
Waist they come to eat at home
腰他們來家裡面吃飯
This time it is his brother who is the king
這個時候做君主的是他的哥哥
sometimes even his brother
有時候甚至是他的弟弟
Then he will act like a sister
那他就會用姐姐的姿態
sometimes his brother
有時候是他的哥哥
Sometimes he'll use the phrase that we're all the same parents.
有時候他就會用我們都是同一個父母
born of this soft gesture
所生的這種軟性的姿態
to intercede
來求情
then come to lobby
然後來遊說
and then to solve some
然後來解決一些
Seems like it can't be returned
好像看起來不能轉還
But in the end it was transferred to Princess Juli
但是最後在公主居立裡面轉還的
something like this
這樣子的事情
So after doing this
所以這樣子的做下去之後
we discover
我們發現
women's politics
以前女性政治
We all feel like we're going to be queen mothers
我們都覺得要當太后的
Only female emperors and heroines can study
女皇帝女豪傑才能夠研究
Actually no
其實沒有
Princess politics can actually be studied
公主政治其實也是可以研究的
That means the identity of the daughter
那也就是說女兒的這個身份
the same person
同氣一息的這個人
In fact, it is worth studying
其實是值得研究的
Another student recently wrote an article
最近又有一個學生寫了一篇文章
that is a college student
那個是一個大學生
I really admire him and work hard
我真的是佩服他又用功
And smart, I think female students in Taiwan
又聰明,我覺得台灣的女學生
They're all smart, beautiful, and hardworking
都是又聰明,又漂亮,又用功
It makes people happy when they see it, the more they interact, the happier they are
看了就讓人高興,越交越愉快
This female student just wrote an article
這個女學生呢,就寫了一篇文章
write what? write
寫什麼?寫
The tomb of Li Jingxun was excavated in 1957
李靜遜墓是1957年挖掘出來的
Since it was excavated
從挖掘出來之後呢
because it has so many beautiful things in it
因為它裡面墓杖有這麼多漂亮的東西
So there have always been archaeologists or historians
所以一直都有考古學家或歷史學家
In fact, few historians
其實歷史學家比較少
Archaeologists do more than scholars of cultural relics and archaeology
考古學家跟文物考古的學者做得比較多
because it's these things
因為它的這些東西
Li Jingxun is with the generation
李靜遜是隨代的
Sui Dai, his surname is Li
隨代,他姓李
But his grandmother is the daughter of Emperor Suiwen
不過他的外婆是隨文帝的女兒
Yang Lihua
楊麗華
His father's surname is Li, of course
他的爸爸姓李,當然啦
Otherwise call me Li Jingxun
不然叫李靜遜
His mother is the Yang family
他的媽媽那邊是楊家
He came down with Emperor Wen's family.
就是隨文帝那家下來的
So there are so many beautiful things in his tomb
所以他的墓裡面有非常多漂亮的東西
Scholars of the past, after this tomb was dug up in 1957
過去的學者,1957年這個墓挖出來之後
there have always been scholars
一直都有學者
From the shape of these cups
從這些杯子的形制啦
The bath food of the necklace
項鍊的這個浴食啊
or shape
或者是形制啦
to study
來研究
For example, these arts and crafts that come with the class
譬如說隨堂就隨帶的這些美工藝術
Is it influenced by the West, including Persia?
是不是有受到西方包括波斯的影響啊
all kinds of these
各式各樣這些
where did these things come from
那這些東西是從哪裡來的
Is it made in China itself?
是中國本土自己做的呢
Or was it sent by someone else?
還是別人送來的呢
buried as a gift
當作禮物才埋在在埋
Look at how old this girl died
你看這個女孩子幾歲幾歲死的
died at nine
九歲就死了
A nine-year-old girl came out with a lot of
一個九歲女孩子目裡面出了一大堆的
amazingly beautiful thing
漂亮的不得了的東西
Of course it will arouse the interest of many scholars.
當然會引起很多學者的興趣嘛
fifty years of research
做了五十年的研究
is studying each of these utensils
就是在研究這些每一個器物的
Cultural traceability Art form and so on and so on and so on
文化溯源 藝術形制等等等等等等
Until recently because of gender
一直到最近因為性別的關係
realized
意識到
Why are these nine year old girls
這些九歲女孩子為什麼
worthy of so many amazing things
配得這麼多了不起的東西
Let's go back and find out
再去看追溯發現
His grandmother is Yang Lihua
他的外婆是楊麗華
Who is Yang Lihua's father
楊麗華的爸爸是誰
Emperor of Hydrology
是水文帝
Why did the daughter of Emperor Water Wen
水文帝的女兒為什麼會
so important
這麼重要
In fact, Emperor Shuiwen took his daughter Yang Lihua
其實水文帝把他女兒楊麗華
Married to the last emperor of the Northern Zhou Dynasty
嫁給了北周最後一個皇帝
Then put the North Zhou
然後就把北周
Give the state a string
給州給串尾了
so understand what
這樣了解有什麼
So Yang Lihua is very painful to her father
所以楊麗華對她的爸爸是非常痛苦
just embarrassing
就是很尷尬
An awkward and painful relationship with a woman
很尷尬又很痛苦的一個婦女關係
Yang Lihua is actually a princess
楊麗華其實是個公主
but she wasn't a princess when she married
但她嫁出去的時候不是公主
she is queen
她是以皇后
she was married to be queen
她是被嫁做皇后的
But after marrying the queen
可是嫁過皇后之後
Her own father took her husband's
她自己爸爸就把她先生的
Stringed by the state
被州給串尾了
Then she becomes a weed
然後她就變成水草
like a princess
好像是公主的身份
She's not in the mood for a princess
她其實沒有公主的心情
Because she's actually the father of the kingdom
因為她其實是王國之父
her mood is kingdom father
她的心情是王國之父
She loves her granddaughter very much
她非常疼愛這個外孫女
This is Li Jingxun
就是這個李靖迅
take her with you
把她帶在身邊
when her granddaughter is dying
當她外孫女要去世
she died at the age of nine
她九歲就去世了
In fact, everything in it
其實這裡面的所有東西
It is likely that they are all collected by Yang Lihua
很可能都是楊麗華的收藏
Not necessarily the collection of nine-year-old Li Jingxun
不見得是九歲的李靖迅的收藏
And that wooden or those wooden cups
而那個木製或那些木杯
or those recorded in
或那些記載裡面
source
所講的那個源流
The main numbers are from the Northern Zhou Dynasty
主數都是從北周
Then talk about how the Li family
然後講李家如何如何
I don't want to say that he is Yang Lihua and the daughter of Emperor Shuiwen.
完全不願意講他是楊麗華是水文帝的女兒
you can see it from here
你就可以從這邊看得出來
If you understand the barrier in terms of gender
如果你從性別的角度來理解這個幕障的話
To understand this barrier from a daughter's point of view
從女兒的角度來理解這個幕障的話
It’s not just about cultural exchanges, artworks, public welfare or things.
就不只是文化交流 藝品 公益 或者是東西
what touches this topic
什麼接觸這個議題
In fact, it also includes the mood of a daughter
其實還包括了一個女兒的心情
Use her granddaughter to express herself
用她的外孫女來展現她自己
An attitude towards her addition and addition
對她的附加跟附加的一種態度
So it's interesting that the study is the latest one
所以這是很有意思的研究是最新的一個研究
We haven't done enough research on daughters.
我們對於女兒的研究其實還不夠多
There are many things worth studying
還有很多東西值得研究的
in other words
換句話說
The last name of Yuan Cuntuo
原存坨的最後名的最後
Painted crouching blue bowl
繪臥藍碗 無絕分方
Although it's all in the past
雖然這都是過去的事了
But it can inspire us
但是它能夠給我們的啟發
In fact, it's been a long way
其實一直遠遠流長
This division is not over yet
這個分方還沒有結束
still going on
還在繼續下去
We got some inspiration from Yuan Cuntuo's life
我們從原存坨的人生得到了一些啟發
History also learns from gender
歷史學也從性別得到的啟發
And in the process we found
而在這個過程當中我們發現
people of different classes different ethnic groups
不同階級的人 不同族群
For example, ancestors of different classes
比如說先輩 不同階級的
For example, something like Yuan Cun Tuo
譬如說像原存坨這樣子的
banned like this
禁訊這樣子的
Or what we just said to help people produce
或者我們剛剛說的這種幫助人生產的
This different class of midwives and stable women
產婆穩婆的這種不同階級的
In fact there is age and backup
事實上還有年齡跟備份
will lead us to some of the past
都會引起我們對於過去的一些
New perspectives on subjects taken for granted
以為理所當然的課題的新的看法
So if we can combine the empress with the heroine
那麼如果我們能夠把女皇帝跟女豪傑
When put into context to understand
放到脈絡中來理解的時候
In fact, there is no need to be so repulsive
事實上也不用這麼排斥
That is actually like
也就是說其實像
The Story of Huiming Empress Dowager
回明太后的故事
Empress Dowager Lin's Story
林太后的故事
including Wu Zetian
包括吳澤天
Or Yang Lihua and his granddaughter
或者是楊麗華跟他的外孫女的
these stories
這些故事
Stories from the royal family
皇室裡面的這些故事
In fact, I put it in the vein
其實我放在脈絡裡面
in the vein of the family
放在家族的脈絡
in the context of political operations
放在政治的操作的脈絡
or in the context of empire building
或是帝國建制的脈絡裡面
In fact, there are many things to talk about
其實還有很多東西可以談
and see something new
而且可以看出新的東西
Not necessarily with ordinary people
不見得跟一般人
Women's life in general doesn't matter
一般的婦女生活沒有關係
may still be related
可能還是有關係的
that apart from gender
那除了性別這個東西之外
I just said class and ethnicity
我剛剛也說了階級跟族群
we've always been like this
我們向來一直都這樣
I think this should refer to each other
認為這彼此應該互相來參看的
studied the 1986 scholar proposed
研究了1986年學者提出
It has been more than 30 years since I did this from a gender perspective
性別角度來這樣做之後到現在也超過30年了
After 30 years, in fact, we also found that as we just said
30年下來事實上我們也發現就像我們剛剛講的
Class and ethnicity other than gender
除了性別以外階級族群
In addition, age and backup in Chinese history
另外在中國史裡面年齡跟備份
is often well worth digging up
常常是非常值得挖下去的東西
So let’s continue to do it. Now some scholars have proposed the so-called multiple intertwined historical research.
所以呢再繼續做下去現在有學者提出所謂多元交織的歷史研究
In fact, historical research is inherently diverse and intertwined, and it is impossible to talk about it from only one angle.
其實歷史研究本來就要多元交織不可能只從一個角度談
Today I'm just starting with a gender perspective
今天我只是用性別的角度做出發點
Then use the round-lipped camel as an example
然後用圓唇駝來做一個例子
I hope to share with you what we have done in the past 30 years
希望跟大家分享我們在過去這30年來
What is the outcome of historical research on gender studies?
性別研究歷史研究的成果是怎麼樣
Then also as a congratulatory gift to celebrate the 90th anniversary of the Academia Sinica and the Eleventh Institute
那麼也作為一個中研院跟十一所90週年慶祝的一個賀禮
hope to
希望能夠
Let everyone be able to hear and be happy
讓大家能夠有點聽到有點高興的地方
History is basically a broken mirror and everything is actually broken
歷史基本上是碎鏡臨時啦所有東西其實都是破的啦
We are fighting together
我們就是通通拼拼拼拼
Let's see if we can spell it out
看能不能拼出一個樣子來
Sometimes it can look like a mess of refracted reflections
有時候看起來可能是折射反觀亂七八糟的
But it still looks a little bit
可是還是看得出一點點樣貌
The same is true for the study of gender or women's history
性別時或婦女的歷史研究其實也是這樣
thank you for listening
謝謝大家的聆聽
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you very much Mr. Li for your wonderful speech today
非常謝謝李老師今天精彩的演講
That's because we have limited time now
那因為我們現在時間有限
Teacher Li just mentioned that
剛剛李老師有提到說
This year is actually the 90th anniversary of Academia Sinica
今年其實是中研院90週年慶
So we will prepare a
所以我們會準備一個
A special coaster for the 90th anniversary of Academia Sinica
中研院90週年特製的一個杯墊
Wait a minute and open up to friends who have problems
給等一下開放有問題的朋友
that's because of time
那因為時間關係
We might just open up and ask three questions today, okay?
我們今天可能就開放問三個問題好不好
ok first
好 那第一位
hey ask the professor
嘿 請教教授
the one you just mentioned
剛剛您提到的那個
There are six kinds of women
有六種婆
ask that toothmaid
請教一下那個牙婆
what with that ex-wife
跟那個前婆是什麼
do something
是做一些什麼事的
Thanks
謝謝
intermediary
中間人做仲介的
A broker is a middleman
仲介就是做中間人做
The kind that sells as an intermediary
做仲介的那種賣賣的
According to the ex-wife
前婆的話有說是跳神婆
Actually it's kind of like
其實就有點像是
wife
老婆
The old castle, he said it was the old castle
老堡 他說是老堡
That means they are all that
那等於是他們都是那個
Wang Kilometer's
王公裡面的
no no no no
沒有沒有不是
Three aunts and six wives are not kings
三姑六婆不是王公裡面
If we want to say three aunts and six wives, we should say she is a professional woman.
我們要說三姑六婆應該說她是職業婦女吧
It may be said that it is an ancient professional woman
可能可以說是古代的職業婦女
However, the third aunt and the sixth wife
不過把三姑跟六婆
Fighting together is to make these nine kinds of people
鬥在一起 就是把這九種人
Get together and talk about them like this
湊在一起講說他們這樣子
They are three aunts and six wives. This is after the Yuan Dynasty.
是三姑六婆 這是元朝以後的事
in the age of what we do
就在我們所做的這個年代
I have sent every water hall
我已經在每到水堂送
Basically these people are normal working women
基本上這些人就是一般的職業婦女
But when someone thinks these women
但是當有人覺得這些女人
Ordinary women from good families should not talk to these outsiders
就一般的良家婦女不應該跟外面這些
when women walking around are together
到處走動的女人在一起的時候
From Yuan Dynasty to Ming Dynasty
元代 中夜以後到明代
start like a scholar
就開始有如學家
put some working women outside
把外面一些職業婦女
become a group
變成一種群體
call it three aunts and six wives
把它叫做三姑六婆
Then he said that women from good families had better not follow
然後就說良家婦女最好不要跟
Three aunts and six wives together
三姑六婆在一起
But in fact it is impossible
可是事實上是不可能的
Because our case in the Ming and Qing Dynasties is also good
因為我們在明清的一案也好
or
或者是
note novel or art inside
筆記小說或藝術裡面
still see like this
都還是這樣看到
Mrs. Wen will still go into the house
穩婆還是會進去家裡面
help give birth
幫忙節生小孩
Grandma will still help the broker to do business
大婆還是會幫忙仲介做生意
Matchmaker is still needed
媒婆還是非常需要
possible today
到今天可能
probably not today
今天大概不需要
at least when i was a kid
至少在我小時候
It seems that they are still needed
好像都還是很需要
so this is
所以這個是
It's just that Rusheng doesn't like this kind of women outside
就是如生不喜歡這種外面的女人
This is the division between male and female
就是男外女內的這個區隔
more and more
越來越
After the room between men and women became more and more strict
男女之房越來越嚴格之後
just some people who work outside
就把一些在外面工作的人
female becomes a
女性變成一種
anonymous group
無名化的群體
But in fact they are
可是其實他們就是
Women who work outside are like this
在外面工作的女性就這樣子
that mistress is
那師婆就是
The so-called Ning just mentioned that
所謂的寧剛提到的就是說
to be the family dancers
去當家庭跳舞的
I'm sorry
不是師婆才是跳神婆 對不起
dancing witch
跳神婆
What is dancing witch
什麼叫跳神婆
dancing witch is
跳神婆就是
go block
去擋吧
Find a way to summon the soul, what, what?
想辦法那個招魂啊什麼什麼
kind of religious
有點也是宗教
this is possible
這個有可能
It means that we boys serve wine and leave wine behind
就是我們男生有上酒留下酒
Those three aunts and six women stink
那三姑六婆臭起來
just had nine
剛剛有九個嘛
It means to drink and stay
就是下酒留的意思嘛
This master feels here
這師父覺得在這裡
ok thank you thank you
好 謝謝 謝謝
There is a picture of Beizhong military uniform you just mentioned
有一個你剛剛講的北中武服圖的那個
You said he himself had guarded his father for thirteen years
你說他本人為他的父親守上十三年
But I see his eldest son in the picture below is also three years old
可是我看你圖下面為他的長子也是三年
what happened
那是怎麼樣怎麼回事的
That's why the patrilineal family is so important
這就是父系家族非常重要的
Dad is the eldest son
爸爸為長子 弟長子
Because if the eldest son lives in the future,
因為這個長子將來他如果活著
should i die
是應該我死了
he wants to inherit me
他要繼承我
is the main axis of this paternal family is on him
是這個父系家族的主軸是在他身上
In the end he died before me
結果他竟然先我而亡
So I'm not for the love of children
所以我不是為了愛小孩的關係
I do it to honor the patrilineal lineage.
我是為了尊敬這個父系家族的傳承
So I have also been rotten for him for three years
所以我為他也是腐展翠三年
also the worst injury
也是最重的傷
so this father
所以這個父
That's why it's called the patrilineal family system
這就是為什麼叫做父系家族體系
Paternal haircut, paternal why is it called paternal paternal
父系理髮 父系為什麼叫父系父系父系是講
Dad is the core
爸爸才是核心
Everyone revolves around this man who is a father
所有的人都是圍繞著這個做爸爸的這個人
To regulate or regulate the relationship between relatives and inferiors
來規定或是來規範彼此的親屬尊卑關係
A child with his mother
一個小孩子跟他的媽媽
not because you gave birth to me
不是因為你生我
I'm the closest relationship with you
我就跟你是最近的關係
It depends on your relationship with my father
是看你跟我爸爸是什麼關係
You and my father are the wife's relationship
你跟我爸爸是正妻的關係
you are my aunt
你就是我的大媽
After you passed away, I just played for your husband for three years
你去世了我就是為你夫展吹三年
you gave birth to me
你生我
But your relationship with my dad is just bad
但是你跟我爸爸關係只是差
my dad's concubine
我爸爸的妾
If you die, there's nothing you can do
那你死了那也沒辦法
I have fewer husbands
我就是夫比較少的
Because all our relationships revolve around Dad
因為我們所有的關係都以爸爸為核心
This so-called traditional Chinese patrilineal family society means
這所謂傳統中國的父系家族社會的意思
Okay, let me recall what you just said
好 那我回憶你剛剛講的說
That production that vertical production
那個生產那個垂直生產
I traveled to Argentina last year
我去年去阿根廷去旅遊
their aboriginal local aborigines
他們那個原住民當地原住民
The localization of their production is on the wall
他們的生產的土化在牆壁上
on their original wall
他們的那個原始的牆壁上
vertical production
就是垂直生產
that knowledge
就是那個知識
and when he gave birth
而且他的生產的時候
His arms are still on that wall
他的手臂還撐在那個牆上
Said that there was that cruel hand on the wall
說牆上有那個狠的手的字
plug it in like this
這樣插下去
just like this
就是跟這個很一樣
then your side
那你這邊
Because you're all in Europe and look like that
因為你這邊都是歐洲有那個樣子
But that's from Argentina
可是那是阿根廷來美洲的
I echo your matter
我就呼應你這個件事情
OK
OK
Ask our colleagues who have done archaeological and anthropological surveys
問我們的同事有做考古人類學調查的
I said you stepped on the Amis
我說你們踏到阿美族的那個
How about it
怎麼樣
He said I went and when I came back he told me
他說我去了 我回來以後他跟我說
I asked and my interviewer said
我問了 然後我的訪問人就說
Yes, yes, I squat down and get down
有啊 有啊 我蹲一蹲就下來了
So actually by the end of the twenty-four seasons
所以其實到二十四季末二十四季末
Taiwan is still like this
台灣也都還是有這樣子
So the one who was lying in the hospital gave birth
所以那個躺在醫院生產
Then let the doctor do this
然後讓醫生來這樣這個
All are medical
全部都是醫療化以後的
very late quiet on human power
非常晚靜 在人類力子上
very short period of time
非常短的一段時間
Now actually because
那現在其實因為
The relationship between the industry and the city movement
駐產市運動的關係
Or a home birth, or a gentle birth
或是居家生產 或是什麼溫柔生產
Various sports appear
各種運動出現
So actually a while ago this topic
所以其實前之陣子這個題目
The group I'm currently in tender production with
我現在在溫柔生產的那個團體
Told once, all the midwives
講過一次 所有的那個產婆
Everyone came to me
通通都跑來跟我
Come and take a photo with me holding the cup
抱著杯比來跟我合照
I am also very happy
我也滿高興的
So now it's back again
所以現在其實又有恢復
Hope to take this living person as the main body
希望以這個生的這個人為主體
See how comfortable he is and how easy he is to move around
看他的舒服 他的走動方便
Instead of this one that is mainly based on the convenience of doctors
而不是以醫生方便為主體的這個
In fact, it is revival
其實又在復興當中
ask the teacher
請教老師喔
teacher
老師
The last word is Broken Mirror Temporary
最後是個字叫 碎鏡臨時
remind me to say
讓我想到就是說
Teachers can use this pedal
老師可以用這個踏片
then about sex
然後就有關性別
And then there are many places
然後還有跟很多地方
Many items are available
很多的項目都可以
Can do research on science
在學問上面都可以做研究
reminds me of being in that
讓我想到在那個
There are many steps in the forest of steles
碑林裡面有很多的踏片
In fact, using this site analogy
其實用這個遺址類推
In fact, it is tantamount to making a fuss out of a molehill
其實也是就等於小題大作
is that we can communicate with many
就是我們可以跟很多的
different categories
不同的類別
As a result, such research can be done
結果就可以做這樣的研究
Is it this way
是不是這樣
ok thank you teacher
好 謝謝老師
Materials actually help us understand
材料其實幫助我們理解
Many handed down documents above
很多傳世文獻上面
no way of knowing
沒有辦法知道的
The problem with the pedals
那踏片的問題
just say sometimes context
只是說有時候脈絡
not very clear
就不是很清楚
if you know where it comes from
如果你知道它從哪裡來
then what is the context
然後脈絡是什麼
Then make the content
然後做了內容的話
Just like Yuan Chuntuo
就可以像袁春托這個
there must be many things
一定會有很多東西
will help us open our eyes
就會幫助我們大開眼界
It's something we couldn't imagine
是我們原來沒有辦法想像的
thanks for your test
謝謝你的考驗
I will let you know before the end
最後結束之前也跟大家預告一下
Feast of Knowledge in October
十月份的知識饗宴
back to our tree science group
回到我們樹裡科學組
Director Chen Guixian of Fate Institute
會有緣分所的陳貴賢所長
Tell us about thermoelectric technology
為我們說熱電科技
Topics from domestic refrigerators to space communications
從家用冰箱到太空通信的主題
Everyone is welcome to sign up
歡迎大家藉實在報名參加
Then we thank Teacher Li again
那我們再謝謝李老師
Thanks
謝謝